<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A ladies legacie to her davghters. In three books. Composed of prayers and meditations, fitted for severall times, and upon severall occasions. As also several prayers for each day in the weeke. / By Madam Elizabeth Richardson, wife to the late Sir Thomas Richardson knight, Lord Chiefe Justice of the Kings Bench.</title>
            <author>Cramond, Elizabeth Richardson, Baroness, d. 1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1165_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210104</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868932</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868932</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121289</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121289)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1165[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A ladies legacie to her davghters. In three books. Composed of prayers and meditations, fitted for severall times, and upon severall occasions. As also several prayers for each day in the weeke. / By Madam Elizabeth Richardson, wife to the late Sir Thomas Richardson knight, Lord Chiefe Justice of the Kings Bench.</title>
                  <author>Cramond, Elizabeth Richardson, Baroness, d. 1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper, and are to be sold at his house in Little Britaine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf has blank recto, ornament on verso.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "novemb 24th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian women --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A <hi>LADIES</hi> LEGACIE TO HER DAVGHTERS.</p>
            <p>In three BOOKS.</p>
            <p>Compoſed of Prayers and Meditations, fitted for ſeverall times, and upon ſeverall occaſions.</p>
            <p>As alſo ſeverall Prayers for each day in the Weeke.</p>
            <p>By Madam <hi>Elizabeth Richardſon,</hi> wife to the late Sir <hi>Thomas Richardſon</hi> Knight, Lord Chiefe Juſtice of the Kings Bench.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Harper,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe in <hi>Little Britaine,</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>VIRTVTE HONOS ACQVIRITVR</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Prayers contained in theſe three Books.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>BOOK I.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Preface, or inducement to Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>Pag. 7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. A preparation to Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. A Prayer to the Holy Ghoſt.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. A Preface to any Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. A confeſſion of finnes, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. A Prayer for the Lords day, before we go to Church.</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. An entrance to Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. A ſhort thankſgiving at the firſt ſight at the morning light.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. A private morning Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9. A thankſgiving.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. A Prayer for the afternoone.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11. A ſhort Prayer for the night.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12. A ſhort Prayer in bed before ſleep.</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13. A Prayer before the receiving the Sacrament.</cell>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A ſhort meditation, direction, or preparation, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14. A thankſgiving after the holy Communion, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15. A ſhort Prayer for concluſion to any Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16. A Prayer for the Lords day in the afternoone, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17. A Prayer to the Trinity for direction and acceptance from God of all our Prayers.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18. Another Prayer for the afternoone for many ſeverall bleſſings.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19. A Prayer of three petitions to the bleſſed Trinity, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20. The concluſion to this book. &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21. A thankſgiving to Almighty God, for his moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſervation of my noble kinſwoman, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22. A Petition of the Author for her ſelfe.</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:4"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>BOOK II.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>AN Exhortation concerning Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>Pag. 53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. A ſhort Petition to precede any other Prayers.</cell>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. A Prayer to God the Holy Ghoſt, for the true ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace in Prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. A ſhort preface before any other Prayers for the Lords day.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. A Prayer for the Lords day at firſt awaking.</cell>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. A Prayer for the Lords day in the morning, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. A Prayer to be ſaid at the Church, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. Another ſhorter Prayer to the ſame purpoſe.</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. A prayer afer the Sermon is ended, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9. A prayer for the Lords day at night, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. A prayer for Munday to God the Father, at firſt awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</cell>
                     <cell>65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11. A morning prayer for Munday to God the Father.</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12. A prayer to God the Father for Munday night.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13. The concluſion for Munday, to be ſaid laſt.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14. A prayer at firſt awaking for Tueſday.</cell>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15. A prayer for Tueſday morning.</cell>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16. A prayer for Tueſday at night.</cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17. The concluſion for Tueſday, to be ſaid at night, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>79</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18. A prayer for Wedneſday at firſt awaking.</cell>
                     <cell>80</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19. A prayer for Wedneſday morning.</cell>
                     <cell>82</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20. An evening prayer for Wedneſday.</cell>
                     <cell>85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21. The concluſion for Wedneſday night.</cell>
                     <cell>87</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22. A prayer for Thurſday morning at firſt awaking.</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23. A prayer for Thurſday morning.</cell>
                     <cell>90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24. A prayer for Thurſday night.</cell>
                     <cell>93</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25. The concluſion for Thurſday night.</cell>
                     <cell>95</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26. A prayer for Friday at firſt awaking.</cell>
                     <cell>96</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27. A morning prayer for Friday.</cell>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>28. A prayer for Friday night.</cell>
                     <cell>101</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29. The concluſion for Friday night.</cell>
                     <cell>103</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30. A prayer at firſt awaking for Saturday.</cell>
                     <cell>104</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:121289:4"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31. A prayer for Saturday morning.</cell>
                     <cell>105</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32. A prayer for Saturday night.</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33. The concluſion for Saturday night, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>111</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>BOOK III.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. A Short Preface before any other prayers or petitions.</cell>
                     <cell>113</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. A ſhort thanskgiving at firſt ſight of the morning light.</cell>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. A prayer for helpe in preſent temptation, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>114</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Munday. 1. A thankſgiving to the bleſſed Trinity.</cell>
                     <cell>116</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tueſday. 2. A prayer for grace and true faith</cell>
                     <cell>117</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wedneſday. 3. A prayer for charity.</cell>
                     <cell>119</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Thurſday. 4. A prayer for ſpirituall graces.</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Friday 5. A prayer for defence, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>123</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Saturday. 6. A prayer for the true ſpirit of prayer, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>124</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A ſhort prayer to be joyned to the former prayers, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>125</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. A prayer containing 7 humble petitions, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. A ſorrowfull widows prayer, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>133</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. A prayer for mercy in time of affliction.</cell>
                     <cell>136</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. A prayer for due preparation before the Communion of the Lords Supper.</cell>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. An humble thankſgiving after the receiving, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>145</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. A meditation concerning death.</cell>
                     <cell>147</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. A prayer to live bleſſedly, and dye happily.</cell>
                     <cell>154</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. A prayer to be prepared for a happy death, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>156</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. A prayer in ſickneſſe, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>159</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. A prayer in the time of ſickneſſe to be fitted, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>161</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. My prayer of thankſgiving, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>165</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. My concluſion, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>167</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. Another ſhort prayer.</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:5"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121289:5"/>
            <head>A LADIES LEGACIE TO HER DAVGHTERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y dearly beloved Daughters (of which number, I account my two ſons wives, my daughters in law, the Counteſſe of Marlborough, and Mrs. <hi>Francis Aſhbournham,</hi> to be mine alſo) aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my ſelfe of your loves and kinde acceptance, I preſent this little Booke unto you all, which being mine, I hope you will carefully receive it, as comming from my love and affection towards you, and that you will pleaſe for my ſake, the more to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it to your good; to which I will (while I live) dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adde my prayers and bleſſing for your preſent and future happineſſe: and that this my poore labour may prove a happy furtherance to all your good endeavours towards vertue and piety: Therefore let me as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121289:6"/> intreat and prevaile with you to eſteem ſo well of it, as often to peruſe, ponder, practice, and make uſe of this Booke according to my intention, though of it ſelfe unworthy; for you ſhall finde your greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe will be in the true feare, conſtant love, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervice of Almighty God, which never faileth of comfort and reward, he being the only and moſt liberall giver of all good gifts and bleſſings, both ſpirituall and temporall; to whoſe infinite mercy and gracious gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, I moſt humbly commend you all, and daily will doe the like in my prayers ſo long as I live. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, moſt deare hearts, conſider, That theſe Petitions are preſented to a moſt bountifull and Al-ſufficient Lord, that vouchſafeth in Chriſt to make us his adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted children, and to be our Gracious Father, who gave his only Son for us, in whom he will deny us nothing: And greater benefits then here are asked, cannot bee received; therefore give me leave, ſince I have ſuch great intereſt in you, to perſwade and obtaine of you all, often to beg theſe bleſſings of God, by theſe prayers faithfully offered up unto his Majeſty: Whereby you ſhall glorifie his holy Name, make your ſelves eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſed, and bring much joy and comfort to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Mother, ELIZ. ASHBOURNHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121289:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>I</hi> Had no purpoſe at all when I writ theſe books, for the uſe of my ſelfe, and my children, to make them publicke; but have beene lately over perſwaded by ſome that much deſired to have them. Therefore I have adventured to beare all cenſures, and deſire their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and pardon, whoſe exquiſite judgements may finde many blameworthy faults, juſtly to condemne my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; which I thus excuſe, the matter is but devotions or prayers, which ſurely concernes and belongs to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as well as to the beſt learned men: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope herein, I neither wrong nor give offence to any, which I ſhould be very loath to doe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <p>This Booke was written at <hi>Chelſey</hi> in the yeare 1625. by <hi>E. A.</hi> at the Duke of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> houſe, a part whereof was lent me by the good Dutches, my moſt honoured Lady, when the great ſickneſſe was in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121289:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter to my foure Daughters,</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, Frances, Anne, <hi>and</hi> Katherine Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bournham, <hi>of whom three were then unmarried, only</hi> Anne <hi>was married to Sir</hi> Edward Deering <hi>Knight and Baronet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My deare Children:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have long and much grieved for your misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and want of preferments in the world: but now I have learned in what eſtate ſoever I am, therewith to be content, and to account theſe vile and tranſitorie things to be but vaine and loſſe, ſo I may win Chriſt the fountaine of all bliſſe, wiſhing you with me, to condemne that which neglecteth you, and ſet your hearts and affections on better ſubjects, ſuch as are above, more certain and permanent; and feare not but what is needfull for this preſent life ſhall bee ſupplyed by him who beſt knows our wants: and had it not been for your ſakes (whoſe advancements love and nature bindeth me to ſeeke) I had prevented the ſpite of my enemies, and forſaken the World before it deſpiſed me: But though I am ſo unhappy as to be left deſtitute, not able to raiſe you portions of wealth, yet ſhall I joy as much to adde unto the portion of Grace, which I truſt, and pray, that God will give to each of you, to whoſe mercy I daily commit you, nothing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121289:7"/> doubting but that he will receive you into the number of thoſe fatherleſſe he graciouſly taketh care of, if you omit not to ſerve and depend upon him faithfully, for he never faileth them that truſt in him. God is as free and ready to give as we to aske, and contrary to the World, he grows not weary of importunate ſuters, but often deferreth his bleſſings to make us the more earneſt for them. Neither hath the Lord withdrawn his favour ſo from us as to leave us utterly deſolate to deſpair, but hath graciouſly raiſed us comfort by honourable friends to be carefull and deare parents unto us, whom God preſerve and ſhew mercy to them and theirs, as they have done to us. And here I ſend you a motherly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and commend this my labour into your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving acceptance; that in remembring your poor mother, you may be alſo put in minde to performe your humble duty and ſervice to our heavenly Father, who hath created us to his owne glory and ſervice; and all we can performe, comes far ſhort of what we owe unto him; yet is he well pleaſed, if we returne (for all his mercies) but obedience, and the ſacrifice of praiſe and calling upon his holy Name. Now prayer being the winged meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to carry our requeſts and wants into the ears of the Lord (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith) he will praiſe the Lord ſeven times a day, and prevent the light to give thanks unto God; and indeed, who can awake to enjoy the light and pleaſure of the day, and not begin the ſame with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of the Lords gracious direction in all things, and deſire of his bleſſing upon us, and all that we have or doe? Or how can we poſſeſſe or hourely receive ſo many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121289:8"/> favours and benefits from God, and not offer unto him an evening ſacrifice of thanksgiving? Or who dares adventure to paſſe the dreadfull night, the time of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and yeeld themſelves to ſleep, the image of death, before they are at peace with God, by begging pardon for their ſins, and craving his protection and care over them in the night? I know you may have many better inſtructers then my ſelf, yet can you have no true mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but me, who not only with great paine brought you into the world, but do now ſtill travell in care for the new birth of your ſoules; to bring you to eternall life, which is my chiefeſt deſire, and the height of my hopes: And howſoever this my endeavour may be contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible to many, (becauſe a womans) which makes me not to joyne my ſons with you, leſt being men, they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrue my well-meaning; yet I preſume that you my daughters will not refuſe your Mothers teaching (which I wiſh may be your ornament, and a crown of glory to you) who I hope will take in the beſt part my carefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, for your preſent and future happineſſe, towards which I have not failed to give you the beſt breeding in my power, to bring you to vertue and piety, which I eſteem the greateſt treaſure; and ſure I am, it leads you to him that is the giver of all good things, both ſpirituall and temporall; to whoſe infinite mercy I moſt humbly commend you, who I truſt will fulfill all your neceſſities, through the riches of his grace, and make you perfect in all good workes to doe his will. And the God of peace ſanctifie you throughout, that your whole ſpirits, ſoules and bodies, may bee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121289:8"/> kept blameleſſe unto the comming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which ſhall bee the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 23.</note> joy of your moſt loving Mother,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Eliz. Aſhbournham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <div type="preface">
               <head>A Preface, or inducement to Prayer.</head>
               <p>THe great God, and Lord of Heaven <note place="margin">Acts 17. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 27. 8. Cap. 23. 14. 17. Rom 1. 19, 20.</note> and Earth, whoſe wee are, and whom only we ought to ſerve, hath not left himſelfe without witneſſe: For as much as that which may be knowne of God, is made manifeſt unto us, for the inviſible things of him, that is his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power and Godhead, are ſeen by <note place="margin">His power Godhead. Rom. 5. 5. 8 9.</note> the creation of the world, being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in his workes, to the intent wee ſhould bee without excuſe. Alſo the infinite love of God is ſhed abroad in <note place="margin">His love, Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Jo. 3. 16. Jo. 4: 9. 10 3. 16. Jo. 15, 23. 10. 15.</note> our hearts, and ſet out towards us in the moſt gracious worke of our redemption, in that Chriſt died for us being ſinners, and when we were enemies, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled us unto himſelf by the death of his only begotten Son, whom God ſent into the world that wee might live
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121289:9"/> through him, and be ſaved by his life, <note place="margin">Chriſts love.</note> greater love then this can none have, to lay downe his owne life for us. Now there are three ſpeciall things amongſt many that doe alwaies binde and urge us to the acknowledgement of God, to the love of his Majeſty, and the often <note place="margin">His bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits. Of our ſins<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> calling upon his holy Name, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, the multitude and greatneſſe of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits towards us, for which we ought to give him continuall thanks. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the infiniteneſſe of our grievous ſins, <note place="margin">Our m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> for which we muſt of neceſſity daily aske mercy, and pardon from him. Thirdly, our owne manifold miſeries and infirmities, for which we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſeek reliefe and remedy. The firſt of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe <hi>David</hi> conſidered, ſaying, What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all <note place="margin">Pſal. 116. 12, 13.</note> his benefits towards me? I will take the cup of ſalvation and call upon the name <note place="margin">9. 1.</note> of the Lord, I will praiſe him with my whole heart all the daies of my life. All his Pſalmes are full of thankſgiving. To the ſecond, Chriſt inviteth us ſaying, Come unto me all ye that are weary and <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 28.</note> heavy laden, and I will eaſe you. If any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the juſt:</hi> He is the <note place="margin">1 Jo. 2. 1. 2. 1.</note> reconciliation for the ſins of the whole <note place="margin">9.</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121289:9"/> world: And if wee acknowledge our ſinnes, he is faithfull and juſt to forgive, and cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſſe. For the third, wee are incouraged by God himſelfe, ſaying, Call upon me in the day of trouble, ſo will I deliver <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 15. Iſay. Matth. 8. 17.</note> thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me; for he will have mercy upon us, and heal all our infirmities; and when wee are in miſery, he ſaveth and delivereth us. Now for the performance of our duty in thankſgiving, the blotting out of all our offences, and the releaſe of our miſeries, with the continuance of Gods grace and favour in all things, the chiefe and only way to find and obtain all, is rightly to ſeek, and truly to ſerve the Lord by prayer, who is the author and fountain of all goodnes, grace and mercy; Every good gift comming from above, even from him that freely ſaith, Aske, and yee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; ſeek, and yee ſhall finde; knock, and it ſhall be opened unto you; for hee that is Lord over all, is rich unto all that call upon him in truth; and the prayer of the faithfull, avails much, if it be fervent; for faithfull and devout prayer is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall intercourſe and communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Lord and us; and it is like <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> ladder, by which our prayers make
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121289:10"/> our wants aſcend unto God, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie deſcend downe upon us; for with the heart man believeth unto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and with the mouth we confeſſe unto ſalvation; but take heed in ſending up thy deſires, prefer the good of the <note place="margin">Col. 3. 2.</note> ſoule, before the pleaſures or content of thy body; and ſet thy affections on things that are above: Firſt, ſeeke the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 33.</note> of God and his righteouſneſſe, and all other wants ſhall be ſupplied by his mercie, according to his will, and our neceſſities. And when thou entereſt into the houſe of God, take heed thou offer not unto him the ſacrifice of fooles, but before thou prayeſt, prepare thy ſelf, <note place="margin">Col. 3. 2. Eccleſ. 4. 17. 18. 22.</note> thy heart and tongue, as <hi>David</hi> did, leſt thou tempt God to diſpleaſure: Be not raſh with thy mouth, nor let thy heart be haſty to utter a thing before God: But ere thou preſume to preſent thy ſelf, <note place="margin">Pſal. 108. 1.</note> or ſervice unto the Lord, meditate upon theſe three things: Firſt, of the reverence we owe to the great Majeſty of God, <note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> in whoſe preſence we are, and to whom we muſt ſpeake; this brings humility and lowlineſſe of ſpirit, which makes us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto him. Secondly, of our knowledge and beliefe of the Lords <note place="margin">Eſay 65. 24. Job 15. 16</note> ſweet and gracious promiſes, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121289:10"/> cauſeth boldneſſe to come unto him, with ſure confidence of being heard. Thirdly, of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe, and what apprehenſion we have of our owne wants and miſeries, and the great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Gods helpe and mercy to relieve us. This makes us to know and hate our ſelves, and to love and honour God, in whom is all our help, hope, and happineſſe; therefore with devout re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, zeal, humility, and true faith, flye unto his mercy, and ceaſe not to call often (as <hi>David</hi> did) ſeven times a day upon the holy Name of the Lord, Pſal. 119. 164. by whom we ſhall bee ſaved, Rom. 10. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>1. <hi>A preparation to Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Everlaſting fountaine of all goodneſſe, and well-ſpring of grace, without whoſe ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſiſtance, we are altogether unapt and unable to performe any duty or ſervice that may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto thee: Vouchſafe therefore (deare Lord) to helpe mine infirmities, who cannot of my ſelfe pray as I ought, but let thy holy Spirit direct and teach me truly to call upon thy divine Name, with a penitent and faithfull heart, an humble, contrite, and lowly ſpirit, a quiet, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and recollected minde, freed from the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and cares of this vilde world, or the love of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121289:11"/> this preſent life; ſo as I may dedicate my ſelfe wholly unto thee a living ſacrifice, faithfully and devoutly to ſerve thee now, and all the daies of my life. O Lord, make mee to lift up innocent hands, with a pure heart; and guide thou my lips with wiſdome, and ſet a watch of grace before my mouth, that my tongue may not offend thee at any time, but duly praiſe thy glorious Name, now and for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>2. <hi>A Prayer to the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Gracious Lord Holy Ghoſt, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to fit and prepare my heart, and to direct and aſſiſt me in the right and true perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty and ſervice now of prayer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my God: Thou underſtandeſt my diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of my ſelfe to any goodneſſe: neither know I how to pray as I ought, except thy holy Spirit teach me: Therefore I earneſtly and humbly pray thee to give mee thy grace and true ſpirit of prayer, that ſo I may now and at all times offer up my petitions and praiſes, in calling upon thy great and glorious Name, in a right faithfull and acceptable manner, to the glory of God, and the good and comfort of me thy poor ſervant, in ſoul and body, with the furtherance of my ſalvation, through Jeſus Chriſt, my bleſſed and only Saviour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:121289:11"/>
               <head>3. <hi>A Preface to any Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O My Lord, in all humility I come unto thee, the giver of all grace; thou knoweſt my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aptneſſe to any goodneſſe, thou haſt given me an earneſt deſire to pleaſe thee, make perfect thine owne good worke, and grant me a ready will and ability to performe my humble duty herein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, that ſo I may ſincerely and intirely love, fear and honour thee above all, and moſt carefully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey thy bleſſed will in all things: Good Father, let thy manifold mercies cover my infinite offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from thy All-ſeeing eyes, and by thy grace caſt all vaine thoughts, and ſinfull hindrances out of my ſoule, that thy ſacred Spirit may direct my ſpirit to pray with due reverence to thy Majeſty, confidence in thy mercy, with ſure truſt in thy promiſes, and feare of thy judgements. And that I may offer up all my ſupplications unto thee, with unfeigned zeale, true faith, humility and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Sweet Lord, make me heartily thankfull unto thee for all thy bleſſings, and let all my peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions tend to thy glory; ſo as I may finde favour with thee, that thou wilt be graciouſly pleaſed to heare and accept of me and my prayers, that they may enter into thy preſence, and obtaine pardon of all my ſins paſt, with grace to frame my life in true obedience to all thy Commandements, the reſt of my daies to come, that ſo my laſt end may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121289:12"/> be happy, and after death I may enjoy the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to live with thee, my Lord, for evermore, through the merits and paſſion of my only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt, So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>4. <hi>A confeſſion of ſins, with a prayer for remiſſion, taken partly out of the prayer of</hi> Manaſſes.</head>
               <p>ALmighty Lord God of our fathers, who haſt made heaven and earth, with all the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof, who haſt bound the ſea by the word of thy commandement, whoſe terrible and glorious Name all men doe feare, and tremble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy powerfull judgements; for the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thy great Majeſty cannot be borne, and thy angry threatnings againſt ſinners is import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and who can ſtand in thy preſence when thou art offended? But yet (O Lord) thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promiſes to penitent ſinners are unmeaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and unſpeakable; for thou art the moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord, full of mercy and great compaſſion, and of long ſuffering, that deſires not the death of a ſinner, but that he ſhould repent and live, who of thy great goodneſſe haſt promiſed to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and forgiveneſſe to them that ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, that they may be ſaved. Now thou therefore (moſt dear Lord) who cameſt not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance (of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121289:12"/> whom I am the chiefe) thou of thy infinite mercy (I truſt) haſt appointed repentance and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion unto me, whoſe ſins are in number above the ſands of the ſea, or the haires of my head; I have committed much evill, and have omitted to doe the good I ought, for I have neglected all my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſervice towards thee, and am not worthy to be called thy ſervant, nor to behold the height of heaven, or to looke up unto the place where thine honour dwelleth, for the multitude of mine iniquities have bowed me downe, and as a weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty burden are too heavy for me; I am depreſſed with the load of my ſinnes, and oppreſſed with the feare of due puniſhment for them; for I have juſtly provoked thy wrath (O God) and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied my tranſgreſſions before thee: I have not done thy will, neither thy holy Commandements have I obeyed. Now therefore (O my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) to thee I humbly bow the knee of my heart, imploring thy mercy, and beſeeching thee of grace: I will confeſſe my ſins againſt my ſelfe, and will not hide my unrighteouſneſſe from thee: I have ſinned (O Lord) I have grievouſly ſinned, &amp; I acknowledge my manifold offences; for which I have nothing to anſwer, but (like the Publican) Lord be mercifull unto me a miſerable ſinner: Wherefore I moſt humbly intreat thee to forgive me, my ſweet Saviour forgive me, and deſtroy me not with mine iniquities, be not angry with me for ever, neither condemne me in thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121289:13"/> to the lower part of the earth, and reſerve not evill for me hereafter: But (deare Father) make me of that bleſſed number, to whom thou imputeſt not their faults, and whoſe ſinnes by my Saviours righteouſneſſe are covered; for thou art the God of the juſt, and the God of them that will repent, and in poore me, thou wilt ſhew all thy goodneſſe and pity: for thou wilt pardon and ſave me that am ſo vilde and unworthy, even of thine owne great grace and mercy: Therefore I will turn my ſteps into thy waies, and will ſeeke thy will, and obey thee with my whole heart: I will praiſe thee all the daies of my life, and for ever: And let the heavens and the earth praiſe thy eternall Majeſty; for thine is all glory for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <head>5. <hi>A Prayer for the Lords day, before we goe to Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Eternall God, moſt high Creator; preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and diſpoſer of all things: to thee is due all praiſe, honour, and worſhip, for thou art our gracious Lord, the only author of all our good, by whom we live, move, and have our being. O with what humble reverence, and devotion ought we to prepare our ears and hearts, to hear, receive and performe any thing which concerneth thy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121289:13"/> moſt ſacred Majeſty; and even to take heed unto our feet when we enter into the houſe of God, that our waies may not offend thee: Neither ought we to preſume to take thy holy Name into our mouths, except we endeavoured our ſelves to be reformed by thy lawes. Thou, O God, art Lord God of Sabbath, and haſt inobled this day by the glorious reſurrection of thy Son our Lord Jeſus, and by the guidance of the Holy Ghoſt in thy bleſſed Apoſtles, and Catholicke Church, haſt ordained it for thy publicke ſervice, honour and worſhip: ſo make me to ſerve thee therein with due feare and reverence. I moſt humbly beſeech thee to ſanctifie my heart and ſoule to the true performance of thy bleſſed will in rightly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame; and leave me not unto my owne weakneſſe and diſability, who can of my ſelfe neither thinke well, nor doe any thing that is good, for all my ſtrength and righteouſneſſe is in Chriſt my Redeemer: Aſſiſt me therefore (ſweet Saviour) with thy Spirit of grace to ceaſe from ſin, and all worldly workes, or earthly cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons this day, that may withdraw me from thy fear and ſervice: And give me an attentive eare to hearken diligently to thy divine word: Open my heart as thou didſt the heart of <hi>Lydia,</hi> that with true underſtanding, I may receive, and faithfully keep the ſame, with a conſcionable care to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what I ſhall learne thereby, devoutly calling upon thy moſt holy Name. and uſing due reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121289:14"/> in all my actions before thee: And good Lord, bleſſe thy ſervant whom thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this day to inſtruct and direct us in thy word and will; open to him the doore of utterance, and give him the true underſtanding of thy holy word, that according to thy gracious pleaſure all may be ſaved that come unto the knowledge of thy truth, and that he may be faithfull in thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, rightly to diſpoſe thy divine myſteries, and to teach in faith and verity: And grant that I may heare with due attention, and reſolve to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and practice all good inſtructions, with true intention to thy glory, and the furtherance of my ſalvation, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>6. <hi>An entrance to Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God of mercy, thou wilt not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould turne from his wicked waies and live: Vouchſafe to knit (deare Lord) my ſoule unto thee, that I may truly fear thee, and unfeignedly love thee, dedicating my ſelfe unto thy ſervice, and ſetting mine affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and deſires in all true obedience, to ſeeke above all things thy glory, thy Kingdome, and thy righteouſneſſe; that ſo all thy graces may daily increaſe in me, and my humble and unperfect ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in calling on thy holy name, may grow daily
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121289:14"/> more faithfull and fervent, now and at all times to be acceptable unto thee, through the merits of thy deare Son, and my only Saviour, in whom thou art well-pleaſed, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>7. <hi>A ſhort thanksgiving at the firſt ſight of the morning light.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord, I bleſſe thee for my health, reſt and preſervation this laſt night, and all my time paſt: And now moſt humbly pray thee give mee grace ſo to ſpend this day, that ſome glory may redound unto thee by my ſervice, ſome benefit and good unto them with whom I live, by my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and ſome further aſſurance unto my ſelfe of thy favour, and my eternall ſalvation, through Jeſus Chriſt my Redeemer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <head>8. <hi>A private morning Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ETernall God, and my moſt loving Father, in all humility of ſoule, and unfeigned acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of my bounden duty, I humbly preſent my ſinfull ſelfe here before thy Throne of grace and glory; beſeeching thee to ſtrike an awfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence into my heart, leſt my preſumption and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121289:15"/> want of due reſpect towards thy great Majeſty; ſhould turne my prayers into ſinne. And ſeeing without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, indue me, good Lord, with true faith to believe, and apply unto my owne ſoule, all thy moſt gracious promiſes in Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be my righteouſneſſe, redemption, and the reconciliation of my ſins; his pretious bloud I know is all ſufficient to ſatisfie thy juſt diſpleaſure againſt me, and to make me, through him, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare pure, holy, and acceptable before thee: But of my ſelfe, alas, I confeſſe that I am poor, wretched, miſerable, and wholly corrupt both in ſoule and body, the chiefe of all ſinners, guilty of the breach of all thy Commandements, ſuch an one as in whom is no goodneſſe, and to whom there is nothing due, but ſhame and utter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ever! Lord give me a lively apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſight of my wofull eſtate, that with true faith, contrition, and unfeigned repentance, I lay hold on thy mercy and gracious pardon, in thy beloved Son my only Saviour, humbly beſeeching thee (O dear Lord) to accept his bleſſed death, as an abſolute diſcharge for all mine offences; ſo as my ſins may never be imputed unto me, but that all my infirmities may be healed by his wounds; for I know thy mercy is above all thy works, and thou delighteſt not in the death of a poor ſinner. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will wait for thy ſalvation, relie on thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, and truſt in thee for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:121289:15"/>
               <head>9. <hi>A thanksgiving.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will praiſe the Name of the Lord becauſe he is good, and his mercy endureth for ever; for thou haſt many waies extended thy great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards me, thine unworthy ſervant, which I acknowledge with all humble thankfulneſſe; for who am I, that thou ſhouldeſt be mindfull of me in mercy, to refreſh me this night paſt with quiet reſt, and to defend both my ſoule and body from all the perills thereof, preſerving me by thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious providence all my life hitherto, from many evills and juſt puniſhments that my ſinnes have deſerved, ſhould have fallen upon me: And thy mercies are renewed every morning: O Lord, thy compaſſions faile not, but thou haſt multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy benefits towards me, both ſpirituall and temporall; which I beſeech thee for Chriſt Jeſus ſake ſtill to continue and increaſe, eſpecially thy favour in beſtowing all ſpirituall graces on mee needfull to ſalvation. O let thy holy Spirit direct me in every word and good worke, and fill me with the fruit of righteouſneſſe, ſo as I may have a holy care this day and ever, to live as in thy ſight, and to ſtudy to pleaſe and obey thee in all things, with reverence and feare, in a pure, holy, and blameleſſe converſation. O God, knit my ſoule unto thee, and create a new and upright heart within me, and ſanctifie me throughout, in ſoule,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121289:16"/> body and ſpirit, that I may give up my ſelfe a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſacrifice, holy and acceptable unto thee, and may be preſerved from all ſin and evill, this day and for ever: crucifie my ſinfull fleſh with the luſts thereof, and withdraw mine affections from the love of this vile world, and fix my deſires on things that are above, where my Saviour ſitteth at thy right hand, who is my treaſure, my hope and help, with whom I truſt to live for evermore, Amen. And further I beg all theſe bleſſings in the name, merits and mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, concluding in that perfect prayer which he hath ſanctified and left us ſaying, Our Father, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="prayer">
               <head>10. <hi>A Prayer for the afternoone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt Gracious God, and my mercifull Father in Jeſus Chriſt: how exceedingly are wee wretched creatures bound unto thy excellent Majeſty for that unſpeakable priviledge which thou vouchſafeſt unto mortall man, to have free liberty and acceſſe (through Chriſt) unto thy gracious preſence, there to unfold our woes, to powre out our ſoules, and lay open our griefes and deſires before the immortall God, who is ready to heare, and art both able and willing to relieve and helpe us? This imboldneth me (unworthy wretch) to preſent my perſon and petitions unto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121289:16"/> thy grace, and to call upon thy holy name through thy beloved Son: Lord let the words of my mouth, and the meditations of my heart, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies right and acceptable in thy ſight, my ſtrength and my Redeemer; for thou knoweſt my nature and ſubſtance, being but fleſh and bloud, how corrupt and fraile it is, ſo that I am not of my ſelfe able to performe any holy duty as I ought, neither to will or do any thing that is good, without thou grant me the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, to ſanctifie my thoughts, to guide my tongue, and to helpe my infirmities: what am I but duſt and aſhes, a moſt vile and miſerable ſinner, conceived and borne in iniquity, and my tranſgreſſions are daily multiplied, adding ſinne unto ſinne till they be innumerable? how have I miſpent this preſent day, the ſinnes whereof, may juſtly provoke thy heavy diſpleaſure againſt me, having throughout my whole life, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all evill, and omitted all good, and have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the performance of my bounden duty and ſervice towards thee upon every flight occaſion; and which is worſt of all, cuſtome of ſinning, hath ſeared up my conſcience, and deprived me of the true ſight and ſenſe of my ſins and wofull eſtate, and bred ſuch a fearfull hardneſſe in my heart, that I cannot duly repent as I ought, and as the greatneſſe of my fault requires? Thou haſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led often, and ſought to reclaime me, and haſt waited to have mercy on me, but I have refuſed,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121289:17"/> and hated to be reformed, careleſſely neglecting thy infinite patience, long ſufferance, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards me. But now to thee, O God of mercy, I bring my heavy laden ſoule, caſting my ſelfe downe at thy feet, beſeeching thee, O Lord, to receive me to grace and favour, and reject me not as I have deſerved, but convert thou me, and I ſhall be changed: make me turne unto thee in true contrition, that thou maieſt returne unto me in gracious compaſſion, to forgive all mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, remit my ungratefulneſſe, and remember my offences no more. O waſh and cleanſe my ſinfull ſoule in the pure bloud of that innocent Lambe, that I may feele the vertue of his death, to ſlay all ſin in me, and the power of his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to raiſe me to newneſſe of life, in true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all thy Commandements; and with a child-like love, feare to offend thee, ſtriving to pleaſe thee in all things, that ſo I may obtaine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and mercy in thy ſight, both for thy bleſſing in this life, and eternall ſalvation after death. through thy dear Son, and my only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <head>11. <hi>A ſhort Prayer for night.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God, the fountaine of all goodneſſe, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and thankfully acknowledge, although I am altogether unworthy of the leaſt of thy mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121289:17"/> mercies; yet have I great experience of thy infinite goodneſſe, bounty and favour, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my ſoule and body all my time paſt, this day, and alwaies, preſerving me from all the evills which ſin and nature have made me ſubject unto, with a gracious ſupply daily ever ſince I was born, of all things needfull for this preſent life: For all which I humbly bow the knee of my heart and ſoule unto thy glorious Majeſty; but eſpecially for all thy graces furthering my ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt, I bleſſe and praiſe thy moſt holy name, yeelding all poſſible and hearty thanks for all thy benefits vouchſafed to mee, the continuance whereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I humbly beg at thy gracious hands, commending and committing my ſoule and body into thy mercifull protection this night and ever, praying thee to preſerve me therein from all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills, ſin or evill, for thou Lord only keepeſt mee in ſafety: now ſtretch out thy wings of grace and mercy over me, that while ſleep ſeizeth upon my body, let not ſecurity oppreſſe my ſoule, but ſo ſanctifie all outward refreſhings unto me, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may bee the more fit and able to ſerve thee faithfully all my life to come, that taking quiet reſt, becauſe thou Lord ſuſtaineſt me, I may alſo when this life ceaſeth, lay downe my head in thy peace, and be made partaker of thy glory, through thy mercies and Chriſts merits, with the aſſiſtance of the bleſſed Spirit. To whom, O Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be all praiſe, power, dominion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121289:18"/> and glory now and for ever, Amen: Continuing my prayers further as Chriſt hath taught us, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Our Father, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="prayer">
               <head>12. <hi>A ſhort Prayer in bed before ſleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEare Lord, receive me this night and alwaies, into thy gracious protection, to give mee now health, ſafety, and reſt, if it be thy will: And dear God, when I ſhall enter into my long ſleep of death, vouchſafe to ſanctifie, and prepare my ſoule for eternall life, by the aſſiſtance of thy grace and holy Spirit, before thou call me away hence; and grant me a happy and bleſſed depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this world, that thou maieſt receive me into thy favour and mercy, to be with mee in my death, that I may dye in the Lord, and reſt in peace, and obtaine a bleſſed reſurrection, that ſo I may be accepted to live with thee, to praiſe thy great and holy name for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <head>13. <hi>A Prayer before the receiving the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Moſt ſweet Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and my deare Lord, who art the author and finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of my faith, redemption, and ſalvation, the life
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121289:18"/> and food of my ſoule: I moſt miſerable ſinner, preſuming nothing at all on mine owne merits or worthineſſe, but truſting wholly in thy infinite mercy and goodneſſe, doe feare and tremble to appeare before thy Majeſty, or to come unto the table of this heavenly banquet: But thou Lord Jeſus who graciouſly calleſt me, and all heavy laden ſinners, accept in mercy the will for the deed, in that I am unworthy and ill prepared to preſume into thy preſence; and vouchſafe me the aſſiſtance of thy divine Spirit, I humbly beſeech thee, in this holy action, that my duty and ſervice therein may bee acceptable in thy ſight: And powre down thy heavenly bleſſing upon this thy holy Ordinance of thy Word and Sacraments, that they may be effectuall to revive, ſtrengthen, and ſupply in me all ſanctifying and ſaving graces needfull to the due and right performance of this ſacred duty in an acceptable manner, whereby to enlighten my underſtanding with thy grace to the right knowledge of thee and thy truth; and work in me a lively true faith, wherewith I may lay hold and apply unto my ſicke ſoule all the ſweet and comfortable promiſes and benefits purchaſed by the bitter death of my ſweet Saviour: Indue me alſo with moſt unfeigned and hearty ſorrow and repentance for all my great and grievous ſins and offences committed againſt thee; for all which I moſt humbly beg thy gracious pardon: and grant me ſuch perfect love and charity, that I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121289:19"/> may ſincerely, with all due reverence and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, love thee, my God, with all my heart, ſoul and ſtrength, and may love my neighbour as my ſelfe, yea my very enemies for Chriſts ſake; that ſo I may rightly receive this bleſſed Sacrament, being prepared by thy grace as I ought to bee: And let, O Lord, thy pretious bloud ſhed for me, cleanſe and waſh away all my ſins, and the breaking of thy pretious body, heale all the wounds of my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſoule, that by the gracious operation of the Holy Ghoſt, I may be inwardly and inſeparably joyned to thee my head Chriſt; that thou maieſt ſupply all my weakneſſe and defects in ſoule or body, out of thy infinite fulneſſe of grace and mercy; that being cloathed with thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I may be accepted by thee, and through thee; and ſo be accounted worthy to be partaker of all thy merits, that with the outward ſigne of bread and wine, I may bleſſedly receive the true ſignified Chriſt, with all his benefits, and may have grace to hunger and thirſt after the ſpirituall food of Chriſts body and bloud, to nouriſh my ſoule unto eternall life, and to make me become a new creature in holineſſe of living, with all true and humble thankfulneſſe, to thy glory and my everlaſting ſalvation: beſeeching thee to accept my poor endeavours for perfect performance, and reach forth thy helping hand from heaven to ſave me, thy unworthy ſervant, pardoning my ſins, and covering my imperfections, with the pure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121289:19"/> of that immaculate Lambe, Jeſus my Saviour. And ſo I humbly commend my ſelfe unto thy mercy, who art able to doe abundantly, above all that I can aske or thinke; to thee be all honour, power, and praiſe for evermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>A ſhort meditation, direction, or prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before you preſume to enter into the preſence and ſight of God, to approach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heavenly banquet, humbly deſiring this, or the like by prayer. As thou draweſt near unto the holy table, pray earneſtly in thy heart unto Chriſt:</head>
               <p>THat he will draw near by grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and our ſelves.</note> thy ſoul, to ſtrengthen thee with knowledge, true faith, unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and perfect charity, that thou maieſt rightly, reverently, and faithfully receive this holy Sacrament to Gods <note place="margin">Pſ. 14. 22. 1 Jo 1. 8.</note> glory, and thine owne comfort, and ſalvation. Now when thou commeſt to communicate and receive this bleſſed <note place="margin">Col. 3. 2. Rom. 12. 1. 2. &amp; 1. 15.</note> Sacrament of the Lords Supper: Firſt, baniſh all vaine and earthly thoughts, and recollect thy heart to the ſerious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121289:20"/> of that which is the life of the <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 4 Humility. 1 Pet. 5. 6. 1 Jo. 2. 2. &amp; 4. 14.</note> Sacrament, even the death of thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and humbly and devoutly preſent thy ſelfe and ſervice to the Redeemer of thy ſoule, and Lord of the feaſt, the only ſaviour of mankinde, Jeſus Chriſt our righteous Lord. Then apply thy minde to theſe contemplations: Firſt, remember with great reverence the infinite Majeſty of God, his mercy, <note place="margin">True re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. 1 Jo. 9. Prov. 28. 13.</note> goodneſſe, and juſtice, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence we are. Secondly, conſider thine owne vileneſſe, miſery, and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being wholly corrupt both in ſoul and body. Thirdly, confeſſe all thy ſins <note place="margin">True faith 1 Pet. 1. 18. 19 21. 2. 14. 1. 3. 21.</note> plainly, for in hiding our ſins this work will not proſper; but with moſt hearty and unfeigned ſorrow, in all humility caſt thy ſelf at Jeſus feet, earneſtly beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for pardon, with hatred to all ſin, and purpoſe of amendment: For who <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 22 Heb. 12. 24. 1 Jo. 2. 3.</note> ſo confeſſeth and forſaketh their ſins ſhall finde mercy. Fourthly, trie and acknowledge thy faith, and ſtedfaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in Chriſt Jeſus (the bleſſed Son of God the Creator) to be the only Saviour <note place="margin">1 Tim. 21 5. Jam. 1. 17.</note> and Redeemer of the world, who dyed for thy ſins, and roſe againe for thy ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, and is aſcended up to heaven for thy ſalvation, where ſitting at Gods
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121289:20"/> right hand, he maketh interceſſion for <note place="margin">1 Tim. 21 5.</note> thee, and powreth downe all graces and bleſſings upon thee, who giveth himſelf with all his merits, unto thee in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, covering all thy offences with <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 17.</note> his perfect obedience: So making thee righteous, and leaving thee a pledge and <note place="margin">Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. 1 Jo. 17. 19. Heb. 13. 12.</note> ſeale of thy future and eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, this his holy inſtitution, which the divine word hath ſanctified to that end and purpoſe. Now call to minde the exceeding love of God and Chriſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, the one in ſending his only deare Sonne, to become man and ſuffer death: The fifth, in giving his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious body and bloud, to bee crucified <note place="margin">Gods love to us.</note> and ſhed upon the croſſe, to ſatisfie the juſt wrath of God due for thy ſins; of which this bread broken, &amp; wine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out (that we ſee) is a remembrance which we ought often to celebrate, and ſet our hearts and ſoules duly and truly, <note place="margin">Our love to God.</note> to love and honour this gracious God and Lord, who hath loved us firſt, and done ſuch great things as to give himſelf for us. 6. Ponder well in thine heart <note place="margin">1 Ja. 4. 9. 10.</note> all the divine myſteries of this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; to which heavenly banquet, Jeſus thy Saviour now inviteth thee, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away thine hatefull iniquities, and <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 8.</note>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121289:21"/> cloathing thee with his innocencie; ſo <note place="margin">Jo. 15. 12. Charity to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. 1 Jo. 4. 21.</note> to make thee acceptable in the ſight of God the Father, and by the gracious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the Holy Ghoſt, joyning thee unto himſelfe, as thy head, and all of us in true love one to another, as members of one body, to walke in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life the reſt of our dayes. 7. And <note place="margin">Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 1 Jo. 33. 10. 1 Pet. 4. 2.</note> laſtly, forget not to be ever truly thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for theſe ineſtimable benefits of God the Father, of the bleſſed Trinity; and of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord towards us, who hath laid downe his own life to redeem us, ſuch vile and miſerable ſinners, all which the Holy Ghoſt applieth unto us. <note place="margin">Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. 1 Jo. 5. 7. Eph. 5. 20. 1 Theſſ. 5. 18.</note> Infinite mercies, we are never able ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to acknowledge and admire. Prepare not thy belly, but thy ſoule; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and thou haſt eaten; this ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="prayer">
               <head>14. <hi>A thanksgiving after the holy communion of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH! bleſſed and praiſed for ever, be the Name of the Lord my God, who hath done great and many things for me; and holy is thy gracious and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121289:21"/> name, and let thy mercy and thy truth (O Lord) never forſake me, but vouchſafe to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue thy goodneſſe and loving kindneſſe towards me for ever, and ſay unto my ſoule thou art my God, my helpe and my ſalvation for evermore. And now eſpecially (O Lord) as I am infinitely bound, I render unto thy divine Majeſty all humble and poſſible praiſe and thanks for this preſent and particular favour ſhewed unto me thy unworthy ſervant, in feeding my ſoule to eternall lfe, with the moſt pretious food of thine owne ſacred body and bloud, blotting out all my ſinnes, and ſanctifying mee by thy holy Spirit, imputing to me thy righteouſneſſe, and admitting mee (ſo unworthy) to be a happy partaker of this bleſſed Sacrament: The benefit whereof is unſpeakable, and the mercy therein unexpreſſable; only I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire thy goodneſſe towards mankind, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy great mercy, beſeeching thee (my God) as thou haſt vouchſafed to accept mee at this holy Table; ſo (good Lord) let mee not depart without a bleſſing, but be pleaſed to receive me into thy gracious care and favour, that I may live and die therein; and give mee grace to ſpend the reſt of my time in a carefull reformation of all evills paſt, a diligent performance of thy moſt holy will in all things, and true obedience to all thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, with a faithfull and right application of all thy mercies and merits; ſo that I may feele thy bitter paſſion (O Lord) ſweet unto my ſoule, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121289:22"/> by the aſſiſtance of thy Spirit, bring forth the fruits of amendment of life, and moſt hearty thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all my daies; that at the end of this life, I may obtaine a bleſſed roome in the Kingdome of glory, there to praiſe thy holy name for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="prayer">
               <head>15. <hi>A ſhort Prayer for concluſion to any prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God the Father, bleſſe and governe my ſoule and body, in all things to thy ſervice: O Lord the Sonne my Saviour Jeſus, protect me, and direct me at all times to doe thy will: O holy Ghoſt, bleſſed Spirit, preſerve mee from falling into any ſinne or evill: but inſtruct, ſanctifie and lead me into the waies of truth and righteouſneſſe, that I may live in thy feare, and dye in thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and may continue in thy right Church and true faith unto my end: So that in the houre of my death, and in the dreadfull day of judgement, I may finde grace in thy ſight that thou maieſt pardon and paſſe by my ſins, and receive me to mercy through Jeſus Chriſt, that I may live with thee my God for evermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="prayer">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121289:22"/>
               <head>16. <hi>A Prayer for the Lords day in the afternoone when you are from Church; being ſeven humble petitions from a poor ſinner to our Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Lord and fountain of mercy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and allowed by ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt great and gracious Lord, and <note place="margin">1. Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life. Luke 18. 13. Rom. 6. 6.</note> my only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, whom the Angels doe admire, all the Saints doe magnifie, and at thy name (O Jeſus) doth every knee bow in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth: I moſt humbly beſeech thee, to have mercy on me that preſume to ſpeake unto thee, who am but duſt and aſhes; yet Lord I beg of thee to forgive all my grievous and manifold offences, and caſt all my ſins out of thy ſight, and not only to pardon all my paſt miſdeeds, but alſo by thy mighty power and ſpirit, to ſlay all ſin in me for the time to come. And of thy gracious favour vouchſafe while I live in this world to make mee a bleſſed partaker in the firſt reſurrection <note place="margin">2. To riſe from ſin, Rev. 20. in this life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> to ariſe here, from remaining or lying dead in ſin, and ſo the ſecond death ſhall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121289:23"/> have no power to hurt me, but by thy <note place="margin">3. In death Rev. 14. 13 21. 3. 4. Luke 22. 32. 36.</note> grace and aſſiſtance, I may become a new creature in all holineſſe of life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, that I may daily bee raiſed from ſin by thy holy Spirit to a new life of grace in Chriſt. But when the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time of my death doth approach, ſweet Jeſus leave me not, but keep and deliver mee from that great houre of temptation, when Sathan will ſift mee, and ſeeke my deſtruction, then deare Lord, pray for me that my faith may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faile, neither let my ſoules enemies prevaile over mee, but make thy poore ſervant one of thoſe bleſſed that ſhall die in thee, O Lord, whoſe tears God will wipe from their eyes, and they ſhall reſt from their labours, and their workes follow them. Now, good Ieſus, grant alſo in the laſt day and houre of death, <note place="margin">4 The firſt judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Mat. 25. 34. 41.</note> when I ſhall come to my firſt account before the Throne of God, and the dreadfull Majeſty of the Father; O my Saviour, appeare with mee, that by thy gracious mediation I may finde favour in his ſight, and through thee obtaine to bee received into the ſociety of thy Saints and ſervants; and alſo by thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy and bitter paſſion, that I may in and through thee have my ſins
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121289:23"/> covered and pardoned, and may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy to eſcape thy juſt and great wrath, which my iniquities have deſerved, and ſay alwaies unto my ſoule thou art my God, and my ſalvation for ever. And ſo I miſerable ſinner, through thy merits, ſufferings, and unſpeakable mercy, may be made able to ſtand before thee the bleſſed Son of God and man, at my appearance in thy glorious and aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence when thou commeſt to judge the world, and haſt full power to ſave or to condemne us, then looke Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour on me as one of thine. And ſweet <note place="margin">5. At the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 6. Is after death. Rev. 8. 20. 15.</note> Saviour, I further beſeech thee by thine owne former and free election and meer grace towards me, vouchſafe in the dreadfull time of thy great viſitation, that my poore name may be found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heaven in the booke of life, ſo as ſin nor Sathan may not bee able to blot mee out; but that thou, gracious Ieſus, wilt be pleaſed to acknowledge me (thy moſt unworthy ſervant) to be thine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and all his holy Angells. Now laſtly, Lord by thy great goodneſſe and <note place="margin">The 7th. For eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, John 17. 22. 24. Pſ. 16. 11. Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> mercy, that I may be received into thy grace and favour, and ſo accepted as to injoy that moſt happy place and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inheritance of everlaſting glory,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121289:24"/> which thou our Ieſus haſt dearly purchaſed for us: that where he my bleſſed Saviour is, I may live with him, who loved me ſo much as to die for me, and through him being admitted into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence of God, which is the fulneſſe of joy, at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore: I ſhall there eternally ſerve, praiſe and magnifie his moſt holy name, who liveth for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="prayer">
               <head>17. <hi>A Prayer to the Trinity for direction and acceptance from God, of all our prayers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt glorious God, and our heavenly Father in Chriſt, I moſt humbly pray thee for his ſake to heare and accept mee, and my ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that I offer up unto thy Majeſty in the name of thy beloved Son: And I beſeech thee ſweet Ieſus, in thy love and mercie, which made thee become our Redeemer; vouchſafe alſo to be my gracious advocate, and to direct and receive my petitions, and preſent them to the Father, for by and through thee only, I muſt obtaine acceptance. Now further I beg of thee, Lord Holy Ghoſt, who beſt can teach us to pray as we ought, to take compaſſion on my frailties and infirmities, to heale and helpe them, and be pleaſed to ſanctifie and aſſiſt my heart and ſoule to performe this duty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121289:24"/> and ſervice at all times, rightly, faithfully, and conſtantly; to Gods glory, and mine owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and furtherance of my eternall ſalvation in Chriſt my Saviour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="prayer">
               <head>18. <hi>Another Prayer for the afternoon for many ſeverall bleſſings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH moſt dear Lord, who knoweſt my mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold infirmities, and innumerable miſeries: In mercy let thy gracious care and holy hand bee over me now and ever, to guide me into thy right paths, that I may walke in the wayes of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and keepe them with my whole heart unto my end. And vouchſafe, good God, to clenſe and change the thoughts of my corrup heart from vaine and idle imaginations, to good and godly meditations, which may produce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me by thy aſſiſtance, holy actions agreeable to thy moſt bleſſed will; and by thy ſpirit let my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections be reformed, and my love withdrawne from the vanities of this vile world, and may bee fixed on heavenly things above, that there may be my heart and only joy, where my Lord Chriſt ſits in glory at the right hand of his Father; and ſo I may with bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> chuſe the better part, to forſake all the world, and my ſelfe alſo, to follow and heare Ieſus; and firſt and chiefly ſo to ſeek as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121289:25"/> to obtaine that which is moſt needfull, even thy glory, O God, thy Kingdome, and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, and leave all other things to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on me as ſhall ſeem beſt unto thee. And Lord grant that my underſtanding may be inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to diſcerne, imbrace, and practice the holy workes of thy bleſſed Spirit, and that my memory may be ſtrengthned to retaine and make right uſe of all the good inſtruction that I heare or read ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy will, and make my heart the ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of all thy divine precepts, that by thy grace I may bring forth good fruit in my life; and make mee able rightly and reverently, to read and heare thy holy word, and heavenly will daily as I ought to doe, and by thy grace to frame my life thereafter; and direct thou me thy poor ſervant in all I goe about to doe that which is beſt, and moſt to thy glory, that howſoever all the powers and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>culties of my ſoule, or the members or ſenſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y body may be decayed or loſt by age, griefe, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckneſſe, for the occaſions of this life, yet ſo Lord all that is needfull for thy conſtant ſervice, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, continue to my laſt breath. And alſo be pleaſed to grant, that my death be neither ſudden, nor unexpected, nor my pains violent, whereby to be made unable earneſtly and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pray and call upon thy holy name; but if it be thy will, give mee knowledge of my death when thy time is come to call mee out of this world, and aſſiſt me fervently to crie unto thee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121289:25"/> for grace and mercie, in the needfull time of dread and danger; then (deare Lord) fit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare me for thy ſelfe, and give me a bleſſed depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence to dye in thee, my Lord, and ſo I ſhall remaine ſafe and ever happy; and ſweet Ieſus, make me pray unto thee with my laſt breath, and yeeld up my ſpirit to God that gave it with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in my mouth unto my gracious God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. Now vouchſafe, good Lord, while I live, to indue me thy moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervant with thy grace and holy Spirit, whereby devout love, and feare of thy Majeſty, with true faith, ſtedfaſt hope, perfect charity, and unfained repentance, with all other ſaving gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may be daily renued and increaſed in mee, towards thee, to thy glory, and the furtherance of my ſalvation through Chriſt: O ſweet Saviour, who haſt performed and ſuffered great and many things for mee; deare Jeſus, continue thy infinite favour, and finiſh thy worke of mercy towards me the leaſt of thy ſervants, ſtill to call and draw me daily unto thee, and make me faithfull, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and wholly thine, in all humble obedience and true humility to ſerve thee in uprightneſſe of life, and a holy converſation towards all ſo long as I live, and wilt aſſure my ſoule, that thou art my mercifull God, and after death, make me a happy partaker of thy everlaſting Kingdome of glory. So be it. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="prayer">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121289:26"/>
               <head>19. <hi>A Prayer of three petitions, to the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, for the ſpirit of prayer, for repentance and remiſſion of ſins, and grace to amend and lead a new life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O My Lord Holy Ghoſt, our ſanctifier and comforter, and preſerver, the giver of all heavenly gifts and graces, and the directer and aſſiſter of us to all goodneſſe: I moſt humbly pray thee to indue me thy poore ſinfull ſervant, with thy true ſpirit of grace and prayer, to helpe and teach me how to pray as I ought, and to drive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and baniſh from me in the performance of this my duty, all evill temptations, and wicked hindrances that ſeek to pervert and withdraw my heart and ſoule from the true ſervice of my God; and ſuffer not the world, the divell, nor any his agents to have power over me, or part in mee, to prevaile againſt me, and to cauſe God to turn his eare and face of mercy, from hearing and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my prayers and ſupplications: but Lord, by thy grace make my petitions now and alwaies right, faithfull, and acceptable to Almighty God, through Ieſus Chriſt my bleſſed Saviour.</p>
               <p>But O my God heavenly Father, the originall of all goodneſſe, and mercy, who graciouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt us to call upon thee in the time of trouble, that thou delivering us, we may glorifie thee;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121289:26"/> what greater miſery and danger, then a heavy load of ſins that will not eaſily be caſt off, and a wounded ſpirit who can beare it? for I confeſſe I have moſt grievouſly ſinned againſt thee, and my iniquities are multiplied before thee, as the ſtarres which cannot be numbred. O Lord, whoſe compaſſion never faileth thoſe that ſeek and truſt in thee, as thy mercy exceedeth all thy great workes, ſo let that through thy deare Son move thee to releaſe mee of this intolerable burthen; which elſe will throw mee out of thy preſence and favour, wherein is the fulneſſe of joy; and preſſe me down to hell into everlaſting torments amongſt the enemies of God and man. Now mercifull God, who haſt pity on thy poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and delighteſt not in the death of a ſinner; Lord turne me from all my evill waies, that I may be converted unto thee, to feare, love, and obey thee unto my end: And vouchſafe to pardon all my tranſgreſſions paſt, and remove my ſins from me as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, and bury them in oblivion, that they may not be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate my God from mee, as far as heaven from hell: but Gracious Lord, be pleaſed to give me, thy unworthy ſervant, the bleſſed gift of true ſorrow and repentance to ſalvation, to fit me for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and prepare me with grace by the amendment of all my miſdeeds, for thy loving acceptance of me in thy favour againe, and ſay to my loſt ſoule, I am thy God, and thy ſalvation for ever; and ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121289:27"/> thou working in me, both the will and the deed, the praiſe, honour and glory be only thine, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore.</p>
               <p>Now ſwet Jeſus, the fountaine of mercy, and Saviour of all that truſt and believe in thee, who graciouſly calleſt all heavy laden and penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to come to thee, that thou maieſt eaſe them; have mercy on me, and heale my ſinfull ſoul with thy moſt pretious bloud; and thy righteouſneſſe I know is alſufficient to cover a world of ſinnes, if thou pleaſe to impute it unto mee. O ſhrowd mee under thy innocent wing, that the great wrath I have deſerved may never fall upon mee: but vouchſafe, dear Lord, to receive mee ſinfull creature into thy favour, as thou didſt <hi>Mary,</hi> to become wholly thine, and be thy faithfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple ſo long as I live; and ſtretch forth thy hand of mercy, as thou didſt to <hi>Peter</hi> from ſinking in the ſea; ſo Lord ſave me thy unworthy ſervant, from periſhing in my ſins; and by thy aſſiſtance, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy bleſſed advice, that I may make my peace here, where I have tranſgreſſed, before I goe where the utmoſt farthing muſt bee paid. O Lord, by thy grace make me a new creature, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worke out my ſalvation, with ſorrow for my time loſt, feare to offend again, and trembling at the heavy judgements due unto me, and ſtriving to make my calling and election ſure, by a holy life and godly converſation both towards God and man all the reſt of my dayes. And make mee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121289:27"/> caſt utterly off all love of this deceitfull world, which is but loſt, and my owne vaine deſires that hang ſo faſt on, and only apply my heart and ſoule to ſeek after thee and thy Kingdome, with the righteouſneſſe thereof, and then I ſhall obtain the end of my faith and hope; even thy glory, and my owne ſalvation, through thee only dear Jeſus, my bleſſed Lord and alone Saviour. To whom with God the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, one eternall God and glorious Trinity, be rendred as is due, all praiſe, honour and glory, for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="prayer">
               <head>20. <hi>The concluſion to this booke. A ſhort Prayer ſo to performe our duties here towards God, that we may obtaine heaven hereafter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH moſt mercifull Lord God, thou knoweſt my unaptneſſe to any good: I humbly pray thee to give me thy poor unworthy ſervant grace ſo truly to feare thee, as not to offend thee; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to beleeve in thee, and confidently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye upon all thy gracious promiſes, in all my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and neceſſities; and ſo entirely and ſincerely to love and honour thee above all things, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world may withdraw my minde from thee, nor any vaine hopes, or earthly deſires make mee neglect my ſervice to thee; but that I
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121289:28"/> may daily ſtudy and ſtrive, rightly and carefully to obey thee my Lord at all times, diligently to ſeek thee, and know thy will, and faithfully to ſerve and pleaſe thee as I ought to doe as long as I live. For thou, O God the Father, lovedſt us firſt, and ſent thy deare Son out of thy boſome to redeeme us, and our ſweet Saviour Jeſus in his love gave himſelfe, and laid downe his owne life to ſave us from eternall death; greater love cannot bee found then for one to dye for a friend, but thou Lord diedſt for thine enemies; much more having now reconciled us to the father, and to thy ſelfe: I truſt being united to thee alſo by the Holy Ghoſt, by ſanctification and true faith wrought in me by that bleſſed Spirit, I ſhall obtaine mercy through the merits and ſufferings of my deare Jeſus, to live with thee in heaven hereafter, to glorifie the great Name of God, the eternall Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, to whom bee all praiſe and honour for ever; and let heaven and earth, Saints and Angells, and all creatures, give glory to him for evermore, Amen.</p>
               <p>Here is one Prayer more which I joyne to theſe, becauſe it concerned one of my daughters, to whom this Booke belonged, though it was lately penned upon a very ſtrange accident.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="prayer">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:121289:28"/>
               <head>21. <hi>A thanksgiving to Almighty God, for his moſt mercifull preſervation of my noble kinſwoman the Lady</hi> Eliz. Feelding, <hi>and of my owne daughter, the Lady</hi> Eliz. Cornwalleis, <hi>from drowning under the Bridge, and was long under water: and one worthy Gentlewoman in the company could not bee recovered. This may ſerve upon any ſuch fearfull accident.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt Mighty God, Creator of heaven and earth, and the only diſpoſer of all things therein, thou art the defender and protecter of all thy children and ſervants, and the gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of all thoſe that depend upon thee: thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ruleth both by ſea and land, and thy all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiding providence directeth all things in the world, according to thy own high will and good pleaſure, and for the good of all them that truſt in thee. Whereof thou haſt given many, and mee the unworthieſt of thy ſervants, an eſpeciall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thy infinite mercy towards my deare daughter and kinſwoman, in that great and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous deliverance lately of them, in the dreadfull danger of ſudden death by drowning in the Thames; for thou didſt mercifully provide and take care to ſave their lives, when they were paſt ſenſe to take care of themſelves, or to call upon thee for helpe; yet beyond all hope, thou didſt bring them backe from the gates of death, praiſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121289:29"/> for ever be thy moſt glorious Name; and let nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther us, nor any of our generation forget this thy great mercy. Now Lord, make us duly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge all thy benefits, and let us not paſſe them out of our mindes without true thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for all thy favours continually vouchſafed unto us undeſerved: for all which we poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have nothing to returne to thee, but devout love, faithfull ſervice, and carefull obedience, with the humble ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; which by thy aſſiſtance, I will performe towards thee with a gratefull heart, ſo long as I live, and for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="prayer">
               <head>22. <hi>A Petition of the Author for herſelfe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, he would readily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the duty in his charge that lay upon him, leſt while he preached to ſave others, himſelf ſhould become a caſt-away: ſo deareſt Lord, I having taken pains to compoſe many Prayers for the uſe of others (under my care) to further them in the conſtant performance of this duty of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; which being rightly uſed, will draw many bleſſings from thee: Almighty God, I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee, to heare and receive their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, that call upon thee by theſe Prayers. So, Gracious Lord, ſuffer not me to neglect my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121289:29"/> duty and daily ſervice herein, towards thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, but make me carefully, rightly and reverently to offer up due praiſes and prayers, daily unto thee in a faithfull and acceptable manner all the daies of my life. And give me thy poor ſervant the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thy grace and holy Spirit, to reform all my waies before thee; to ſuppreſſe and overcome the corruption of my heart, the vanity of my mind, and to forſake and abandon the love of this vile world, with all the deceitfull vanities thereof, and to caſt off thoſe great &amp; ſuperfluous cares and deſires after the things of this mutable life, which paſſe away like a ſhadow or dream. Wiſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> that had the plenty, and triall of all things under the Sun, tells us what it will prove, only vanity of vanities, and vexation of ſpirit. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me learne with <hi>Paul,</hi> in what eſtate ſoever I am, therewith to be content, and to ſubmit with humble patience to thy pleaſure in all things thou ſendeſt, who knoweſt what is beſt and fitteſt for me; and keep me for repining and deſpairing in thy chaſtiſements; for thou canſt heale as well as wound, when thou pleaſeſt. Therefore I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate my heart and ſoule, and all my endeavours unto thy faithfull ſervice, ſtriving to make my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and election ſure, by looking after thee my God, thy Kingdome, and thy righteouſneſſe, which is the only thing needfull: This grace grant unto mee, O God, for Jeſus Chriſts ſake. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Book.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121289:30"/>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121289:30"/>
            <head>BOOK II.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Book I began to write at my houſe at <hi>Barking</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> where I retired my ſelfe in ſolitarineſſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of my worthy and dear huſband, Sir <hi>Thomas Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Juſtice of the Kings Bench: who dyed at Candlemas, 1634.</p>
               <p>Where ſhortly after I finiſhed theſe Prayers follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for my owne private uſe; being the fitteſt imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for my time, who was then in ſo much heavineſſe-</p>
               <p>I call this Book a weekly exerciſe of Prayer, either for a private perſon, or in their owne family: To which there are added ſome other neceſſary Prayers, very uſefull for thoſe particular occaſions, whereto they are directed: which I ſhall be very glad and joyfull, if my children, grand-children, kindred, friends, or any good Chriſtian that ſhall peruſe them, may make a good and right uſe of them to Gods glory: And I doe moſt heartily and humbly pray, that God will vouchſafe to heare in heaven, and to receive, accept, and grant their juſt requeſts, to his owne honour, their comfort, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121289:31"/> my great happineſſe, who am a wel-wiſher, and true lover of their ſoules in the Lord.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Eliz. Richardſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="authors_note">
               <p>THeſe Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> I compoſed for the inſtructions of my children, &amp; grand-children, after the example of my dear parents, Sir <hi>Thomas Beaumont,</hi> and his Lady, of <hi>Stoughton</hi> in the County of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> who I thinke were as carefull and induſtrious to breed up their children (which were living) in the inſtruction and information of the Lord, to ſerve and obey God, as any parents could poſſibly be, which made them take much paines with us, more then is uſuall, by their endeavours to bring us to know and feare God, and to keep his Commandements: Which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, is the whole duty of man. But when parents have done the beſt, and all we can, it is Gods grace and bleſſing that muſt perfect the worke: which I humbly pray him to adde to accompliſh my deſire, to their eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:121289:31"/>
               <head>An Exhortation concerning Prayer.</head>
               <p>BEfore thou goeſt to pray: conſider ſeriouſly of theſe three things, which are very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to fit and prepare thee the better for that holy and bleſſed exerciſe: Firſt, ponder with thy ſelfe, into whoſe preſence wee come, and to whom we preſume to ſpeak, being before the great Majeſty of God Almighty. Secondly, in what manner we pray, and to what end our prayers tend, which muſt chiefly reſpect the glory of God and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and then out owne deſires and neceſſities, both for ſoule and body. Thirdly, weigh well what good or hurt, what benefit or danger may enſue, by the performing of this duty carefully or negligently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>1. <hi>A ſhort Petition to precede any other Prayers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord Holy Ghoſt, who knoweſt my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt heart, and the frailty of my ſoule, which can performe no good but by thy grace. Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, my Lord, to ſanctifie, aſſiſt and teach me the unworthieſt of thy ſervants, by thy holy Spirit, ſo to pray now and alwayes, that my ſupplications may be faithfull and acceptable to my God, to his glory, and the comfort and good of my ſelfe, both in ſoul and body for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121289:32"/>
               <head>2. <hi>A Prayer to God the Holy Ghoſt, for the true ſpirit of grace in prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God Holy Ghoſt, the giver of all good gifts and graces, give mee thy true Spirit Lord, who art the comforter and ſanctifier of thine E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: thou knoweſt my great and manifold infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and frailties; all which, I humbly pray thee in thy love and mercie to heale and helpe. And Lord give me power, ſtrength, and grace, by thy aſſiſtance, to reſiſt and overcome all wicked aſſaults and temptations of the divell, that ſeeke to draw me from God and goodneſſe, and lead mee to all evill: but vouchſafe Lord, I beſeech thee, ſtill to be preſent with me in this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and indue thy poore ſervant with thy bleſſed Spirit and gift of prayer to call upon thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name faithfully and ſincerely, whereby my unworthy petitions (though full of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) may be received and accepted by thee. And Lord, baniſh all wandring thoughts, and wicked hindrances from my ſoule, in the performance of this my bounden duty and ſervice, that I owe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, my God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt: And be pleaſed Lord, to aſſiſt mee now and ever with thy grace to worſhip thee at all times, in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and truth, as thou requireſt: and not to preſent a dead, dull and corrupt offering unto my Lord, of the lips without the heart, or by joyning in my
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121289:32"/> thoughts God and the world, or mammon toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which thou hateſt, and ſo make my prayers abominable to thy Majeſty; for thou haſt made the heart, who ought and muſt be ſerved and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with it. Therefore I humbly pray thee, to inable me by thy aſſiſtance, to offer unto thee, my God, a holy and living ſacrifice, of my ſelfe, my prayers, and praiſes daily, in a right and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable manner, not looking ſo much to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and recompence of reward that ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thereby from thy mercifull hands to my owne good, but chiefly for the honour and glory of thy great Name, whoſe I am, and whom I am bound to ſerve, and from whom I have already received ſo many great bleſſings and benefits both ſpirituall and temporall: for which I render moſt humble and hearty thanks unto thy Majeſty. Now laſtly, deare Lord Holy Ghoſt, I earneſtly beg of thee, daily to unite mee unto thy glorious head, and only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo I may performe with true faith, good devotion, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſincerity, this, and all other holy duties and ſervices, according to thy bleſſed will and word, to thy glory and my great comfort; now and for ever: So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121289:33"/>
               <head>3. <hi>A ſhort preface before any other Prayers, for the Lords day.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALmighty Lord God, in whoſe glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence I am, preſuming to take thy ſacred name into my ſinfull mouth: before thee, Lord, I moſt humbly proſtrate my ſelfe; thou ſeeſt the heart, and knoweſt our wants before we aske, yet haſt thou commanded us to ask in thy Sons name, promiſing for his ſake, to grant us all needfull bleſſings both for ſoule and body. O Lord, thou underſtandeſt my great weakneſſe and diſability, who can doe no good, but by thy aſſiſtance: I now moſt humbly pray thee, to keep all evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions from my heart and ſoule, and ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due mee with thy true Spirit of grace and prayer, in performing this duty and ſervice to thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty; that ſo all my ſupplications may now and at all times be right, faithfull, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and pleaſing unto thee: and by thy great mercy alſo, prevailing for my good, and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my ſalvation, through my only Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>4. <hi>A Prayer for the Lords day at firſt awaking.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Moſt glorious Lord God, the high and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Creator of heaven and earth, with all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121289:33"/> things therein; Thou didſt finiſh that mighty work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſix dayes, and reſted the ſeventh, commanding thy Church and people of the Jewes to keep holy the ſeventh day, to thy due ſervice and praiſe. But our Lord Jeſus having finiſhed the redemption of mankinde by his croſſe and paſſion, and bitter ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, didſt bury that Sabbath in his grave upon that day, and by thy Spirit didſt guide thy Apoſtles and Chriſtian Church to ſanctifie and keep holy this firſt day of the weeke, in perpetuall memory of his glorious reſurrection and eternall reſt from that labour, and ſuffering for our redemption, to thy due ſervice and praiſe; bleſſed be thy holy name therefore. And now, dear Lord, for all my former neglects of my duty herein; for Jeſus his ſake, pardon my ſinfull breaches of this, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy holy Commandements heretofore: and vouchſafe, O God, alwaies to knit my ſtraying heart, to the true feare of thy great name, to keep me from offending thee, and fill my ſoul with the infinite love of thy divine Majeſty, that I may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrive to lead the reſt of my life in all obedience to thy holy will. And Lord, vouchſafe to inſpire me thy moſt unworthy ſervant, I humbly pray thee, with thy bleſſed Spirit, that I may withdraw my minde this bleſſed day, from all worldly cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, thinking my owne thoughts, ſpeaking my owne words, doing my daily works, or going my owne waies; but aſſiſt me with thy grace, that I may apply my heart and ſoule wholly to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121289:34"/> of thy wonderfull works, and manifold mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, with thankfulneſſe, and to attend thy ſervice either publique or private, with care and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to obey all thy Commandements hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth with diligence, and conſtantly ſerving thee all my life to come, that ſo I may praiſe and glorifie thee, and thou maieſt pardon my ſins, and ſave my poore ſoule, through thy great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merited mercie in Jeſus Chriſt, my Lord and only Redeemer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <head>5. <hi>A Prayer for the Lords day in the morning before going to Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and all that is within me praiſe his holy name, who is moſt worthy of all honour and glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALmighty God, our heavenly Father in Jeſus Chriſt thy beloved Son, who of thy infinite goodneſſe by thy great power and divine word, didſt in ſix dayes create heaven and earth, the ſea and the whole world, with all things therein, and reſting the ſeventh day, didſt bleſſe and hallow it, commanding all thy people in purity after thine owne image, to keep the ſame holy to thy due honour and praiſe; having alſo given us ſix dayes for our owne occaſions: and after this great and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121289:34"/> unexpreſſible worke, thou didſt alſo in thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time accompliſh by thy beloved Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that happy redemption of mankinde, who were loſt by ſin, and fallen from thee; which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable mercie and benefit was as upon this firſt day of the week conſummated by the miraculous bleſſed reſurrection of our Saviour, which wee Chriſtians now keep in commemoration of theſe thy infinite benefits; that according to thine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment thy ſervants may reſt this holy Lords day, from all worldly affaires to thy honour and glory: bleſſed and praiſed now and for ever, bee thy glorious Name, for theſe thy marvellous workes. Therefore I moſt humbly beſeech thee, O Lord, of thy great mercie, by thy Spirit of grace, to ſanctifie mee thy moſt unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, both in ſoule and body, that I may at all times, but eſpecially this Lords day, and upon all other daies conſecrated by thy Church to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of any of thy bleſſings, benefits and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, wholly devote my ſelfe, to thy true feare, holy devotion; and faithfull ſervice, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thy bleſſed will and commandement: And ſo thy worthy name may be glorified, my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation furthered, and thy favour and bleſſing reſt alwaies upon me and mine. And likewiſe I moſt humbly pray thee, O God, for thy Son Jeſus ſake, to forgive all my ſins done in my whole life paſt, in breaking this and all other thy divine Laws, that through the death and bitter paſſion of my deare
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121289:35"/> and innocent Saviour, which hee ſuffered to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us, thou wilt vouchſafe to be reconciled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, thy guilty and ſinfull creature; that as this is a day of reſt to thy due praiſe, ſo by thy marcy it may bee a happy day of joy and peace to my poore ſoule and conſcience, through my only Lord and bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>6. <hi>A Prayer to be ſaid at the Church, as ſoone as we are come into our ſeat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord our God, who art here preſent amongſt us, thou ſeeſt and underſtandeſt all things, and knoweſt my heart; prepare, ſanctifie, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt my heart and ſoule, with thy grace, ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have my ſelfe, both outwardly and inwardly, as in the preſence of thy glorious Majeſty, in this thy bleſſed houſe of prayer and hearing thy word, with ſuch due reverence, feare, humility, true faith and devotion, as may be beſt pleaſing and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto thee, and moſt profitable and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable for the good of mine owne ſoule. O God, indue thy ſervant the Preacher, with thy holy Spirit, to teach thy ſaving truth rightly and ſincerely, that it may be powerfull to our edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and effectuall to the beating downe, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of all ſins from our ſoules, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121289:35"/> of faith and grace in us that heare him; to thy glory, and the furthering of our ſalvations, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>7. <hi>Another ſhorter Prayer to the ſame purpoſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOod Lord, that knoweſt my infirmities, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and remove all ſin and evill hindrances and impediments of drouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe, and wandring thoughts from me fraile ſinfull creature, and open my ears and heart like <hi>Lidiees</hi> to attend and marke diligently what is taught out of thy moſt ſacred word. Inlighten, Lord, my underſtanding, to conceive rightly what I heare, and keep my mind wholly intentive upon thy faithfull ſervice; in hearing thy holy word with true devotion before thee; and make my memory retentive of all the good inſtructions that I learne, and give me grace carefully and conſcionably to practice them throughout my whole life, to the honour of thy great name, the performance of thy moſt holy will, the amendment of all my faults; and finally, the ſalvation of mee thy poore ſervant; through my Saviour Jeſus Chriſts merits and mercies, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:121289:36"/>
               <head>8. <hi>A Prayer after the Sermon is ended, before we go out of the Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt Gracious Lord God, I humbly beſeech thee, to pardon all my ſinfull neglects, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and want of due preparation, or any infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that have overtaken mee in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of my duty towards thee, in this thy houſe, and bleſſed exerciſe of Prayer, and hearing of thy divine Word. And let me not depart out of this holy place without thy bleſſing, whereby my knowledge, faith, holineſſe, and comfort in thee may be daily increaſed in me: And Lord, adde thy grace to what I have now heard, that by thy gracious aſſiſtance, it may bring forth plentifull fruit in me, to the reformation of my life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, in avoiding all evill, and doing all good, which may be ſerviceable and acceptable to thy Majeſty, and beſt pleaſing in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, my only Saviour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Lords day at night, of three Petitions.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, thankfulneſſe for benefits already received, with prayer for the continuance of all Gods mercies. Secondly, for repentance, true faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, and amendment of life. Laſtly, ſo to live and dye unto God here, that after death, we may live with him in heaven for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121289:36"/>
               <head>9. <hi>The Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and forget not all his benefits, which forgiveth all thine iniquities, and healeth all thine infirmities, which redeemeth thy life from death, and crowneth thee in mercy and compaſſion, who provided a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for thee, before thou hadſt being to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thine owne wretched eſtate. Oh, my Lord God! how good and gracious haſt thou ever been in all thy mercies both ſpirituall and temporall towards me, the leaſt and unworthieſt of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, before I was borne, and ever ſince, from time to time? Now Lord, I humbly pray thee, in the ſame love and favour, from which I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto received ſo many and great benefits, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe thou alwaies to continue thy bleſſings unto me, eſpecially in daily renewing all ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in my ſoule, for the true performance of all holy duties and ſervice, in a right and acceptable manner towards thy Majeſty: and Lord, make my humble thankfulneſſe unto thee, appeare in my true obedience of thee in all things, that I may duly praiſe and glorifie thy name for ever. Now deare God, let not thy mercy in prolonging my daies, encreaſe the number of my ſinnes, and ſo to heap up wrath unto my ſelfe againſt the day of wrath, by drawing upon me due puniſhments for my offences; but mercifull God, adde thou grace
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121289:37"/> unto my daies; and for Jeſus ſake, forgive all my ſinnes paſt that I have done before thee in my whole life time, eſpecially in my many breaches of this holy and bleſſed Lords day, which we keep in remembrance of our Saviours reſurrection; with all my neglects and defects in the performance of my duties towards thee this preſent day, and heretofore, according to thy Commandements. And grant, O God, through thy mercies, and my Saviours merits, that my iniquities may never bee imputed unto mee; but Lord, let thy goodneſſe, patience, and long ſufferings, lead me to daily and unfaigned repentance: and give me true faith in all thy gracious promiſes, and by the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, to bring forth amendment of all my former faults, with true obedience unto thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will, and holineſſe of living all my life to come: That ſo I may obtaine grace and favour in thy ſight, to prevent and keep mee hereafter from all ſin and evil, or offending thee, my God, in thought, word and deed; and direct thou my waies right before thee, in all godlineſſe and uprightneſſe of heart, that I may be enabled through my Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to doe every good worke, and by thy grace to live here according to all thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements; and when thou pleaſeſt to call for mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of this wicked world unto thy ſelfe, Lord aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt me with thy ſpirit and grace to make a bleſſed end, and to die in thee, my Lord, and ſo I ſhall finde mercie through the merits of my Saviour
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121289:37"/> Jeſus, after death to be accepted and received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdome of heaven, and through Chriſt my Saviour, may bee admitted into thy glorious preſence, O God, where is the fulneſſe of joy, and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore, of which Lord make me a happy partaker, when this life is ended. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="prayer">
               <head>10. <hi>A Prayer for Munday to God the Father, at firſt awaking.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will praiſe thee with my whole heart, for thou haſt dealt lovingly with mee. Bleſſed and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed now and ever, be thy moſt glorious Name, O my God, heavenly Father, for all thy great and manifold mercies and bleſſings, both ſpirituall and temporall in ſoule and body, vouchſafed unto mee thy moſt unworthy and ſinfull ſervant, before I was borne, and hitherto, this laſt night, and all my life paſt; for thy favours have ever been right, good and gracious towards mee, having done great and many things for mee, prayſed be thy moſt holy Name, who haſt been my only ſtay, ſuccour, helpe and comfort in this world; and thy infinite mercy in Ghriſt, is all my hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for the life to come. Now Gracious Lord, who haſt been my good God and guide from my youth, have pity upon my infirmities: and for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121289:38"/> Jeſus ſake, forgive all my ſinnes that I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted before thee in my whole life paſt, and let thy mercy and truth, never leave me nor forſake me, neither in life, in death, nor in the laſt judgement, but be pleaſed by thy Spirit, to ſay alwaies unto my ſoule, eſpecially at my death, thou art my God and my ſalvation, for in thee will I truſt ſo long as I live, and for ever. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>A ſhort ſupplication before the weekly Prayers.</hi> 11. <hi>A morning Prayer for Munday to God the Father.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEare me when I call upon thee, O God of my righteouſneſſe, have mercy upon mee, and hearken unto my prayer. Moſt Gracious Lord God, and my heavenly Father, in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus my Saviour; thou knoweſt my great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous infirmities, that I can of my ſelfe neither will nor performe any good, nor think a good thought, but by thy grace; therefore I moſt humbly pray thee to indue mee thy poore unworthy ſervant with thy holy Spirit, whereby theſe and all other my prayers and petitions, that I preſume to offer unto thy Majeſty, may by thy aſſiſtance be made in a right manner, and in an acceptable time, when thou wilt pleaſe to be found of me, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly to heare and receive me and my ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121289:38"/> And now vouchſafe, dear God, to ſanctifie, prepare and aſſiſt my heart and ſoule, with thy true Spirit of grace and prayer, to drive away all vaine and wandring thoughts, ſluggiſh dulneſſe, and all evill temptations out of my minde; and knit my heart and ſoule to the true feare of thy great Name, and to the devout love of thy divine Majeſty; and teach mee with all due reverence, and ſuch true humility and devotion, as is fit to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in thy ſacred preſence, that I may rightly, faithfully, and humbly, now and at all times, call upon thy holy Name as I ought to doe, and daily pray unto thee, O my bleſſed Lord God, who haſt awaked mee in health and ſafety to this daies light, which I moſt thankfully acknowledge, with all other thy bleſſings and benefits, both ſpirituall and temporall, beſtowed on me thy ſinfull ſervant, from time to time; beſeeching thee of thy infinite mercy alwaies to continue them unto me. And as thy gracious providence hath brought me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin this new day, ſo Lord, by thy power defend me therein from falling into any ſin or evill, to offend thee; but give me grace at this preſent to performe, and ever continue to lead a new, a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and an upright life in thy ſight, all the reſt of my daies to come, to frame my heart, and reforme my waies in all true obedience hereafter to thy moſt holy will and Commandements. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I humbly praiſe thy glorious Name, for thy gracious preſervation of me and mine, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121289:39"/> thy benefits vouchſafed me the laſt night, and all my life paſt unto this inſtant houre, having hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto given me health, maintenance and ſafety; which, I pray thee, whilſt I live, ſtill to vouchſafe me, and make me truly thankfull to thee for all thy mercies; and let thy benefits never ſlip out of my minde, but that I may daily and duly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them to the true praiſe of thy moſt holy Name. And grant me grace to ſpend the reſt of my time to come more carefully and faithfully then I have formerly done, to ſeeke, ſerve, feare, love, obey, and pleaſe thee my Lord, in all things as I ought to doe, ſo that it may bee more then meat and drinke unto me, to doe the will of thee my heavenly Father. And I moſt humbly beſeech thee, O God, the fountaine of mercy, to forgive and pardon all my ſinnes and offences paſt that I have committed againſt thee, either in ſoule or body throughout my whole life; Lord blot them out of thy remembrance, with the moſt pretious bloud of thy deare Son, my only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; and grant through thy mercies, and his merits, and ſufferings, that my iniquities may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be imputed unto me. But vouchſafe, O God, now and ever, to keepe me thy poore ſervant, as the apple of thine own eie from all ſin and ſhame, and hide mee under the ſhadow of thy wings from falling into any evill or danger this day; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, O Lord, preſerve mee alwaies from the great wickedneſſe of committing any preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121289:39"/> ſin before thee, and from the fearfull ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt (which is unpardonable) and from the dangerous ſins of neglect towards thee, hardneſſe of heart, ſenſeleſſe ſecurity, or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into wicked deſpaire, whereby I may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my ſoule of thy mercy in Chriſt for my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But, good God, direct thou my thoughts, deſires, words, and deeds, to be ever agreeable to thy moſt holy will, and obedient to all thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, that I may henceforth live before thee with an upright heart, daily ſtudying and ſtriving to ſerve and pleaſe thee in all things, ſo long as I live, that after death, I may praiſe and magnifie thy Name in heaven among thy Saints and ſervants, for ever and ever. Theſe great mercies, O gracious God, with all other thou knoweſt needfull for me, either for this life or the life to come, I further beg of thee, in the name, merits and mediation of thy deare Son, and my ſweet Jeſus, concluding in that perfect forme of prayer, which hee hath taught us, ſaying, Our Father, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="prayer">
               <head>12. <hi>A Prayer to God the Father for Munday night.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord my God, how excellent is thy name in all the world, who haſt done great workes, and brought mighty things to paſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALmighty Lord, and my heavenly Father in Chriſt, moſt high and mighty God, Creator,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121289:40"/> poſſeſſor, preſerver, and diſpoſer of heaven and earth, and all that is therein, the fountaine of grace and mercy, and Father of light, from whom commeth all good and perfect gifts: I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray thee of thy great goodneſſe to give mee thy poore ſinfull ſervant, thy grace and holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to direct my heart and all my waies aright in thy ſight, and to guide me in the paths of truth and righteouſneſſe; and Lord, lead mee into that ſtreight way, and through that narrow gate, which bringeth unto life eternall; that ſo of thy infinite mercie through Chriſt, I may enter in (though moſt unworthy) with them that obtaine grace to finde it, and there to live with thee, my God, in joy and bliſſe for evermore. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I yeeld and render unto thee, my Lord, all humble and poſſible praiſe, honour, and thankes, for all thy great and manifold mercies and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, ſpirituall and temporall, vouchſafed unto me thy moſt unworthy ſervant in ſoule and body from time to time; and alſo for thy gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of me and mine, and all other thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings beſtowed upon me this day paſt, and all my life hitherto. Now, good God, for Chriſts ſake, I humbly pray thee, to forgive and pardon all my ſinnes and treſpaſſes that I have committed before thee, inwardly or outwardly in ſoul or body, by thought, deſire, word or deed, this preſent day, or any time of my life heretofore. Mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, waſh away all my ſinnes out of thy ſight,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121289:40"/> with the moſt pretious bloud of that All-ſufficient ſacrifice, the innocent Lamb of God, Jeſus, who was ſlaine for our tranſgreſſions: hide all my ſins in his wounds, and bury them in his grave, ſo as they may never bee able to riſe in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, either to accuſe or to condemne mee. But Lord, make me of that bleſſed number, whoſe ſinnes thou wilt cover, and whoſe iniquities thou wilt pardon. And vouchſafe alſo to forgive my omiſſion of all thoſe good deeds I ought to have done, and my ſinfull neglect in the true perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all duty and ſervice that I owe unto thee; eſpecially my wicked negligence in calling upon thy holy Name, and daily praiſing thee for all thy mercies: and likewiſe I beg pardon for my often omitting, or ſlightly performing this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of praying unto thee as I ought, now and at all times; which Lord give me grace more carefully, faithfully and devoutly to perform towards thee, by the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit ever hereafter, that ſo of thine infinite mercy thou maieſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing mee to that eternall Kingdome which thou hall prepared, O God the Father, before the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, for all that truly love and beleeve in thee, to thy great praiſe and honour, and my ſalvation i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, through thy mercy, O bleſſed Lord God, to whom be glory now and ever.Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121289:41"/>
               <head>13. <hi>The concluſion for Munday, to be ſaid laſt, or in bed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O My God, I moſt humbly commmend and commit my ſelfe both body and ſoule, my children and grand-children, my kindred, friends and family, and all that doth belong unto me, here or elſe where, with all my fellow members in thy whole Church, into thy moſt gracious protection and preſervation, this night and alwaies. Good God, I beſeech thee, vouchſafe to bleſſe, ſanctifie and keep our ſoules and bodies in thy true faith, feare and favour, with ſafety, this night, and to our lives end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="prayer">
               <head>14. <hi>A Prayer at firſt awaking, for Tueſday, to our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY ſoule ſhall magnifie thee, O Lord, and my ſpirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour, who hath done and ſuffered great and many things for me, bleſſed be thy moſt holy Name for thy infinite benefits and bleſſings, both ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall beſtowed upon mee thy unworthy ſinfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant from time to time. And chiefly (Gracious Lord) for thy accompliſhment of my redemption before I had any being: who didſt vouchſafe to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121289:41"/> come into the world amongſt evill men, and to be borne of a Virgin, to take the ſhape and nature of man upon thee, and in our fleſh didſt work and performe all righteouſneſſe to bee imputed unto us; and alſo ſubmitted thy ſelfe to ſuffer the moſt bitter and ignominious death of the Croſſe, to free us from that eternall death, which our ſinnes have deſerved; and alſo roſe againe from the grave the third day, to overcome ſin, death, the grave, hell and Sathan, with all other things for us. And ſo thou, ſweet Jeſus, art become our reconciliation, redemption, righteouſneſſe, and juſtification, with hope alſo through thee of ſalvation and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification hereafter. Of all which thy ineſtimable benefits, I humbly pray thee, O Lord my Saviour, of thy infinite mercy both in this world, and after this life is ended, to make me thy poor unworthy ſervant a happy partaker amongſt thy Saints and ſervants, that I may live hereafter with thee and them, to praiſe and glorifie thy Name, my deare Jeſus, for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="prayer">
               <head>15. <hi>A Prayer for Tueſday morning, to God the Son, our Redeemer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Know that my Redeemer liveth, and ſhall ſtand the laſt day upon the earth, to judge the world in righteouſneſſe, and all the people with equity.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121289:42"/> O ſweet Ieſus Chriſt, who art my Lord and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Saviour, the beloved Son of God, the bleſſed Redeemer of the world, the only ſearcher of mans heart, before whom all things are manifeſt, all deſires knowne, and from thee no ſecrets can be hid: Lord cleanſe and reforme the thoughts of my wicked corrupt heart, by the inſpiration of thy moſt holy Spirit, to purge my heart, ſoul and conſcience from all ſin, evill, and dead works, rightly and faithfully, to feare and ſerve thee, the true and living Lord, that I may unfainedly love thee, and conſtantly praiſe and magnifie thy holy and bleſſed Name all the daies of my life, and for ever. Now, Gracious Ieſus, grant that the words of my mouth, and the thoughts, and meditations of my heart, in theſe and all other prayers and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions that I make unto thy Majeſty, may bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies guided by thy bleſſed Spirit, and that all my waies and actions; be directed according to thy holy word, and ſo by thy merciful aſſiſtance, all things I goe about, ſhall be ever right and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in thy ſight, O Lord God of truth, that art my ſtrength and my Redeemer. And deare Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who knoweſt the infinite corruption of my wretched nature, and my unaptneſſe to all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vouchſafe to draw and knit my heart and ſoule, to thy true feare and faithfull ſervice, and ſuffer no worldly reſpects, regard of perſons, nor any pleaſures, to withdraw my minde, or hinder my ſoule from the true performance of my daily
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121289:42"/> duties and ſervice towards thee, my God, with due obſervance of thy great Majeſtie, faithfully, devoutly and conſtantly ſerving thee, and calling on thy holy name, now and at all times, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhipping thee in ſpirit and truth, as thy ſelfe haſt commanded. And be thou pleaſed, dear Lord, by thy grace, to guide and direct my heart, ſoule, and body, with all my deſires, waies, and workes, according to thy owne good will and pleaſure; for I humbly commend and commit my ſelfe, my children and grand-children, with all belonging to mee, and all things that any way concerneth me, to thy moſt gracious protection, direction, and diſpoſing, now and ever. And I humbly pray thee, O my ſweet Ieſus, ſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent me with thy holy Spirit, that I bee led into no temptation this day by the divell or his evill agents, the vaine world, or my owne corrupt fleſh, neither ſuffer any ſinfull thoughts to poſſeſſe my ſoule; but aſſiſt me, I beſeech thee, to ſet a watch over my heart and waies, and before my mouth, and ſet a ſeale of grace and wiſdome over my ſoul, and upon my lips, that I offend not with my tongue, or in my actions, either againſt thee my God, my neighbour or my owne ſoule; but Lord, make my heart cleane and upright before thee, and keep me from falling into my former ſins againe, but indue me with grace ſo to number my daies, that I may apply my heart to wiſdome and goodneſſe, and daily endeavour and ſtrive to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121289:43"/> lead a new and godly life in thy ſight; and make me firme, ſtedfaſt, and conſtant in thy right Church, ſaving truth, and true faith unto my lives end, to live and die therein; but if I hold any errors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thy will and word (O Lord) ſpeedily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert my ſoule unto thee, and ſhew me the paths of life, and teach me thy truth, and ſuffer me not to ſlide from it, but ſo long as I live here, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet my whole heart, ſoule, and delight, to ſeek, to ſerve, to love, and to fear thee, my Lord, in all true obedience, humility, repentance, and purity, with ſtedfaſt faith in thee, and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of living, as is required of thy children and ſervants, through the aſſiſtance of thy bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the bleſſing of thy heavenly Father, who liveth and reigneth with thee, three Perſons, and one true eternall God, bleſſed for ever. Amen. Concluding my humble petition, with that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect prayer, which Chriſt our advocate hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and taught us ſaying, Our Father, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="prayer">
               <head>16. <hi>A Prayer for Tueſday at night to our bleſſed Saviour, for my ſelfe and children.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Sweet Ieſus Chriſt, that art both God and man, my bleſſed Saviour, Redeemer, and Mediator, who underſtandeſt all things, and ſeeſt what we want before we aske, and knoweſt beſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121289:43"/> what is in miſerable mortall man, that is made of earth, how corrupt my nature and ſubſtance is, how many and great my frailties and infirmities are, and how ſubject I am to fall into all manner of evill both in ſoule and body, if thy grace uphold me not: therefore I moſt humbly beſeech thee, O Lord, to receive me and mine now and ever, into thy provident and gracious care, to protect and direct us in all our waies to doe thy bleſſed will, and to live in all thy holy feare, to ſave and guide us waking from all ſinne and ſhame, and to keep and defend us ſleeping from all perills and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers either of ſoule or body, that ſo by thy mercie we may reſt in peace and ſafety this night, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo awake in thy grace and favour, and doe all things to thy honour and glory, and may live and dye thy true and faithfull ſervants; and after death vouchſafe, dear Lord, by thy merits and ſufferings to give us eternall life with thee in heaven, which thou haſt dearly purchaſed for us. Now ſweet Jeſus, vouchſafe to indue and aſſiſt mee with thy grace and holy Spirit, that I may be able rightly, faithfully, and confidently (as I ought to doe) to cry and pray unto thee, my God, for grace and mercie, that I may finde favour in thy ſight, and that my truſt in thee may never ceaſe, that ſo I may obtaine true contrition for all my offences, and pardon for my ſins paſt, with all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces for my ſalvation both in life and death, and aſſured hope of everlaſting life when
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121289:44"/> this is ended, through thy pretious death and bitter paſſion, ſweet Ieſus my Saviour. Now, good Lord, indue me with grace, to fit and prepare my ſoule as I ought, before my day of death approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that I be not taken unprovided; but aſſiſt me with thy bleſſed Spirit to worke in my heart a true and lively faith, to lay faſt hold upon all thy mercies, merits, and gracious promiſes, and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to apply them to my owne ſoule. And further give mee, I humbly pray thee, unfaigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and remiſſion of all my ſinnes, with other needfull graces for the performing of all holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to thy Majeſtie, that ſo I may be inabled right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully to ſerve and pleaſe thee while I live here; and alſo make me carefully to fit and prepare my ſoule for thy mercifull acceptance, before thou call me to thy ſelfe out of this vale of miſery; and give mee grace daily to die unto this world, and forſake it while I am in it, that I may live more and more in true holineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe before thee; and ſo I ſhall obtain bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe here to be directed by thee in all things, and to have thy protection over me to die happily in thee, and live eternally with thee, who art my only Saviour and Redeemer, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, to whom be all glory for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="prayer">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121289:44"/>
               <head>17. <hi>The concluſion for Tueſday, to be ſaid at night or in bed, to the Son, for my ſelfe and children.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY ſweet Ieſus, by thy grace and holy Name, keep mee thy poore ſervant, and all mine from all ſinne and ſhame, and by thy bitter death and paſſion, ſave us from thy great wrath, and endleſſe damnation, and by thy powerfull reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, raiſe us daily from ſin to grace and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, and by thy glorious aſcention, draw me thy unworthy ſervant continually to heaven after thee by a holy life and godly converſation; and of thy great mercie, after death, reſerve me to be where thou art, and make me partaker of thy everlaſting ſalvation; and in all my troubles, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and diſtreſſe, doe thou my griefes redreſſe, and be my bleſſed conſolation; and vouchſafe to receive me this night and alwaies into thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſervation: for now I will lay me downe in peace, and alſo reſt and ſleep, becauſe thou Lord, doſt only mee ſuſtaine, and wilt in ſafety keep: for on thee alone I wholly doe depend, who art all my hope, helpe, comfort, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſweet Ieſus my Saviour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="prayer">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:121289:45"/>
               <head>18. <hi>A Prayer for Wedneſday to the glorious Trinity at firſt awaking.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GReat is our God, and worthy to be praiſed, I will ſpeake of all thy marvellous workes, for thou haſt done great things, and holy is thy Name.</p>
               <p>To thee O God, heavenly Father, our gracious Creator of all things; with God the Son, that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Redeemer of mankinde, and God the Holy Ghoſt the ſanctifier of thine elect; unto thee, O Lord, three Perſons, one true and everliving God, be given and rendred as is due by mee, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy children and ſervants, all humble and poſſible praiſe and thanks, now and ever. For I thy moſt unworthy ſervant, doe humbly and thankfully acknowledge, that I finde thy bleſſings and benefits both ſpirituall and temporall, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and waking, daily and howrely, to be renued towards me, for which I bleſſe and magnifie thy holy Name, eſpecially for thoſe ſpirituall graces thou haſt vouchſafed unto my ſoule from time to time, before I had any being, for my election by the whole Trinity, and my creation by God the Father, which thou didſt fully performe in thine owne innocent perſon: but chiefly in that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite love token unto mankinde, of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ordaining and ſending thy deare Son out of thy boſome into the world; and thou, O Chriſt,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121289:45"/> in comming amongſt wicked men, to put thy ſelfe into their cruell hands for our redemption, and ſo become our righteouſneſſe, juſtification, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which thou haſt dearly purchaſed for us with thy own bloud. And ſince I was borne, O bleſſed Spirit, for my continuall preſervation, and daily ſupply of all needfull bleſſings for my ſoule and body, eſpecially for my vocation, and calling to the right knowledge of God and his ſaving truth, with ſome meaſure of true faith, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and regeneration from ſinne to grace, all wrought in mee by the holy operation of thee Lord Holy Ghoſt; by whom alſo we are united unto our Lord and head Chriſt Jeſus, from whom Lord let me never be ſeparated. Now vouchſafe O God, ſtill to continue all thy mercies towards me; and chiefly in giving me daily a ſupply and increaſe of all heavenly gifts, and ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whereby I may be able rightly, faithfully, and conſtantly, to feare and love, to ſeek, ſerve, and pleaſe thee my God, in all things as I ought to doe; that ſo I may obtaine thy grace and favour (by thy aſſiſtance) to live a holy life here accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy will, that thou of thy infinite mercie, Almighty God, and glorious Trinity, maieſt make me partaker of thy heavenly Kingdome of glory hereafter. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="prayer">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:121289:46"/>
               <head>19. <hi>A Prayer to the Trinity for Wedneſday morning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God the Father of heaven, the gracious Creator of all things, the righteous judge, that ſearcheth the heart, and trieth the children of men, and beholdeth all our waies; and knoweſt my ſubſtance is but duſt, fleſh and bloud, and my nature as it is corrupted by ſin, is of it ſelfe, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſuall and diveliſh, and can merit nothing from thee, O Lord, but condemnation. Deare God, the originall of all goodneſſe, I moſt humbly beſeech thee to have mercy upon mee miſerable ſinner, and enter not into judgement with thy poore ſervant, for no fleſh living is righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; neither reward me after my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for I am a wretched and moſt ſinfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and have done exceeding much evill in thy ſight; but I humbly pray thee, O God, for thy dear Son and my Saviours ſake, to withdraw thy great wrath and heavy diſpleaſure from mee, which my ſinnes have juſtly deſerved; and if it be thy will Lord releaſe my preſent afflictions, which now and long have lain upon me: and vouchſafe alſo to prevent and remove thoſe weighty judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that hang over my head for my iniquities, that by thy unſpeakable mercies I may eſcape them; yet if thou pleaſe further to viſit mee with fatherly chaſtiſements for the amendment of my
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121289:46"/> faults; Lord give me wiſdome and patience to beare all things as I ought to doe, without offence towards thee, and by thy grace to make the beſt and righteſt uſe of all thou ſendeſt, ſo as in the end they may turne to thy glory and the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my ſalvation in Chriſt my Lord. O God the Son, Redeemer of mankinde, who didſt vouchſafe to bee borne of a woman, to become man for our redemption, and cameſt into the world to ſeek and ſave all thoſe that were loſt by ſin, that they might live by faith in thee; which Lord grant unto me, ſweet Jeſus my Saviour, and have mercie upon me a wicked ſinner, to forgive and pardon all my ſinnes and offences that I have done before thee all my life paſt in thought, word and deed; and impute not my iniquities unto me, neither deſtroy mee with my tranſgreſſions, nor let thy heavy diſpleaſure reſerve evill for me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: but deare Lord, of thy great goodneſſe grant me thy poore ſervant true faith, and unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentance, with thy gracious remiſſion of all my treſpaſſes, and waſh my ſinnes out of thy ſight with thine owne moſt pretious and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, which thou didſt ſo freely ſhed for our redemption; naile all my offences upon thy croſſe, and bury them in thy grave, ſo as they may never be able to come in judgement againſt mee, either to accuſe or ſhame me in this world, or to condemne and confound mee in the world to come, for thy mercies ſake, ſweet Jeſus my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121289:47"/> But I moſt humbly beſeech thee, O Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſanctifie and cleanſe my heart and ſoule from all ſinne and evill, by thy holy Spirit, that I may be upright in thy ſight, to reforme all my waies before thee, and let thy grace and holy Spirit lead mee into the paths of truth and righteouſneſſe all my life, that after death thou maieſt of thy infinite mercy bring me to that everlaſting inheritance of happineſſe which thou haſt ſo dearly purchaſed for us with thine owne bloud, in whom is all my truſt, who art my only Saviour, Mediator and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate for ever. O God the Holy Ghoſt, our comforter, preſerve and ſanctifie thou my heart and ſoule, that I may unfeignedly love thee, truly feare thy holy Name, and faithfully ſerve, pleaſe and obey thee, as I ought to doe now and all the daies of my life: And vouchſafe, O bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to inſtruct and inlighten my ſoule and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, with the true knowledge, devout love, and ſtedfaſt beliefe of thy ſacred truth, and keepe me therein for ever. O Holy Ghoſt, vouchſafe to make thy ſeat and dwelling in my ſoule, and let thy holy Spirit take full poſſeſſion of my heart, and abide alwaies with mee to fill me with all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces, whereby I may bee preſerved from falling into any ſinne or evill, and bee inabled to doe all good that may be beſt pleaſing unto thee, and to performe all duty and ſervice (by thy aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) in an acceptable manner unto my graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Almighty God, the Father, the Son, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121289:47"/> the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, and one ever glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trinity, to whom be rendred all praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, power, and thanks, as is right due, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="prayer">
               <head>20. <hi>An evening Prayer to God the Holy Ghoſt for Wedneſday.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God the Holy Ghoſt, bleſſed Spirit, by whom we are ſanctified and ſealed unto the day of redemption, and by whoſe holy operation, we are joyned unto our bleſſed Lord and head Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; from whom let nothing in heaven or earth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeparate me: And mercifull Lord I humbly pray thee, caſt me not in thy diſpleaſure out of thy care and favour for my ſinnes, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw not thy grace and holy Spirit from me, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſake me, nor leave me to my ſelfe, who am wholly ſubject to all wickedneſſe. But I moſt humbly beſeech thee, to creat in me a new, a clean, an upright, a faithfull and perfect heart in thy ſight, to walke in all true holineſſe before thee, as thou requireſt, all my daies to come; and good Lord, daily renue thy grace, and a right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit within mee, to ſanctifie and cleanſe my ſoule from ſinne, to preſerve mee from falling into evill, and to guide me into the waies of truth and righteouſneſſe. Now dear Lord, marke me thy
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121289:48"/> poore ſervant for thine owne, and prevent mee with thy grace that I never grieve, deſpight, or neglect thee my God in any thing, neither to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt or quench the good motions of thy holy Spirit in my heart at any time; but I moſt humbly pray and deſire to bee led and directed in all things by thee, who beſt knoweſt my frailties and infirmities, that I can (of my ſelfe) neither will nor performe any good at all, much leſſe call upon thy holy Name as I ought, all my beſt works and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, being full of imperfection and corruption; but I humbly beſeech thee, good Lord, to accept in me the will for thee deed, the affection for the action; and vouchſafe to heale and helpe my great diſability to any goodneſſe, and teach, and aſſiſt me rightly, faithfully and conſtantly, to pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee my God, now and at all times according to thy holy will, and daily to call upon thy great Name in truth and ſincerity. And be pleaſed, O Lord Holy Ghoſt, to prepare, aſſiſt and lift up my heart and ſoule towards thee, and bend downe thine eare of mercy to heare me, and vouchſafe thou bleſſed Lord, to make requeſt by thy grace in mee, with ſuch inward and faithfull devotion, humility, ſighs and groans as cannot be expreſſed, that ſo my ſupplications may bee acceptable to God my heavenly Father, through the merits and ſufferings, of my dear Saviour Jeſus, and the holy working of thee O God the Holy Ghoſt, my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121289:48"/> who art the ſanctifier and preſerver both of my ſoule and body; I humbly pray thee to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame my heart and ſpirit with fervent zeale and unfeigned devotion to the true and conſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all duties and ſervices that I owe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee my God. And vouchſafe Lord, by thy holy Spirit to infuſe into my ſoule everlaſting and devout love towards thy Majeſty, with Chriſtian charity towards all my brethren, thy children and ſervants: And Lord, put thou a right and ſtedfaſt hope into my heart that my truſt in thee may never faile, till I have attained to the eternall felicity, which God the Father hath prepared, and our bleſſed Saviour hath purchaſed, and thou bleſſed Spirit by thy holy aſſiſtance wilt bring us unto, to glorifie the Name of my God in heaven hereafter for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="prayer">
               <head>21. <hi>The concluſion for Wedneſday at night, to the bleſſed Trinity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MErcifull God, heavenly Father, bleſſed Son, and Holy Ghoſt, who haſt appointed the night for all mortall creatures to take reſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which our weake natures cannot ſubſiſt: I am now in health by thy gracious providence, by thy favour, and laid downe in my bed, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth the grave, and by thy mercie hope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121289:49"/> to take quiet reſt and ſleepe, that is the image of death, from which I know not whether ever I ſhall awake againe to this worlds light, for my life dependeth on thy good pleaſure; therefore I moſt humbly pray thee of thy infinite mercy, O God, to forgive all my ſins paſt that I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thee, this preſent day or heretofore, through the merits and ſufferings of my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Jeſus; and vouchſafe heavenly Father to bee reconciled unto mee, thy moſt guilty ſinfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, in and through thy dear and innocent Son, who is my righteous Saviour: And grant while I live here, that in Chriſt I may hereafter live to thee, and thy faithfull ſervice; and when I ſleepe, Lord let me ſafely reſt by thy bleſſed preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, that I may continue in thy true faith, feare and favour with a good conſcience unto my laſt breath; that ſo if thou call me away this night, or any other time in my ſleep, thou wilt in Chriſt pardon my ſinnes, and after death receive my ſoule to thy grace and mercy, to remaine with thee for ever, and may praiſe thee, my God, everlaſtingly. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="prayer">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:121289:49"/>
               <head>22. <hi>A Prayer for Thurſday morning at firſt awaking to God the Father.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY God, I heartily praiſe thee for my preſent health, reſt and preſervation this night and formerly, and ſafe approach by thy providence to this light. I humbly beſeech thee, vouchſafe this day and alwaies, to bee my preſent helpe in all dangers, and my mercifull God to pardon all my ſinnes and wickedneſſe, that I have done hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and to prevent and to protect mee by thy grace and favour from falling into any ſin or evill to offend thee hereafter; and direct me by thy holy Spirit in all things I goe about, to doe that which is acceptable in thy ſight (through Chriſt) and to the beſt for my owne ſoule. Deare Lord, give me thy ſinfull ſervant thy grace, whereby I may be able rightly and faithfully to ſeeke, ſerve, and pleaſe thee my God, as I ought to doe, this day and at all times throughout my whole life: Theſe great bleſſings I beg of thee, O God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by thy gracious aſſiſtance, in, and through, and for the ſake of thine owne deare Sonne, and my only Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous. So bee it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="prayer">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:121289:50"/>
               <head>23. <hi>A Prayer for Thurſday morning to God the Father.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt mighty God, and my mercifull Father, the giver of all good gifts: grant mee thy grace and the light of thy countenance, to guide mee this day and ever, to walke in thy paths of truth and righteouſneſſe all my life, and to runne in the way of thy Commandements unto my end; for thy beloved Sonne hath taught us before all things to ſeek that which is moſt needfull, even the Kingdome of God, and the rightouſneſſe thereof, and then our heavenly Father will ſupply all things elſe which he knoweth to be neceſſary for us: Good Lord, make me (with <hi>Mary)</hi> to chooſe the better part, to ſeek, heare, and follow our Saviour Jeſus, and let that never bee taken from mee thy poore ſervant. To which end, I humbly pray thee, O God, to weane and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my heart and ſoule, from the cares, love or liking of this vilde world, and all the vanities thereof, all which like a dream and ſhadow fade away: And Lord, drive all wicked thoughts out of my minde, and baniſh covetous deſires (the root of all evill) from my heart, and make me ever conſider what it would advantage me, if I could win the whole world, and ſhould loſe my owne ſoule. Therefore I beſeech thee, O Lord, by thy holy Spirit, to ſettle my heart and ſoul, my deſires,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121289:50"/> affections, and delight, only upon thee my God, thy glory, thy Kingdome, thy righteouſneſſe; and make me to account all earthly things but droſſe and dirt ſo that I may win Chriſt, and attaine to the excellent knowledge of Jeſus my Saviour, who is the Lord of life, him chiefly, O God, let me finde and obtaine to be mine, with whom I ſhall have all other good things, by thy infinite mercie I beſeech thee, that ſo I may be able rightly and faithfully to ſerve and pleaſe thee as I ought, while I live heare, that after death thou of thy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able goodneſſe, maieſt make mee partaker of thy heavenly Kingdome of glory. And now, deare God, vouchſafe unto me thy moſt unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant the grace of daily and unfeigned ſorrow and repentance for all my ſins, with a ſound ſenſe and feeling of them in a contrite ſpirit, with care to reforme all my former faults in the reſt of my life, and make me ſtrictly to examine my owne heart, ſoule, knowledge, and conſcience, of all the evills I have done before thee, and ſeverely to judge, hate and condemne my ſelfe for them, that ſo I may eſcape thy great wrath, and may not bee judged and condemned by thee in thy heavy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, which I am not able to beare; for who can ſtand in the ſight of thy great Majeſty when thou art angry? therefore I moſt humbly pray thee, good God, in the multitude of thy mercies, to forgive and grant me thy grace and pardon of all my ſins and offences paſt that I am guilty of,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121289:51"/> for thy beloved Sonnes ſake, that ſo my iniquities may never be imputed unto me; but Lord give me true faith to lay faſt hold upon thy mercies, and all thy gracious promiſes, and the merits and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Ghriſt, with grace rightly to apply them to my owne ſalvation, through Jeſus my Saviour; that ſo I may be quit through him, and freed of my account with thee before I die; and grant that I may daily die unto the world, and hate all the vaine preſſures thereof, and may live more and more unto thee in all righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of living before thee as becommeth thy Saints: that ſo when thy appointed time is come for me to enter into my long ſleep of death, that thou wilt be pleaſed by thy holy Spirit to fit and prepare me, and to give me a happy and bleſſed departure out of this life, to die in the Lord that I may reſt in peace and ſafety, and be raiſed up by my Saviour to grace and glory, that thou pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all my ſinnes, and receiving me to mercie, thou maieſt wipe all teares from mine eies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all ſorrow from my ſoule, and for Jeſus ſake to admit me into thy glorious preſence, and there to enjoy eternall felicitie, and be a happy member of thy bleſſed Church triumphant to praiſe thee there for evermore. Amen. And the bleſſing of God Almighty, the eternall Father, the beloved Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, be ever with mee, to ſanctifie, bleſſe and preſerve my ſoule and body in thy feare and favour, and true faith, ſtedfaſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121289:51"/> hope, and perfect charity unto my lifes end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="prayer">
               <head>24. <hi>A Prayer to God the Father for Thurſday night.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAve mercy upon me, O Lord, and hearken unto my prayer, for I know thou Lord wilt bleſſe the righteous, and with thy favour wilt compaſſe him as with a ſhield. Lord thou loveſt not wickedneſſe, neither ſhall evill dwell with thee, thou ſhalt deſtroy them that ſpeake lies, for thou abhorreſt all them that worke iniquity: yet thou deſireſt not the death of a ſinner but that he ſhould returne and live; therefore deare Lord, deliver my ſoule and ſave me in thy manifold mercies, for I have grievouſly ſinned before thee, and my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are gone over my head into thy preſence, and are too heavy for mee to beare. But I moſt humbly beſeech thee, for thy beloved Son Jeſus ſake, to give me unfaigned ſorrow and repentance for all my ſinnes paſt, which are great and many, and grant me thy gracious pardon and remiſſion for all my offences committed this day or hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt thee; and Lord, indue me with true faith to lay hold of all thy mercies, and my Saviours merits and ſufferings, with grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, reforme my life, according to thy moſt holy word and Commandements, all the reſt of my
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121289:52"/> daies to come: to which end Lord give me a ſoft, a penitent, upright and contrite heart, with a tender conſcience, and a true and ſound ſenſe and feeling of all my ſinnes, infirmities, and ſpirituall wants, with grace earneſtly and faithfully to cry and pray unto thee for mercie and reliefe in all my neceſſities, and chiefly for all ſpirituall graces to my ſoule. And as I truſt thou wilt awake mee from the dulneſſe of this nights ſleep in ſafety to the morning light; ſo dear Lord, by thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit daily quicken my ſoule from the deadneſſe of ſinne, to newneſſe of life, and raiſe me up in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hereafter, from the darkneſſe of death, unto light and life eternall, to live with thee my God for evermore. Now gracious Lord, receive mee with all that doth belong unto me into thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protection now and alwaies, to keep and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from all ſinne and evill, giving us this night quiet ſleep, health and reſt if it be thy will; and grant whether I ſleep or wake, live or dye, I may be wholly thine, and doe all to thy honour and glory; that ſo both in life and death, Chriſt may be to me an advantage, through thy infinite mercie, O my bleſſed Lord God. Now I humbly pray thee, ſo to inlighten the darkneſſe of my ſoul and underſtanding with thy grace, that I may ſee clearly the right way to heavenly happineſſe, and by thy aſſiſtance follow hard after it untill I have attained to it; and alſo for thy holy Names ſake defend mee from all perills and dangers of this
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121289:52"/> night either to my ſoule or body, to me or any of mine, for the love of thy only Son, my deare Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt: for whoſe ſake, grant me alſo the guard of thy holy and good Angells now and ever, that they may pitch their tents about mee to preſerve mee from all my enemies bodily and ghoſtly; and commit mee Lord to the cuſtody of thy bleſſed Spirit to keep me from falling into any ſinne or evill, and to guide my waies into the paths of truth and righteouſneſſe, that I may live in thy holy feare, and dye in thy faith and favour; and good God, grant that in the howre of my death, and in the day of judgement, thy dear Son and my ſweet Jeſus, may bee my mercifull judge and Saviour, to pardon and paſle by all my ſinnes, and cover them with his righteouſneſſe, that after death I may bee received and accepted into thy grace and favour, to live and remaine in joy and bliſſe eternally with thee my God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. Now, O God, who canſt doe abundantly, more then I can aske or thinke, to thee be all praiſe, honour and glory, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="prayer">
               <head>25. <hi>The concluſion for Thurſday night in bed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord my God, I thanke thee for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vouchſafed unto mee this preſent day
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121289:53"/> and formerly: and now be pleaſed, O Lord, by thy holy Spirit to ſanctifie me thy poor unworthy ſervant, in ſoule, body and ſpirit throughout, to thy right faithfull and conſtant ſervice all my daies; and aſſiſt me with thy grace that I may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe, lament, hate, leave and amend all my former miſdeeds, and may become faithfully and unfainedly thine in all true obedience and ſincere and perfect love toward thy Majeſty, both living and dying, and for ever; that through thy mercy and Chriſts merits, I may be found blameleſſe at the appearance of my Lord Jeſus, by whom I truſt to obtaine to live in heaven with thee, and to bee preſented by my Saviour unto thy gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance in that great day of the Lord, to remain with thee my God for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="prayer">
               <head>26. <hi>A Prayer for Friday at firſt awaking to God the Son.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEare Saviour Jeſus, have mercy upon mee a miſerable ſinner: Thou immaculate Lambe of God, that kneweſt no ſinne, but diedſt for our tranſgreſſions, and ſhed thine owne moſt pretious bloud to cleanſe us from ſinne: I moſt humbly praiſe and magnifie thy holy Name for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies who haſt done and ſuffered great and many things for mee, but eſpecially I bleſſe thee for
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121289:53"/> thoſe ſpirituall bleſſings thou haſt beſtowed upon me before I was borne, and hitherto. Now ſweet Jeſus, who knoweſt my frailty, I doe moſt humbly pray thee never to leave me to my ſelf, nor to my ſoules enemies, neither while I live, at my death, nor in the great and dreadfull day of judgement, when all things ſhall bee made manifeſt before thee, and it will be wholly in thy power to ſave or to condemne; then Lord Jeſus looke in mercie on me as one of thine, whom thou loveſt to the end, to pardon and cover all my ſinnes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me into thy grace and favour, for by thee only commeth my ſalvation, and in thee, O Lord, is my whole truſt: Therefore vouchſafe Lord, to continue thy goodneſſe, thy favour, and thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe towards me this day and for ever, in forgiving all my iniquities, that I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in my whole life paſt; and alſo my ſinfull omiſſion of thoſe duties and good workes, which thou haſt commanded, and I have wickedly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected. But I moſt humbly beſeech thee, my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to indue mee thy moſt unworthy ſervant with thy grace and holy Spirit, to direct my heart, and all my waies aright before thee, and preſerve me at all times in the ſincere and perfect love of thy divine Majeſty, and in thy feare and favour, with unfaigned repentance and amendment of life, that I may obtaine thy gracious pardon for all my offences; and Lord, give me true faith, ſtedfaſt hope, and perfect charity unto my li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:121289:54"/> end. Theſe great mercies I aske at thy gracious hands, deare Jeſus Chriſt, who art my only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Redeemer, Mediator, and Advocate; to whom be all praiſe and glory for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="prayer">
               <head>27. <hi>A morning Prayer for Friday, to God the Sonne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SWeet Saviour, none can come to the Father but by thee; and whoſoever commeth unto thee thou caſteſt not away, but wilt raiſe him up at the laſt day unto eternall life.</p>
               <p>Now deare Jeſus, thou bleſſed Son, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lambe of God, that takeſt away the ſinnes of the ſinnes of the world, who graciouſly calleſt unto thee all heavy laden and penitent ſinners that thou maieſt eaſe and refreſh them; have pity on me, and vouchſafe to ſanctifie and cleanſe my ſoule and body, from all ſinne and evill by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, and make mee pure and upright in thy ſight, and be pleaſed to protect and direct my heart and ſoule, and all my waies before thee, and to indue me with thy bleſſed Spirit, to preſerve mee from falling into any ſin or offence towards thee; but aſſiſt me with thy grace in all things I goe about to doe, that I may doe that which may be moſt acceptable and beſt pleaſing in thy fight. Now Lord, I confeſſe that I was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121289:54"/> and borne in ſinne, and I am a miſerable and wretched ſinner above all others, and unto whom ſhould I come, but to thee the Saviour of mankinde, who cameſt into the world to ſave ſinners by thy grace, of whom I am chiefe? O fountaine of mercy, who didſt vouchſafe to bee borne of the bleſſed and pure Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> (to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come man) and tookeſt our wretched nature upon thee, therein to ſuffer death, to reaſſume us from eternall death, ſinne, the grave, hell and Sathan, and didſt willingly lay down thine owne life for us, which no man could take from thee, that wee might live by faith through thee; and alſo thou hadſt power to take it up againe, and didſt riſe from the grave the third day for our juſtification, and to vaniſh all our ſpirituall enemies: and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thou our Lord, didſt gloriouſly aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, there to take poſſeſſion, and make interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us unto thy heavenly Father, with whom thou doſt reigne in heaven for ever, whither thou doſt graciouſly and daily draw to thee all thoſe that truly beleeve in thee, there to live hereafter with thee; of which number, deare Lord, in the fulneſſe of thy mercies make me one. Now I fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humbly pray thee, ſweet Jeſus, the Saviour of all that truſt in thee, that thou wilt have mercy on mee, to forgive and pardon all my ſinnes and offences paſt, and preſent, both originall and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, of omiſſion and commiſſion, of infirmity or preſumption, whatſoever I ſtand guilty of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121289:55"/> theee, and even thoſe ſecret ſinnes, that none but thy All-ſeeing eyes, and my owne conſcience can teſtifie againſt mee, which is more then a thouſand witneſſes: I humbly pray thee to caſt them all behinde thy backe into the pit of oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, never to come in remembrance with thee; and waſh all my faults out of thy ſight with that bleſſed ſtreame of thine owne moſt pretious bloud, which thou didſt ſo plentifully ſhed for us in thy moſt bitter paſſion. O bleſſed Lord, let not all theſe thy mercies and benefits which thou haſt done and purchaſed for mankinde, be fruitleſſe or in vaine towards mee, thy poore unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, whoſe confidence is only in thee, that thou wilt make mee a happy partaker of all thy great benefits and favours: And ſweet Ieſus, grant through thy mercies, merits and infinit ſufferings, that my tranſgreſſions may never bee laid to my charge: for there is no other name under heaven but thine only, bleſſed Ieſus our righteous Lord, by which we can be ſaved. To thee bee rendred as is due all honour, praiſe, thanks, and glory, for ever and ever: Concluding my petition with that perfect Prayer, which thy ſelfe haſt taught us, ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art in heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="prayer">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:121289:55"/>
               <head>28. <hi>A Prayer for Friday night, to God the Sonne, our bleſſed Saviour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will love thee dearly, O Lord my ſtrength, for thou art my helper, my refuge, and the lifter up of my head, and I will praiſe thy name ſo long as I have breath. O Lord Chriſt, by whom was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the Law and the Prophets, and in thee all the promiſes of God are Yea and Amen, to the glory of God the Father, and the comfort of all thy ſervants; thou art that pure and innocent Lambe of God, that was killed and is alive, to thee was given all power, honour and glory, who liveth and raigneth for ever in heaven and earth, of whoſe Kingdome there is no end; to thee Lord bee all poſſible praiſe and thanks for ever. This is my only Lord and bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, who died for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our juſtification, and art our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate in heaven; ſo that whatſoever we ſhall ask the Father in thy name, according to thy will, if we beleeve, we ſhall obtaine it for thy ſake, who art the beloved Son of God, in whom only hee is well pleaſed. My deare God, have mercy upon me a moſt grievous ſinner to pardon all my offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces paſt, in ſoule or body, of ignorance or wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of frailty, neglect, contempt or wicked ſtubborneſſe; bury them all, ſweet Jeſus, in thy grave, and cleanſe them from before thine eyes,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121289:56"/> with thy moſt pretious bloud, which thou didſt of thine owne accord and infinite love ſhed for us, to free us from eternall death which by our ſinnes are due; therefore gracious Lord, grant through thy merits, and manifold ſufferings, that my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities may never be able to appeare before thee againſt me, either to accuſe or condemne me, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this life, at my death, nor in the great and laſt judgement: but in that dreadfull day, Lord by all thy mercies I beſeech thee, ſhew thy ſelf my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Saviour, to paſſe by &amp; cover all my miſdeeds with thy righteouſneſſe, that ſo I may eſcape thy juſt wrath which my tranſgreſſions have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Now, deare Ieſus, while I live here, make me thy unworthy ſervant wholly thine, to be thy faithfull and conſtant diſciple, and ſo to love thee as to keep thy Commandements which are not grievous, but in obeying them there is great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and let me ſo follow thee here, as to bee lowly and meek, to forſake my ſelfe and the world, and to take up all my croſſes with patience, and ſtrive to goe after thy ſteps, though I be farre unable to drinke of that heavy and bitter cup of Gods wrath of which thou ſo deeply taſtedſt, who art the propitiation for our ſinnes to deliver us from that fearfull condemnation due unto us: my offences Lord, I confeſſe did adde unto that weighty burden of Gods heavy diſpleaſure, and our grievous ſinnes which thou didſt beare upon the croſſe for all true beleevers, who ſhall paſſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121289:56"/> from death, to life eternall, which thy ſufferings, O Chriſt, hath purchaſed for us; whereby I, the unworthieſt of thy ſervants doe alſo hope to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee hereafter, from the grave to heaven at the reſurrection of the juſt, that according to thy will declared before thy death, all that are thine ſhall bee with thee, even where thou art to enjoy all bliſſe and happineſſe; in thine owne love by thy unmerited mercies, we ſhall bee made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with thee of thy heavenly Kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there to ſerve and praiſe thy glorious Name, who art moſt worthy, world without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="prayer">
               <head>29. <hi>The concluſion for Friday night.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LOrd Ieſus, vouchſafe to receive me this night into thy gracious protection both in life and death: And deare Lord, I humbly pray thee to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten me with thy grace rightly and faithfully to ſerve and obey thee in all true devotion, and with due ſubmiſſion to thy holy will in all things ſo long as I live; and now Lord, I am in health laid downe in my bed by thy loving permiſſion, hoping to take quiet reſt and ſleep, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to give me, and alſo I truſt by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to a wake in thy grace and favour to the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light againe, becauſe thou gracious Lord,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121289:57"/> doſt only me ſuſtaine, and wilt in ſafety thy poore ſervant keep; who doe moſt humbly commend and commit my ſelfe, my ſoule and body, my children and grand-children, and all I have to thee, from whom I have received all the good I doe enjoy, for thou haſt ſhewed great mercies unto me; for which I bleſſe and praiſe thy holy Name, beſeeching thee to give me grace, never to forget thy benefits, but to continue Lord thy true and faithfull ſervant unto my death, and for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="prayer">
               <head>30. <hi>A Prayer to the bleſſed Trinity, at firſt waking for Saturday morning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will praiſe the Lord becauſe he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever; by whom we live, move, and have our being, our maintenance, ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and preſervation. Now glorious Trinity, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, I humbly pray thee, vouchſafe unto mee thy moſt unworthy ſervant, ſuch grace and favour to knit my heart and ſoule faſt to theee, ſo that my ſinnes, nor my ſoules ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the wicked world, my owne corrupt fleſh, nor the malice of the Divell, may not be able to pluck mee out of thy mercifull and powerfull hands; but Lord aſſiſt me with thine owne bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, that I may daily continue and increaſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121289:57"/> in all ſincere and perfect love and obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy Majeſty; and in thy feare and favour, and all other ſaving graces, to have a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before thee, with true faith, ſtedfaſt hope, and perfect charity unto my lifes end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="prayer">
               <head>31. <hi>A Prayer unto the Trinity for Saturday morning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord our God, how excellent is thy Name in all the world, for thou haſt laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the earth, and the heavens are the workes of thy hands, and thou didſt create, and doſt governe, diſpoſe and rule the whole world, with all things therein, according to thy good pleaſure. O moſt divine and adored Trinity, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Son and Holy Ghoſt, three perſons, but one true, eternall and everliving God, to whom be all praiſe, honour and glory as is right and due for ever. Thou only by thy word and power didſt make all things for thine owne glory, eſpecially mankinde after thine image in purity and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to thine own ſervice; for by thy ptovidence and mercy commeth all good gifts and bleſſings unto us, and alſo deliverances only from thee, of thoſe evills and dangers which ſinne hath made us ſubject unto in falling from thee, and our firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, by the ſubtillty and malice of Sathan and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121289:58"/> our owne frailty, yet of thine owne free grace thou didſt elect a number by thee ſelected of thy choſen ſervants to inherit an eternall Kingdome, with and through thy beloved Son, whom thou didſt ordain and ſend into the world at thine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time to be the redemption of all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in thee. O God the Son our bleſſed Lord Jeſus Chriſt, it is written of thee that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe the will of God the Father, who ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee to be our Redeemer, and wert made of God unto us, wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ſalvation, with glorification hereafter. Now deare Jeſus, who haſt paid our ranſome, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the all-ſufficient and acceptable ſacrifice of thine own pretious bloud to waſh away our ſins, who was lifted upon the croſſe between heaven and earth to make an attonement betwixt God and man, his heavy wrath and our grievous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſo thou art become our Prieſt, to offer up thy innocent ſelfe to cleanſe us from our ſinnes, who art our Prophet to inſtruct and teach us and direct our waies aright, to ſhew us the path of life, and make the way plaine before our faces, and by thy example, to beare our croſſe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and follow thee that art the way, the truth and the life, to lead us to eternall ſalvation; alſo thou art our King to protect, defend, and reigne over us in mercy, truth and righteouſneſſe, till thine enemies be made thy footſtoole, and all that hate thee be deſtroyed before thee, for God hath
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121289:58"/> put all things in ſubjection under his feet, then ſhalt thou judge the whole world in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and equity, and wilt bring thy ſervants, to that eternall inheritance, which thou haſt by thy merits and ſufferings ſo dearly purchaſed for us, who wert borne unto us to be the joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all people, and the glory and ſalvation of all that truly beleeve and truſt in thee our Saviour. O God Holy Ghoſt, the giver, worker and ſealer of all graces unto us; by thee we are called to the knowledge of God and his ſaving truth, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to the performance of his will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements certified by the holy Spirit of our ſalvation in Chriſt Jeſus, and by thee applied unto us to bee regenerated and borne againe by thy holy operation from ſin to grace, to thy glory and our endleſſe felicity. And thy Spirit alſo witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to our ſpirits that we are the children of God and heires with Chriſt of the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the eternall comfort of all thy ſervants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by thee alſo united to our bleſſed Chriſt, and ſealed to the day of redemption, and continually aſſiſting us to all goodneſſe. Now great and glorious Lord God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, thou haſt plentifully powred downe thy manifold mercies and favours upon us, and multiplied ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly thy bleſſings and benefits ſpirituall and temporall towards us before we had being in the world, ſince we were borne, and after death thou haſt laid up an eternall weight of glory for all
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121289:59"/> thoſe to poſſeſſe that truly beleeve in thee, which give me grace to doe, for none hath or ever can deſerve them. Oh the abundant mercy, bounty, and goodneſſe of our gracious God towards mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall mankinde! who can declare the height and depth of Gods unſpeakable love, or be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thankfull to him for ſuch unexpreſſible bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits; but with <hi>David,</hi> we may ſay (Lord) What is man that thou art mindefull of him? Or what ſhall we render to thee for all thy mercies, having in us no good at all, but what we receive from thy ſelfe? therefore Lord, adde this further grace unto thy former favours, by the aſſiſtance of thine owne Spirit, to make us thy unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, able, rightly, faithfully, and conſtantly to feare, love, honour, ſerve, obey and praiſe thy moſt glorious Name while we live, and for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="prayer">
               <head>32. <hi>A Prayer to God the Holy Ghoſt, for Saturday night.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O God Holy Ghoſt, the giver of all graces and and my gracious ſanctifier, comforter and preſerver, thou knoweſt my infirmities, my incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to all evill, and backwardneſſe to any goodneſſe: vouchſafe Lord, to ſanctifie mee thy poore ſinfull ſervant, in ſoule, body and ſpirit
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121289:59"/> throughout, to thy true feare, intire love, and right faithfull and conſtant ſervice, all my time to come: And be pleaſed Lord, by thy grace to enlighten my dull ſoule and underſtanding, with the ſound knowledge, ſincere love, and ſtedfaſt beleefe of thy ſaving truth, and keepe me ever conſtant therein. And vouchſafe, deare Lord, to inrich me thy poore unworthy ſervant, with the infinite treaſure of that heavenly wiſdome from above, which waiteth about thy Throne, that may teach me thy holy will, and what is good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto thee; and inable me with grace to doe it, that ſo I may diſcerne between good and evill, and make me ſhunne and hate that which is evill, and follow and cleave unto that which is good; and to withdraw my love from this vaine world, and fix my affections upon thee my God, and on heavenly things that are above, that my chiefe treaſure may be ſettled there in heaven, and my heart alſo; and ſo I ſhall firſt ſeek to obtaine that which is moſt needfull, even thy glory, thy favour, and thy bleſſed Kingdome, and then Lord, I know thou wilt ſupply all the defects of grace in my ſoule, and heale all the infirmities of my body; but chiefly vouchſafe daily to continue and increaſe all ſpirituall graces in my ſoule by thy mercy and mighty power, O my bleſſed Lord God: to which end, O gracious Spirit, give mee an upright and penitent heart, an humble and lowly ſpirit, a quiet recollected minde freed
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121289:60"/> from the vanities and cares of this preſent world, and the love of this vile life; but Lord teach mee with <hi>Mary</hi> firſt and above all things to ſeek after thee my God, thy Kingdome, and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, ſo that I may have grace wholly to devote and dedicate my ſelfe, my time and beſt endeavours unto thy true and faithfull ſervice, and daily ſtudy and ſtrive to doe thy holy will in all things, and ſeek thy glory here, that ſo I may be partaker of thy heavenly Kingdome hereafter. And deare Lord Holy Ghoſt, inſpire me with thy grace daily to heare and read thy holy and bleſſed word as I ought to do, and that I may ſo imploy my time therein as to frame my life hereafter to thy glory and my ſoules good. And grant mee graciouſly, O God, to chuſe, to ſpeake, and to walke in the waies of truth and righteouſneſſe, and to ſet thy heavy judgements againſt ſin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before my face to deter and make mee daily to remember my owne laſt end, and by thy aſſiſtance to prepare for it, and to conſider the end in all my actions before I doe them, that I may never doe amiſſe; and let me ſtill remember thy all-ſeeing eyes are ever upon our waies that I may not diſpleaſe or offend thee in any thing: But Lord, indue me with thy holy Spirit to direct my heart and all my waies aright before thee, that ſo thou maieſt witneſſe to my ſpirit that I am the childe of God, and ever continue unto mee that unſpeakable comfort to give me the joyfull hope
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121289:60"/> of my ſalvation, through my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, unto my end: and in my end eſpecially eſtabliſh me with thy free ſpirit to worke in my ſoul all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces that may make me acceptable in thy ſight, through my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for whoſe ſake I beſeech thee further to extend thy goodnes towards me, to forgive all my ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that I have done before thee in my whole life paſt, and preſerve me in ſoul and body from all ſin and evill, either committing or falling on mee; but deare Lord, vouchſafe daily to ſupply and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon me all the benefits and bleſſings neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for this preſent life; but chiefly be pleaſed to ſanctifie my ſoule and body unto thy faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and indue me with all ſaving graces for my ſalvation both in life and death, that ſo I may bee able rightly and conſtantly to ſerve and pleaſe thee whilſt I live here, that alſo by thy gracious aſſiſtance I may obtaine a place hereafter to live with thee eternally, O Holy Ghoſt, and my bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord God, to whom be all thanks and praiſe for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="prayer">
               <head>33. <hi>The concluſion for Saturday night in bed to the weeks Prayers for mornings and nights.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Moſt humbly beſeech thee, my Lord God, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully to loke upon me and my manifold infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121289:61"/> and for Jeſus my Saviours ſake, vouchſafe to forgive and pardon all my ſinnes and grievous offences that I have committed in thy ſight all the daies of my life paſt; and in thy great mercy turne from me all thoſe evils that my tranſgreſſions have juſtly deſerved; and Lord, grant me thy preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace and fatherly providence to bee ſtill with mee to preſerve me at all times from falling into any ſinne or evill, either to offend thee my God, or to hurt my owne ſoule. And vouchſafe, Lord, ſo to direct and diſpoſe the heart and waies of me (thy moſt unworthy ſervant) towards the right performance of all duties and ſervices that I owe unto thee my God, and the happy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining (by my Lord Ieſus) of everlaſting ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to my owne ſelfe; that amongſt all the changes, chances and adverſities of this miſerable, mutable, and mortall life, I may ever be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thy ready helpe and favour from falling into ſin, ſhame, harme or danger, either in ſoule or body, and may be directed and aſſiſted by thy grace and providence to walke in the waies of righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe before thee, that thou my Lord Holy Ghoſt, maieſt guide me in all things I goe about, to doe that which may be moſt ſerviceable, acceptable, and beſt pleaſing in the ſight of my Lord God, to whom be all praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, power and eternall glory, for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:121289:61"/>
            <head>BOOK III.</head>
            <head>Short Prayers which may belong to any the three Books, when time ſerves, not for longer devotions.</head>
            <div n="1" type="preface">
               <head>1. <hi>A ſhort Preface before other prayers or petitions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord Holy Ghoſt, who beſt knoweſt my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold infirmities, have mercy and pity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me; and vouchſafe to prevent, or to baniſh and drive away all evill hindrances and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may withdraw my heart from God in the offering up of my prayers and humble petitions unto thy Majeſty; and be pleaſed Lord, to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, teach and aſſiſt me herein with thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and grace, that I may rightly and faithfully performe this duty and ſervice before thee, to thy glory and my good, and comfort of my ſoule through Chriſt Jeſus. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>2. <hi>A ſhort thanksgiving at firſt ſight of the morning light.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY bleſſed Lord God, I moſt humbly praiſe thee for thy gracious preſervation of mee with quiet reſt and health this night paſt, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121289:62"/> me in ſafety to this light; Lord bleſſe and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie me this day and ever unto thy faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and keep me alwaies in thy true faith, feare, favour and ready obedience; and make me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and unfaignedly thine all my life time, but in my death eſpecially, that when it pleaſeth thee to call for me out of this miſerable world, thou maieſt bring me to eternall ſalvation by thine own merits and meer mercy, ſweet Jeſus, I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <head>3. <hi>A Prayer for helpe in preſent temptation, in the time of prayer to our Lord Jeſus, who overcame and ſubdued the old tempter, the ſubtile Serpent our everlaſting enemy, from whom God defend us.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH my God, heavenly Father, who haſt made and ſeeſt all hearts, and knoweſt my great affection and fervent deſire rightly to ſerve thee, and my weakneſſe and frailty in performance thereof, have pity on my infirmities, and aſſiſt me with thy grace. And ſweet Jeſus my Saviour, who didſt ſuffer thy ſelfe to bee tempted by the Divell, that thou mighteſt overcome the tempter, and ſuccour all thoſe that are tempted; to thee Lord, I call and pray, for helpe and defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this malicious adverſary. O God the Holy Ghoſt, indue me with thy bleſſed Spirit and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſo to reſiſt him that he may flye from me, and baniſh thou Lord, all wicked hindrances and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121289:62"/> away from thy poore ſervant in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all my duties towards thee. Now deare God, have mercy upon me moſt miſerable ſinner, and in thy infinite mercy drive away this ſubtill enemy of my poore ſoule, with his pernitious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, the vaine world, and the corruptions of our owne nature, let them not prevaile over me at any time, for theſe are very ready to aſſault, tempt and draw my minde from thee in all my devotions and ſervices that I endeavour to offer unto thy Majeſty; and to make my prayers vaine and void, and drive me to fall into wicked neglect towards my God, whereby to prevent, deſtroy, and divert all my comforts and hopes in thee O Lord, which is the whole life of my ſoule. But Gracious God Almighty, whoſe power and ſtrength is above all, vouchſafe to overcome and baniſh all from mee, never to returne againe; and let thy bleſſed Spirit reſt conſtantly in me to withſtand all diſturbances in the performance of my duty before thee; and deare Lord, make new, cleane, and upright my heart, and frame it to thy holy will, that ſo by thy gracious aſſiſtance, I may faithfully ſerve and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee, pleaſe and praiſe thee my God, now and at all times, in this life and for ever, to thy glory, and my eternall comfort. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:121289:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The afternoone prayers at foure a clock for each day in the week. Munday.</hi> 1. <hi>A thanks giving to the bleſſed Trinity, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O My good and gracious God, great and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are thy mercies and bleſſings I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from thee both ſpirituall and temporall, from time to time; and now what ſhall I render unto thee, having no good to returne, but the poore fruit of my lips, which is nothing unto thee but the performance of our duties to praiſe thy great Name, and to acknowledge all thy benefits? therefore now I will give thanks to God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, our gracious Creator, who ſo loved us when we were his enemies, and had loſt our ſelves by ſinne, that he ordained, and after ſent his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and beloved Son into the world, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life; Chriſt being the propitiation for our ſinnes, that we may live by faith through him. And alſo I yeeld all poſſible praiſe unto my bleſſed Saviour, who became man, and in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite love willingly laid downe his life for us, and waſhed away our ſinnes with his owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious bloud, and made us by his merits and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, Kings and Prieſts unto God, and adopted children to his Father, and heires with himſelfe of an eternall Kingdome, by whoſe reſurrection we
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121289:63"/> have a lively hope of an inheritance that cannot be ſhaken, and withereth not, reſerved in heaven for us. Now to thee Lord Holy Ghoſt, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, ſanctifier, and comforter of mankinde, by whom we are ſealed unto the day of redemption, and by whoſe holy working wee are united unto Jeſus our bleſſed head, and are certified by thy Spirit, witneſſing to our ſpirits that wee are the children of God to our great comfort; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by thy aſſiſtance and grace, our weake pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are rightly and effectually offered up unto the Lord our God. Now to thee, Almighty God, three Perſons and glorious Trinity, but one true and everliving God, from whoſe mercifull hands we daily receive all the good we doe injoy in this preſent world, with further and full aſſurance of far greater happineſſe by thy infinite mercies in the life to come, be all praiſe and glory. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Tueſday.</hi> 2. <hi>A Prayer to the Trinity for grace and true faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Sweet Jeſus Chriſt, Son of God, who art the divine word, without whom nothing was made, and being made had been utterly loſt, hadſt thou not been our powerfull and mercifull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; thou art the way, the truth, and the life, and thou who haſt ſaid, that no man can come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father but by thee, who cameſt into the world, and didſt willingly lay down thine owne
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:121289:64"/> life only to ſave ſinners by thy grace, of whom I am chiefe; have mercy upon me miſerable ſinner, who can of my ſelfe neither will nor performe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good worke towards God as I ought to doe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but vouchſafe Lord, to indue mee with grace to ſerve and obey thee, to learne thy will and to doe it, and through faith to lay hold of thy mercies, that ſo thou my Saviour maieſt in thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe preſent me to thy heavenly Father, that hee may looke upon me poor ſinfull creature, through thee his deare Son, and for thy ſake to receive and accept me into his gracious favour, to pardon all my ſinnes, and ſave my ſoule, through thy perfect righteouſneſſe, and manifold ſufferings all perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for me. Now thou Lord haſt further ſaid that none can come unto thee except the Father draw him, therefore I moſt humbly pray thee, O God the Father, by that infinite love to wards mankind, which cauſed thee to ſend downe thy beloved Son out of thine owne boſome into this wicked world, that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life: I earneſtly pray thee, O God the Father, to draw me to thy Son Jeſus, that I may lay faſt hold by faith on him to be my Saviour, and to be his faithfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſervant, and to be made through him, and by thy mercie a happy member of him our bleſſed head, &amp; then I ſhall be ſure never to fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but by ſtedfaſt faith in him obtaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſalvation: And deare Lord Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121289:64"/> the giver of grace, by whom we are joyned to our Lord and head Chriſt, and ſanctified to a new and holy life: Lord cleanſe and frame my heart and ſoule by the holy working and aſſiſtance of thy Spirit and grace, unto the right, faithfull and conſtant ſervice of my Lord God my Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, with thee O Holy Ghoſt, ſo long as I live: Lord daily increaſe my faith and all ſaving graces in me for my ſalvation, and may by thee be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and lead into the waies of righteouſneſſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thou haſt brought me unto endleſſe happineſſe through Jeſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> 3. <hi>A prayer to God for charity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Mercifull Lord God, the giver of all graces, I humbly beſeech thee to frame my heart, will and affections, in all ready obedience to thy moſt holy will and Commandements in all things, eſpecially in the workes of mercy, and charity, they being a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice wherewith thou art well pleaſed, and wherein we may imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thee, and ſhall thereby gaine the honour to be made like unto thy ſelfe, and be knowne to bee one of thy diſciples if we love our brethren as our ſelves. O God, as thou haſt bleſſed mee of thy meer goodneſſe with an eſtate above ſome others, to give me the grace of compaſſion and charity, and inlarge my heart towards thy ſervice, to ſhew mercy unto them that want, as thou haſt been
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:121289:65"/> mercifull unto me, that I may willingly diſtribute, communicate to thoſe that are in need, and be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall of my earthly vaniſhing wealth to relieve thy childrens neceſſities, for thy ſake, that are dear unto thee, who wert free of thy very bloud, and ſparedſt not thine owne life to ranſome them and me from utter deſtruction: and ſo the loynes and bellies of the poore ſhall praiſe thee and bleſſe me in their comforts; and thou maieſt vouchſafe to receive and accept at my poore hands that ſmall mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of thankfulneſſe and obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee my God, from whoſe moſt gracious hand I have received many bountifull bleſſings and benefits throughout my whole life, which let mee never forget, gratefully to acknowledge while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have breath, and to praiſe thy holy Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll thy mercies now and for evermore. Amen d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re God. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thurſday.</hi> 4. <hi>A Prayer to the Trinity for ſpirituall graces.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt gracious Lord God, who didſt create man of the duſt of the earth, and knoweſt we are by nature the children of wrath, and wholy inclined to evill; for thou beſt underſtandeſt how unapt and unable I ſinfull creature am to doe any good before thee, much leſſe to call upon thy great and glorious Name as I ought to doe, yet thou in mercy haſt appointed prayer to bee the chiefe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:121289:65"/> meanes betwixt thy great Majeſty, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of us thy poore ſinfull ſervants, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to declare our wants, griefes, and deſires unto thee, who art our only hope and helpe: Therefore deare Lord, indue me thy unworthy ſervant with thy true ſpirit of grace and prayer, to teach mee how to pray as I ought, that thereby I may have power and ſtrength to withſtand all evill tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ſeek to draw me from thy ſervice, and by thy aſſiſtance that I may be able ſo to reſiſt the Divell that hee may flye from me in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all duties towards thee; and give mee grace with faith and fervency, humility and true devotion, to cry and pray daily and conſtantly unto thee for relief and diſtreſſe in all my troubles and wants, and faithfully to call and relye upon thee for all thy bleſſings and benefits both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, to be beſtowed on my ſoule and body as thou ſhalt thinke fitteſt; that ſo I may render all thanks and magnifie thy Name, as I am right bound to doe, for all thy mercies and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours vouchſafed unto me the moſt unworthieſt of all thy ſervants from time to time. And I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray thee, O Lord, to give me the bleſſed gift of true faith, without which it is impoſſible for me to pleaſe thee my God, but thereby I may lay hold, and rightly apply unto my owne ſoule all the infinite benefits purchaſed by the bitter death and paſſion, and precious bloud-ſhedding of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, that I may bring
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:121289:66"/> forth the fruits of righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe before thee as becommeth that Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; whereby I may glorifie thee, and have aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to my owne conſcience that I am thine by conſtantly obeying thy will: And alſo Lord grant me hearty and unfaigned repentance and true ſorrow for all my ſinnes originall and actuall, in omitting the good I ought to do, and committing the evill I ſhould not doe againſt thee, that ſo I may obtaine pardon of all my treſpaſſes, through the merits of Jeſus Chriſt the righteous; and let thy bleſſed Spirit produce in me amendment of my life all my time to come, and aſſiſt mee with thy grace to ſhun and hate all approaches of evil, and Lord ſhew me the way of life, and turne my ſteps into the right paths that I may wallke in true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all thy holy Commandements. Now deare God of thy mercy, give me the true feare of thy holy Name, with aſſurance of thy gracious favour towards me, and continuall joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the Holy Ghoſt, that I may ſtrive alwaies to keep faith and a good conſcience before thee towards all; and indue me with grace, will, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and ability, to do good workes to thy glory, and bring comfort and profit to my ſoule in praying, reading, and hearing of thy moſt holy word at all times, and moſt devout love towards thy Majeſty, with affection to all my brethren, thy children, ſervants and all the daies of my life to come, by thy gracious aſſiſtance dear God. Amen.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:121289:66"/>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Friday.</hi> 5. <hi>A Prayer for defence againſt our ſoules enemies, in all temptations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOod Lord God, who knoweſt the power and great malice of our ſpirituall enemies, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none can defend or deliver us, but only thou, O Lord, whoſe power and ſtrength is over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all; and if thou pleaſe to receive me into thy gracious protection, who can hurt or plucke mee out of thy mercifull hands? Therefore I moſt humbly beſeech thee, O God, to defend me both in ſoule and body, in life and death, from all the temptations of my owne wretched nature within me, the wicked inticements of this vaine world round about me, with the malicious ſnares, and evill temptations of the Divell that are ever at my backe ready to intrap me, and draw my ſoul from thee my God and all goodneſſe, and to lead mee captive into all wickedneſſe, ſinne and evill, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate me from thee, all which like roaring Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeeke to devoure and deſtroy me everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But I moſt humbly pray unto thee, O Lord, who underſtandeſt my frailties, to preſerve and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from all their aſſaults, that they may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to prevaile over me to draw mee to ſin againſt thee my God, in any thing; neither ſuffer them to prevent, hinder, diſturbe or carry away my minde, or poſſeſſe my vaine heart with wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thoughts in the performance of any holy
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121289:67"/> duty or ſervice towards thy Majeſty; nor give them power to bring thoſe harmes, dangers or miſchiefes upon me either in ſoule or body which they deſire to doe. But let thy bleſſed Spirit ſo fully poſſeſſe me, and ever direct and aſſiſt mee in all my waies, to doe all things in a right, faithfull and acceptable manner before thee, that ſo at all times thy Spirit may witneſſe unto my ſpirit, that I am thy childe and ſervant; and of thy infinite mercy good Lord, vouchſafe thou alwaies to ſay unto my ſoule, eſpecially at my death, that thou art my God, my helpe and my ſalvation for ever: and by thy grace make my heart and ſoule to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and performe unto thee againe, that I am, and will bee thy true, faithfull and obedient ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant unto my laſt breath for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Saturday.</hi> 6. <hi>A Prayer for the true ſpirit of prayer, or a meditation. With a ſhort prayer to Jeſus our Saviour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEare Lord Holy Ghoſt, the helper of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, the preſerver and ſanctifier of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, I moſt humbly begge of thee to indue mee thy unworthy ſinfull ſervant, with thy true Spirit of grace and prayer, that I may rightly performe that duty towards thee of calling upon thy holy Name, and all other thy ſervice this day and at all times, with true and right devotion, that ſo my petitions being humbly preſented to thy great
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:121289:67"/> Majeſty lowly and meekly on the knees of my heart &amp; body; they may by thy mercifull aſſiſtance be lifted up and aſcend by the wings of faith and devotion unto the higheſt heavens, and there with confidence through my Saviour Jeſus, enter into the glorious eares and preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, where all mercy, grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe aboundeth. And then my ſupplications by thy favour, may be heard and accepted by thee my God, to prevaile and draw downe from thy mercifull hand all graces and bleſſings needfull, upon me thy poore creature both in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and ſo my unworthy ſacrifice of due praiſe and thanks that I offer unto thee may be received and accepted by thee, the Lord of all mercies, who doth often take in good part even the will for the deed, from thy fraile unworthy ſervants, and then my poore prayers ſhall bring much joy and comfort to me, and give glory to thee, my Lord. To whom (as of right belongs) be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and praiſe, for evermore. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Prayer to our bleſſed Saviour Jeſus, to be joyned to the former prayers.</head>
               <p>OH my deare Lord Jeſus, who didſt in thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy give thy innocent ſelfe to death for me a poore miſerable ſinner; Lord by thy grace make me to dedicate and offer up my ſelfe a living ſacrifice holy and acceptable unto thee, in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121289:68"/> daily ſtriving rightly and faithfully to ſerve and obey thee, that I may be wholly thine; and as thou haſt bought me with an unvaluable treaſure, even thine owne moſt pretious bloud, ſo ſweet Jeſus by thy holy Spirit unite me unſeparably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, my bleſſed head; and by thy aſſiſtance, that I may become a new creature, to hate and forſake all ſinnes, the vaine world, and my wicked ſelfe, and to be a true, carefull and conſtant ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant unto thee, to feare, love, honour, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy great and heavenly Name, who art the comfort and ſalvation of all that beleeve and truſt in thee, which Lord, let me unfaignedly doe, ſo long as I live.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>7. <hi>A Prayer to God, the Lord of all grace and mercie, containing ſeven humble petitions from a penitent ſinner:</hi> 1. <hi>For true faith.</hi> 2. <hi>For the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 3. <hi>For wiſdome.</hi> 4. <hi>For the feare of God.</hi> 5. <hi>For the love of God, and charity to our neighbours.</hi> 6. <hi>For repentance and true contrition of heart.</hi> 7. <hi>And for the grace and right ſpirit of prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Moſt bountifull Lord God, which giveth to all men liberally, and reproacheth none, if we aske in faith and waver not: and our bleſſed Saviour maketh us a large promiſe, ſaying, Aske and yee ſhall receive, ſeeke and you ſhall finde, knock and it ſhall bee opened unto you: And whatſoever you ſhall aske in my Name I will doe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121289:68"/> it, if you beleeve when you pray that you ſhall have it; for your heavenly Father if you aske in my name, will give the Holy Ghoſt to them that deſire him, and wiſdome to ſuch as aske it of God, and no good thing ſhall be wanting or with-held from them which feare the Lord, and walke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly in his ſight; ſo that we may well ſay with <hi>David,</hi> What is man that thou Lord art mindefull of him, and doſt viſit him with thy mercie, and crowneſt him with glory and honour? Moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Lord, theſe thy gracious promiſes and great goodneſſe towards mortall man, imboldneth mee, though a miſerable ſinner, and moſt unworthy of thy favours, now to offer up my ſupplications, and become an humble ſuter to thy Majeſty, to begge theſe great bleſſings at thy hands, who have juſtly deſerved grievous puniſhments from thee for my offences. But of thine owne meer mercie, deare God, who deſireſt not the death of a ſinner, but our repentance, converſion, and ſalvation; and for thy beſt beloved Sons ſake, in whom thou wilt deny us nothing, vouchſafe to incline thine ear to receive the humble petitions of me thy poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, who preſumeth to crave of thee, the Father of mercie, and the originall of all goodneſſe, from whom only commeth all good and perfect gifts, the ſeven ſpirituall and heavenly graces, wherewith to vanquiſh and baniſhus from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dangerous deadly ſinnes, which like Serpents ſlay and deſtroy ſo many ſoules, the leaſt ſinne
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:121289:69"/> we commit, being ſufficient to condemne us for ever. And now firſt, Good God, I humbly pray thee to beſtow upon mee the bleſſed and moſt needfull gift of true faith, without which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe thee, whereby I may ſtedfaſtly believe and truſt in thy goodneſſe, and lay faſt hold of all thy mercies and gracious promiſes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially upon the merits and ſufferings of thy dear Son, and my Saviour Jeſus for my redemption, and by thy grace rightly to apply them all to my ſalvation. And grant I may with thy aſſiſtance, bring forth ſuch fruits of true holineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, as may be moſt to thy glory and the peace and comfort of mine owne conſcience. And ſince I have begun to ſpeake to thee, O Lord, who am but duſt and aſhes, vouchſafe for Jeſus ſake, further to give me the moſt excellent gift of the Holy Ghoſt, to unite me inſeparably to my bleſſed head and Saviour Chriſt, and inſpire my ſoule with all ſaving graces, which may change all the evill in me to goodneſſe, darkneſſe to light, vices to vertues, and ſo wholy to cleanſe and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie my ſoule, body, and ſpirit, throughout, that I may be made perfect to every good worke, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and inabled to all obedience, godlineſſe and holineſſe of life before thee: and I alſo moſt humbly beſeech thee (O gracious God) to inrich me thy poore unworthy ſervant, with the unva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable treaſure of that heavenly wiſdome from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, which abideth about thy Throne, to direct
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:121289:69"/> and reforme my heart, and all my wayes aright in thy ſight, and to teach me thy holy will, and what is good and acceptable unto thee, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me with grace to doe it; and likewiſe Lord indue me with the true underſtanding of thy holy Lawes, that I may keepe them with my whole heart unto my end? Now, O my Lord, we are taught by <hi>Solomon,</hi> That the beginning of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is the feare of the Lord, and the knowledge of divine things, true underſtanding; therefore I doe moſt humbly intreat thee to knit my rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart to the holy feare of thy glorious Name, who only art to be feared, with the due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy righteous and terrible judgements, who canſt caſt both body and ſoul into hel; let this detaine me from falling into any evill or offence towards thee, and thereby alſo draw my ſinfull ſoule unto thy faithfull ſervice, with true contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all my paſt tranſgreſſions againſt thee. But eſpecially, good God, be pleaſed to indue my poore ſoule with the infinite gift and bleſſing of thy ſincere and perfect love of thy divine and heavenly Majeſty who art the true and only good. And, O God, grant that I may love and honour thee above and beyond all other things, with all my heart, all my ſoule, all my ſtrength, and with all my minde, ſetting my affections not on things that are below, but upon heavenly treaſures that are above, which are permanent and fade not, where my ſweet Saviour who dyed for mee on
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:121289:70"/> earth, now liveth and reigneth with thee in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for ever, and maketh interceſſion for mee there, that by thy aſſiſtance I may continually ſtudy and ſtrive, carefully and willingly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all duties towards thee in obeying thy Commandements with an upright and perfect heart before thee: and in all true charity being ready to doe good to others as thou commandeſt, and to love my neighbour as my ſelfe, even my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies for thy ſake. Moſt mercifull Lord, who knoweſt our fraile and wretched natures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt the converſion, &amp; not the confuſion of poor miſerable ſinners; thou ſweet Jeſus, cameſt to call, not the righteous, but ſinners to repentance, ſuch as I am, and to ſave that which was loſt; Oh let not my poore ſoule be loſt which coſt thee thy deare pretious bloud to ſave; but Lord, make mee by true faith lay hold of my redemption by thee, and all other thy workes of mercy; and though I have grievouſly offended in thy ſight, yet I beſeech thee, with-hold not thy favour from me thy poor ſinfull ſervant, but give me the grace of unfeigned ſorrow and repentance, with a true contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a broken heart for all my ſinnes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before thee, from the greateſt to the leaſt, wherein I have diſpleaſed thee, by thought, deſire, word or deed; hating, judging and condemning my ſelfe, for ſo offending thee my Lord God; and moſt earneſtly and humbly crave thy aſſiſtance, that I may now happily returne to thee with a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:121289:70"/> penitent and grieved heart, from whom I have ſo unhappily gone aſtray by a vaine corrupt mind and ſinfull ſoule, whereby I hope in thy great mercy to eſcape thy juſt wrath and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on due to my grievous offences; and may alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy gracious pardon for all my paſſed miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, with the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, which I moſt humbly crave, to amend my former faults, and to reforme my wayes the reſt of my life in all things according to thy bleſſed will. Now laſtly, O gracious Lord our righteouſneſſe, my ſure hope and heavenly Father, the fountaine of all goodneſſe, in whom is all mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, from thee only we receive all good gifts and graces; for thou heareſt the prayers, and to thee ſhall all fleſh come, who underſtandeſt our wants before we aske, and knoweſt our wretched natures and diſabilities to all goodneſſe, ſo that thy grace only muſt worke both the will and the deed of all that is good in us, and then of thine owne mercie accept the ſame through the merits and mediation of our Saviour Jeſus; ſo doubling thy favours towards us miſerable mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whoſe hearts are vile and falſe unto our ſelves and to thee alſo, and our thoughts are only evill continually: Therefore ſweet Jeſus the mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of mercie, vouchſafe to heare and helpe me, to call and draw me to thy ſelfe, and knit faſt my heart and ſoule unto thy true feare, devout love, and faithfull ſervice for ever; that ſo by thy ſelfe.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:121289:71"/> I may be inabled to run willingly and joyfully af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee, rightly and readily to performe all duties towards thee, and keep all thy Commandements conſtantly. Oh gracious Lord Holy Ghoſt, our bleſſed preſerver, comforter and ſanctifier, ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thou my hardened heart by thy grace, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten my dull and ſinfull ſoule, with all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers thereof, my underſtanding, memory, will and affection, with all ſaving graces; eſpecially as the chiefe means to gaine the reſt, vouchſafe to inſpire me with thy true ſpirit of grace and prayer rightly, humbly, fervently and faithfully to call daily on thy ſacred Name, and to worſhip thee in ſpirit and truth, even as thou requireſt to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that ſo by thy favour I may obtaine grace, power and ſtrength, to baniſh all wandring thoughts, and to vanquiſh and reſiſt all wicked hindrances caſt in by the divell or his agents, the world, and mine owne corruptions, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract and diſturbe my ſerious and devout atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of both ſoule and body in rightly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming this du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of prayer unto my Lord God, whereby I may be duly thankfull for all thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and mercies, already beſtowed on me and mine, and alſo to begge and obtaine the gracious countenance of all thy bleſſings ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, in whatſoever thou ſeeſt neceſſary for this preſent life, and that which is to come; but more eſpecially in giving me all ſaving graces, which may fit, prepare and further me here for thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:121289:71"/> Kingdome hereafter. To which my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer bring me by all the merits and ſufferings, and in the fulneſſe of thy mercies, I humbly beſeech thee, dear Jeſus. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>1. <hi>A ſorrowfull widowes prayer and petition unto the gracious protector and defender of widowes, and father of the fatherleſſe, which I compoſed ſhortly after the death of my dear huſband: And this may alſo ſerve any other upon the like occaſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALmighty God, and moſt gracious Lord, who art full of pity and goodneſſe, vouchſafe to heare, aſſiſt, and accept the humble devotion and ſupplication of me thy poore unworthy ſervant, in Jeſus Chriſt thy deare Son. Moſt mighty God, whoſe mercies are above all thy great works, and whoſe power and divine providence directeth and diſpoſeth all things to the beſt, for thoſe that doe love and depend upon thee. Thou haſt ever been pleaſed to ſhew mercie unto me thy poore handmaid, the moſt ſinfull of all thy ſervants, and haſt taken care of mee even from my mothers wombe, and vouchſafed me many benefits and bleſſings, and delivering mee out of very great croſſes and troubles, ſtill holding me up by thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hand from ſinking in the midſt of a ſea of ſorrowes; and like a moſt loving Father in my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers change of fortunes, haſt at all times provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for me and mine beyond our deſerts, or the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121289:72"/> worlds expectation, having in thy mercifull goodneſſe made me ſee with comfort all my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who were left deſtitute, now by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident proviſion and bleſſing, well ſetled for this life: All which by thy infinite favours, Lord make me ever thankfully to acknowledge, and grant that I and all mine, may ſerve, obey, praiſe, and glorifie thy great and bleſſed Name for ever, and ever. And as thou Lord, haſt ſtretched forth thy hand of bounty to ſupply all my worldly wants; ſo dear God, vouchſafe more eſpecially to extend thy gracious care over my ſoule, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and keep me from ſin, and indue me with all ſpirituall graces, ſo that my whole life and waies may ever be ſerviceable and acceptable to thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Majeſty. And now, O Lord, ſince it hath been thy will and pleaſure, to take away, and call to thy ſelfe my deare husband out of this tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life before me, and to bereave me of him who was my chiefe comfort in this world: I humbly beſeech thee, vouchſafe to take me into thy care, and give me grace to chooſe with <hi>Mary.</hi> that better part which may never be taken from mee, chiefly to ſerve and follow thee, that ſo I may turne this freedome from the bond of mariage on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the more to thy ſervice, and may become thy bond woman to ſerve and praiſe thee day and night like <hi>Hanna,</hi> ſo long as I live. And Lord, aſſiſt me with thy grace to obey thee in all things according to thy holy will, daily endeavouring to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121289:72"/> work out my ſalvation with feare and trembling, and continually ſtriving by a godly life and holy converſation, to make my calling and election ſure, which is one of the chiefeſt things needfull. Now deare God, make me to change and far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the fervent affection and carefull obſervance I have lived in towards my husband, into a holy feare, with devout and ſincere love of thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and ſervice, and due watchfulneſſe over my ſelfe, that I diſpleaſe not thee my God in any thing. And good God, by thy holy Spirit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my heart from the covetous ſeeking, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring and longing after the vanities, riches, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, preferments, or vaine pleaſures of this wicked deceitfull world, but inſtead of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer care and troubles in worldly buſineſſes, to pleaſe my husband, and for the good of my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, let me now bend my minde, and wholly ſet my heart and ſoule, to ſeeke after thee my good God, thy glory, thy Kingdome, and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, that ſo I may walke before thee all the reſt of my daies, with an upright, faithfull, and perfect heart in thy ſight. Laſtly, indue mee with true thankfulneſſe to thy gracious Majeſty for all thy manifold mercies vouchſafed unto me, Lord give me grace to uſe thoſe benefits thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweſt on me conſcionably as may be beſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto thee, and to imploy all I have to thy glory, the relievement of thy trueſt ſervants, and my owne comfort, eſpecially the good of my
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121289:73"/> ſoule in performing my duty towards thee, in ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to doe all the good I can, while I have time, for I deſire ſo to uſe and receive thy bleſſings here, as I may be alſo received into the place of eternall bleſſedneſſe hereafter, through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord. Finally, I moſt humbly beg that thou wilt vouchſafe to be a loving and gracious Father in thy care and comfort to me, and all mine, and let thy mercie, bleſſing and favour, reſt alwaies upon me, my children and grand-children kindred and friends, with all that thou haſt given thy poore ſervant, who doth in all humility commend and commit my ſelfe, my waies and workes, wholy to thy moſt bleſſed protection, and direction, to diſpoſe according to thy good pleaſure; that ſo I may doe all things to thy glory here, and by thy mercy be a happy partaker of thy eternall Kingdome of glory hereafter, through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>2. <hi>A Prayer to the God of mercy in time of affliction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious Lord God, the originall of all goodneſſe, and fountaine of mercie, thou haſt commanded thy poore ſervants to call upon thee in the day of trouble, that thou maieſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, and we may glorifie thee; great are the troubles of thy children, but thou delivereſt them out of all; thine eyes, O Lord, are upon thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:121289:73"/> and thine eares are open to their cry, for thou art near unto all that call upon thee in truth, and wilt ſave ſuch as bee afflicted in ſpirit: the ſorrows of my heart are increaſed, Lord draw me out of my troubles; the poore crieth, and the Lord heareth, he prepareth their hearts, and bendeth his eares to them, and delivereth them out of all their feare and care; for the hope afflicted ſhall not periſh before thee for ever. The Lord alſo will be a refuge in due time, even in affliction, and they that know thy Name will truſt in thee, for thou wilt not faile them that ſeek thee: have mercy upon me, O Lord, conſider my troubles which I ſuffer of them that hate me without cauſe, thou haſt been my defence, and haſt lifted me up from the gates of death: O Lord my God, in thee I put my truſt, ſave me from them that perſecute mee, and deliver me in thy good time. But, dear God, I moſt humbly confeſſe that my ſinnes are ſo many and grievous, as they have deſerved farre greater puniſhment then I am able to beare, and I can hope for no helpe or releaſe but from thine owne goodneſſe, who art my only hope and ſure refuge; for thou haſt mercy on whom thou wilt have mercy, and takeſt compaſſion on whom thou pleaſeſt; but I acknowledge that my ſufferings are not anſwerable to my ſinnes, for thou haſt corrected me with favour, not in rigor; therefore if thou ſhouldeſt kill me, yet will I truſt in thee, for thy mercy exceedeth all thy workes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121289:74"/> the ſhadow of thy wings will I reſt in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, till all my afflictions be overpaſſed. Yet Lord, if it ſeem good unto thee to continue theſe heavy troubles and viſitations, that now lye ſore on me, I humbly pray thee to ſanctifie all my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions unto me thy poore ſervant, which I hope are but fatherly chaſtiſements for the amendment of my faults, and not the fearfull judgements and enſignes of thy wrathfull diſpleaſure; from which Lord, for thy Sonnes ſake, preſerve me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y poore ſinfull creature, and lay no more upon me then thou wilt make me able to undergoe as I ought to doe, ſaying with <hi>Ely,</hi> It is the Lord, let him do what he pleaſeth: and make me to conſider like <hi>Job,</hi> that naked I came into the world, and naked I ſhall returne, the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken, praiſed be his name for ever; but thou Lord art my ſtength and my ſtay in all diſtractions. I further humbly beſeech thee, to give me grace and patience in all things, and at all times, to keep my ſelfe from any offence towards thee, by repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at thy juſt and favourable corrections for my tranſgreſſions; but grant that I may as Chriſt hath taught us, meekly and humbly, ſubmit my ſelfe to thy moſt righteous and bleſſed will, that ſo I may (by thy aſſiſtance) make the beſt and right uſe of whatſoever thou ſendeſt, that all may be to the beſt for thy honour, and turne to my good when thou art pleaſed to give a happy iſſue to this temptation, and in thy good time to eaſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121289:74"/> me out of theſe great adverſities to thy glory. But I know that the afflictions of this preſent world, are not worthy of the glory that ſhall bee revealed to us hereafter; yet I humbly deſire if it ſo pleaſe thee, that I may live the reſt of my daies in peace and quiet, conſtantly to attend thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and ſeek after my owne ſalvation. Lord be mercifull to this whole Kingdome, now in very great diſtraction, diſtreſſe and miſery, and alſo to all my fellow members in thy whole Church uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, whereſoever any of us are afflicted, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly or outwardly in body or minde, grant us either ſpeedy delivery, or elſe grace to performe thy good pleaſure, and with patience to wait thy leaſure, untill thou pleaſe to have mercy on us to our releaſe and comfort, and to thy owne praiſe and glory, who never faileſt thoſe that depend upon thee. Now I moſt humbly acknowledge with all poſſible praiſe and thanks, which I am bound ever to render unto thee, that thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly delivered me out of many ſorrowes, eares, troubles and vexations, both in body and minde, and alſo I bleſſe and magnifie thy holy Name for all thy great and manifold bleſſings which thou haſt beſtowed upon me, thy moſt unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; and I pray thee Lord, of thy infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not to let my ſinnes and wickedneſſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy mercies towards me, but pardon and caſt all my offences out of thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt my Saviour; and vouchſafe alwaies to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:121289:75"/> thy grace and favour to mee, and eſpecially in daily renewing all ſpirituall graces in me, that ſo, when, or how ſoone ſoever thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an end unto my daies here, I may then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the end of my faith and hope, even thy glory and my owne ſalvation, through thy beloved Son and my only Saviour Jeſus: for whoſe ſake, Lord heare me, and grant theſe my humble requeſts, with all things elſe which thou beſt knoweſt neceſſary either for my ſoule or body, for this life, or for the life to come, in which, deare God, make mee in thy manifold mercies partaker of eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for evermore. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <head>3. <hi>A Prayer for due preparation before the holy Communion of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Moſt gracious God, and our heavenly and mercifull Father in Jeſus Chriſt, who hateſt nothing thou haſt made, and deſireſt not the death of ſinners, but that we ſhould return to thee and live; thou abſolveſt all thoſe that truly repent and beleeve thy holy Goſpell, and didſt ſend thine only and beloved Son Jeſus into the world, to ſeek thoſe that were loſt, and to ſave ſinners by thy grace, of whom I am chiefe. O ſweet Jeſus, thou calleſt to thee, thoſe that are heavy laden and truly penitent, and weary of their burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſinnes, that thou maieſt mercifully eaſe and refreſh them; thou cameſt to call ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121289:75"/> and reſtore us that were loſt by ſinne, and to lay downe thine owne life to redeeme man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde from eternall death, and haſt left us a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous remembrance thereof in thy moſt holy Supper of that unſpeakable worke of our redemption, which we are exceedingly bound often to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, in acknowledgement of thy unexpreſſible mercy and favour towards us. But oh my Lord! I tremble and feare, knowing that I am a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and wicked ſinner, and my offences have made me abominable in thy ſight, being wholy corrupt both in ſoule and body, from the crowne of my head, to the ſoal of the foot, the worſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of all thy ſervants, and if thou ſhouldeſt ſtrictly marke what I have done amiſſe, or enter into judgement with me, how ſhould I dare to come into thy preſence having nothing to anſwer for my ſelfe, but (to cry with the Publican) I have grievouſly offended, Lord be mercifull to mee a ſinner? (and as another ſaith of himſelfe, how ſhould I preſume to appeare in the preſence of God, can the Lord be mercifull to ſo miſerable a ſinner as I am?) But Lord, I have learned, and do beleeve that there is mercy with thee, and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full redemption; therefore we are infinitly bound to love and feare thee; but I doe humbly confeſſe that I am altogether unworthy of my ſelfe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto thy bleſſed table, but thou Lord that giveſt both the will and the deed in all good workes, ſo Lord I pray thee to worke in me a due
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121289:76"/> preparation for thy acceptance, and then inable me to performe my duty herein in a right and faithfull manner, for there at thy heavenly ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, thou Lord, Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, art preſent in thy great Majeſty beholding our unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect devotions, wants in preparation, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold infirmities; but thou Lord by thy powerfull grace cleanſeſt us from ſin, and changeſt us into new creatures, and in thy higheſt bounty giving thy ſelfe really unto us to be received ſpiritually by faith, and by the working of the Holy Ghoſt; thou art the heavenly food of our ſoules unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, powring ſuch great and wonderfull treaſure into poore earthen veſſels, as we are, and and ſo making us partakers of all the benefits of thy unſpeakable merits, and bitter paſſions and ſufferings. Oh Lord, who inviteſt me thither, continue thy mercy to perfect the good worke thou haſt begun for my ſalvation, and heale thou my corrupt ſoule, converting my ſtraying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull heart, and knit it unto thee my God, and by thy grace prepare and fit me, rightly, reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, faithfully and worthily, to receive that high and divine myſtery, in all humility, contrition, true faith and charity, with ſuch devotion as I ought to doe. Now deare Lord, give me grace rightly to underſtand, and duly to conſider and ponder of thy greatneſſe to feare thee, of thy goodneſſe to love thee, of thy power and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold mercies towards me, ever to beleeve and truſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:121289:76"/> in thee: And alſo to looke into my owne rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſobedience, and ſhamefull ingratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, and my moſt miſerable eſtate, who am in danger of everlaſting damnation by my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable tranſgreſſions committed againſt thee; Lord touch my hardened heart with the oyle of thy grace, that it may be faſtened to receive a ſound and ſenſible feeling and ſight of all my grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious ſinnes paſt, both in committing the evill I was forbidden, and omitting the good I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, with a true ſenſe of thy juſt wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me for the ſame, which may worke in mee by thy aſſiſtance, ſuch unfaigned ſorrow and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitencie, even to breake my ſtony heart with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of my ſelf and all ſinne for ſo offending thee, with ſuch true contrition and repentance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation, as I may obtaine thy mercifull par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſweet Jeſus, that by thy wounds I may bee healed, and all my offences hidden, never to bee imputed unto me hereafter; and by thy grace hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily purpoſing, conſtantly to endeavour the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of all my miſdeeds for the time to come, and by thy helpe to lead a holy and a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified life ſo long as I live. Now I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, oh dear Lord, to indue me alſo with the bleſſed gift of true faith, which is the only hand to lay hold of thee, and all thy mercies whereby thou maieſt dwell in me, and I in thee for ever; I beleeve, Lord helpe my unbeleefe, and ſtrengthen and increaſe in me a right hope,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:121289:77"/> and lively faith, ſtedfaſtly to beleeve, and rightly to apply to my owne ſoule all thy gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, benefits, merits and ſufferings for me to my ſalvation. Oh my God Holy Ghoſt, vouchſafe to inſpire my heart with true and perfect charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all my brethren and neighbours, yea even to my very enemies for thy ſake, that I may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, as thou doſt pardon me. And thou Lord, preſerver of mankinde, by thy gracious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration in this bleſſed Sacrament, joyne me an unworthy member unſeparably unto thy bleſſed head Chriſt Jeſus, eſpecially at this time, grant that through thy holy working and aſſiſtance, I may bee a happy partaker not only of the outward ſignes, but alſo of the inward and ineſtimable gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beſtowed upon our ſoules by the reall body broken, and pretious bloud ſhed of our deare Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus, which was crucified for us, to be the pretious food of our ſoules, all which Lord rightly apply unto my ſoule, with all other benefits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignified and aſſured unto us, and through his righteouſneſſe and merits, that I may be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and accepted by God our heavenly Father, to my eternall comfort and happineſſe; that ſo I may devoutly and everlaſtingly love and honour, magnifie, and admire the infinite mercy, love and favour of God, the Father, our deare Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and of the Holy Ghoſt, to whom be all praiſe and glory for ever. Now Almighty God, grant me thy poore ſervant grace to live in true faith,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:121289:77"/> ready obedience, and continuall thankfullneſſe all the reſt of my daies here, that I may live hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in heaven with thee, in joy and bliſſe for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>4. <hi>An humble thanksgiving after the receiving of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Yeeld unto thee my mercifull Lord God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Holy Ghoſt, all humble and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible praiſe and thanks, for all thy great benefits and loving favours vouchſafed unto me, thy poor ſinfull creature both ſpirituall and temporall all my life hitherto; and deare Lord, the fountaine of all mercie, thou haſt been exceeding good and gracious towards mee, which I humbly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, eſpecially in vouchſafing ſo great and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold bleſſings to me thy moſt unworthy ſervant in this thy preſent favour, which thou haſt been pleaſed to make me partaker of amongſt thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Now, deare Lord, make me ever truly thankfull with all my heart and ſoule unto thee for all thy mercies beſtowed on mee, who with ſhame and ſorrow doe confeſſe, I have deſerved no good, but all evill at thy hands by my mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold offences committed againſt thee; therefore in all humility I doe beſeech thee, to caſt all my ſinnes and wickedneſſe out of thy ſight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and let them be no hindrance to thy grace and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me; but Lord ſtill continue and increaſe thy
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:121289:78"/> fatherly care and loving kindneſſe both to my ſoule and body to prevent and preſerve me from falling into any ſin or evill; and vouchſafe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow all ſpirituall graces on mee, that may inable me to live a more holy and acceptable life before thee ever hereafter; and ſeale thou my pardon for all my ſinnes paſt, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, who dyed for me, and with his owne unvaluable bloud paid my ranſome, and fully ſatisfied thy great and juſt wrath againſt me. But gracious God, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable is thy goodneſſe and infinite favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mankinde, that inſtead of powring down puniſhments upon us for our great offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, thou didſt thy ſelfe in thy tender love ordaine the meanes for our redemption, juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and eternall ſalvation, through Chriſt thine owne deare Son: praiſed be thy glorious Name for ever, and chiefly at this time I magnifie thee ſweet Jeſus (the mirrour of mercy) who before thou hadſt finiſhed the great worke of our redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, didſt alſo inſtitute the bleſſed Sacrament of thy holy Supper that ineſtimable benefit, to all thy ſervants which rightly receive the ſame, it being a pledge of thy love, a remembrance of thy mercy, a renuing of grace in us, a teſtimony of thy favours, a confirmation of our faith, a uniting of us (by thy Holy Ghoſt) to our bleſſed Lord and head Chriſt Jeſus, and all our fellow members in perfect charity one towards another, with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereby of the pardon of all our ſinnes, and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:121289:78"/> eternall ſalvation to our ſoules: the great benefit thereof is beyond my expreſſion, of which this day thou haſt graciouſly vouchſafed to make mee (though unworthy of my ſelfe) yet by thy favour a happy partaker. Now deare Lord, enlarge thy goodneſſe further toward me thy poor ſervant, to give me daily the ſpirituall gifts of ſound repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, encreaſe of true faith to beleeve all thy gracious promiſes, with grace rightly to apply them to my owne ſoule, and all the infinite bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which thou my deare Saviour haſt purchaſed for me, that ſo this Sacrament may worke thoſe good effects in me which thou haſt therein offered unto us, and that I may by thy aſſiſtance, bring forth the fruits of righteouſneſſe, obedience, and true holineſſe of life, all the reſt of my daies, and to make ſuch thankfull and conſtant acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and right uſe of all thy mercies, as I may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy bleſſed Name; reforme my waies, and frame my heart in all things to be faithfully and conſtantly thine, and then I know that thou wilt ever be my gracious God, to thy honour and my endleſſe felicity, through my Lord Jeſus Chriſt the righteous. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>1. <hi>A meditation concerning death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord God Holy Ghoſt, our ſanctifier, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver and comforter, who beſt knowes my corrupt nature, that cannot of my ſelfe performe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:121289:79"/> any true ſervice towards God, being inclined to all evill, and unapt to any goodneſſe, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeecb thee, that underſtandeſt my manifold infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, be pleaſed to indue me with all ſaving graces in the performance of all holy duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. And I humbly pray thee ſweet Jeſus to call and draw me daily unto thee; and vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe Lord by thy holy Spirit to poſſeſſe my heart and ſoule, to make mee wholly and conſtantly thine, truly to feare and love thee, to ſerve and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey thee in all things, that ſo thou in thy infinite mercy maieſt never leave me, but be my gracious Lord, and mercifull God for ever. And I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray thee Lord Holy Ghoſt, to ſanctifie and aſſiſt me thy poore ſinfull ſervant, with all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces for my ſalvation in Chriſt, both living and dying, that I may ſtrive to become what I ought to be, and to doe thy holy will in all things while I live. Now O good God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, thou knoweſt that many and evill have been my daies in this world, and by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence I have attained to a great age, but have not performed the ends for which I came into the world, who being made only to ſerve God in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of our lives to his glory, and our ſalvation, which is the chief thing needfull; but alas, for the moſt part it is the leaſt regarded or thought upon, where I confeſſe (with ſorrow) that I have been too much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectfull, having ſometimes been drawne by the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121289:79"/> cares and troubles of this life, which neceſſity brought upon me, to ſet my heart ever carefully upon earthly things, and likewiſe, too often have I been carried away with the vanity of my owne heart in following after the preferments, or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of my owne heart, in following after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, or delighting in the pleaſures of this vile world, all which periſh in the uſing, by which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions and deceits, that old ſubtill ſerpent Sathan (that firſt wrought our ruine) he now ſteals away our time and hearts, only to make us loſe our ſouls alſo. But deare Lord, though I have too long gone aſtray, yet while I am going towards my God, Lord let it be thy worke of grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to make me ſee and underſtand when I am out of the right way before I goe too far to fall into irrecoverable danger, from which I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. Oh ſhew me the paths of life and lead mee into the true way to heaven that I may firſt turne to thee in true faith with a contrite ſpirit, and a broken heart for my loſt time paſt which I have miſpent, that ſo I may obtaine pardon for all my ſinnes formerly committed before thee, and then I know thou wilt receive me as one of thine, and in mercie bring me to thy ſalvation. Now Lord, although our times are only knowne to thee, yet I cannot have long to live, for the life of man is but ſhort, and old age laden with infirmities and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a ſure meſſenger and forerunner of death, and then draweth near the firſt appearance when
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121289:80"/> my breath ceaſeth, of my poore ſoule before the tribunall ſeat, of thy great Majeſty, O God, and before all thy holy Angels there to bee called to give an account of all my life and time miſpent: Alas, how can I anſwer one thing of a thouſand; now what ſhould I doe, if I had not there in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven an All-ſufficient Saviour, who is alſo my bleſſed advocate to mediate for me, in whom is all my truſt, comfort and confidence; therefore gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord Jeſus helpe me now while I am here, and aſſiſt me to make my peace (as thou doſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe) while I am in the way before the grim and cruell Sergeants of ſickneſſe and death lay hold upon me to prevent me of the freedome, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of my ſenſes, and ſpirit, being aided with thy power, ſtrength and grace by unfaigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and true faith to obtaine through Chriſt my releaſe, and pardon of thoſe grievous debts and treſpaſſes that I ſtand guilty of before God, which I am no waies able to ſatisfie, but only by thee my Saviour Jeſus, or elſe I ſhall be throwne into that dreadfull dungeon, from whence there is no eſcaping: Therefore now I doe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg and pray thee, that I may finde ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in thy ſight, knowing my owne diſabilities, that thou Lord wouldeſt knit and prepare my heart and ſoule, for thine owne mercifull acceptance, before thou call and ceiſe upon me by death, to take me out of this life, and make me continually mindfull of my laſt end while I live in health, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:121289:80"/> of that ſtrict reckoning which then I muſt make unto thee, the great God of heaven and earth, who ſeeth and knoweth all things of all my life paſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to my very words. And let me ſtill remember that thou Lord ſearcheſt the hearts and trieſt the reines, and beholdeſt all our waies, and will bring each worke to judgement, with every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thing, whether it be good or evill: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I moſt humbly beſeech thee, while I am in this world, give me the grace of daily and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned repentance for all my ſinnes paſt, with care to amend all my former faults in the reſt of my life, and narrowly to examine my own heart, ſoule and conſcience of all the evills I have done before thee, hating and ſeverely judging and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning my ſelfe for them, that ſo I may eſcape thy great wrath, and not be judged and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thee, O Lord, in thy heavy diſpleaſure, which I am not able to beare; for who can ſtand in the ſight of thy great Majeſty when thou art angry? Therefore gracious God, let me here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thy mercifull pardon for all my offences paſt, with grace to reforme my former miſdeeds, and by thy bleſſed aſſiſtance become a new creature all my daies, that ſo I may gaine a bleſſed end, through my Saviour to dye in him, and make my peace with God here, before I goe hence and be no more: To which purpoſe I humbly pray thee while I live, to make me a true and faithfull mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thy right Church &amp; Kingdom of grace here
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:121289:81"/> to profeſſe and practice true Religion, and all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of life to my laſt end; but chiefly, Lord, give me a bleſſed part in the firſt reſurrection, that I may not lye dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, but may by thy holy Spirit be daily raiſed from the grave of ſinne, and enabled to live the life of grace, that ſo the ſecond death may have no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to hurt me; and at the laſt when it ſhall pleaſe thee to appoint a ſtop to my daies, and to ſet a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod unto my time, grant that my death be neither ſuddaine, nor unexpected, neither my paines vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, whereby I ſhould be unable, faithfully, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and conſtantly to cry unto thee my God, and call upon thy holy Name, for reliefe and comfort in that great and dreadfull day and time of death and danger, when my ſoules enemies will ſeek my utter deſtruction; then Lord, depart not from me, but pray that my faith in thee faile not, and ſtrengthen my weakneſſe by thy power, and ſupply my ſoule with all ſaving graces, and defend me from the malice and ſubtill temptation of my ſpirituall adverſaries, that they may never be able to prevaile againſt me in any thing. But I humbly pray thee ſweet Saviour, to grant that in the day of thy great viſitation, my poore name through thy unſpeakable goodneſſe, may be then found written in thy bleſſed booke of life, ſo that my ſinnes, nor my ſoules enemies, may not be able to blot it out; but that by thy infinite mercy and favour, ſweet Jeſus, unto me, I may then be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:121289:81"/> in thee worthy to eſcape thy juſt wrath, and by thy power and clemency, who didſt vouchſafe to be borne of a woman, and ſhalt bee judge of the whole world, grant through thy mercies, merits, and manifold ſufferings, that I poore ſinfull creature, may be made able to ſtand before thee the bleſſed Son of God and man in that great and dreadfull day of judgement, when all our ſecret wickedneſſes ſhall be made manifeſt, and thou Lord, to whom all judgement is given by the Father, art to give our finall ſentence: Oh then dear Jeſus, in whom only I truſt, receive me into thy gracious favour as one of thine, that my ſinnes may be covered with thy righteouſneſſe, that ſo I may be preſerved from thy wrath, and that wofull doom, Go ye curſed into hell fire, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the Divell and his Angells; but Lord, in the fulneſſe of thy mercy, make me one of that happy choſen number, to whom that joyfull call ſhall belong, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and enter into that Kingdome, which he hath prepared for you before the beginning of the world; and alſo thou our Saviour haſt purchaſed for us; then Lord in thy infinite love grant me a part in that everlaſting happineſſe, to live with thee, and glorifie thee there, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:121289:82"/>
               <head>2. <hi>A Prayer to live bleſſedly, and dye happily.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH gracious Lord God, who didſt create all things by thy omnipotent power, and laſtly made mankinde! thou beſt knoweſt the frailties and corruption of our wretched nature which we inherit from our firſt parents, whoſe ſubſtance was but earth, and we are of our ſelves inclined onely to earthly and evill things, and ſuch is the condition of mortall man, that all that are borne muſt dye, and returne to duſt from whence they came, but the ſpirit returnes to thee, O God, that gave it, to receive either joy or bliſſe with thee for ever, or elſe eternall baniſhment from thee, who art the only good; therefore I doe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee, deare Lord, to looke mercifully upon me, to helpe my manifold infirmities, and daily to prevent and keep me from falling into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne or evill to offend thee. But eſpecially in the time of my death, dear Lord, be mercifull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me a moſt miſerable ſinner, to forgive all my ſinnes and offences paſt, that I have committed againſt thee my God, my brethren, or my owne ſoule; and grant through the merits, and many ſufferings of thy beloved Son, and my only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus, that they may never bee imputed unto me thy poor ſervant, but vouchſafe good God, in thy manifold mercies to indue mee thy moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſuppliant, with all ſaving graces leading
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:121289:82"/> to my ſalvation both in life and death; for we daily ſee by example how ſuddainly death may ſurpriſe us when we leaſt expect it; therefore while this life is in being, and I am going on in the way of all fleſh, which can be of no long continuance; Lord teach and aſſiſt mee to make my peace for my offences with thee my God while I am here, who elſe wilt take an account of me in a dreadfull place, and art able if thy wrath be not pacified, to caſt me into hell fire, from which there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; therefore have mercy on me, ſweet Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that I may by thy helpe, grace and aſſiſtance, rightly fit and prepare my ſelf for thy acceptance before ſickneſſe lay hold on me; for when death ſeiſeth it will carry mee immediately before the judgement ſeat of thy great Majeſty: Oh there let me finde thee, deare Jeſus, to be my gracious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Advocate, and ſo I ſhall obtaine mercy and favour, and by thy ſufferings, my offences pardoned, and Gods ſevere juſtice ſatisfied. And thus in thee and through thee only, my bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer Ieſus Chriſt, I ſhall be received to grace and mercy, and made partaker of eternall life, and remaine with Almighty God, in whoſe preſence is the fulneſſe of joy, and at his right hand there are pleaſures for evermore, which Lord make me partaker of, there to glorifie the Name of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:121289:83"/>
               <head>3. <hi>A Prayer to be prepared for a happy death, and to gaine a joyfull reſurrection.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt glorious Lord God, who didſt make all things, thou well underſtandeſt that we poor creatures (how highly ſoever we are conceited of our ſelves) are but duſt and aſhes, and muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to earth from whence we came; our lives and times are in thy hand and power, and what thou haſt appointed we cannot change, and all things to our ſelves are moſt uncertaine; for when thou with juſt rebuke doſt chaſtiſe man for iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, thou makeſt his ſtrength and beauty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume away like a flower of the field that withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and falleth: for when thou calleſt, man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not retaine the ſpirit, nor adde one houre to his time, but it returnes to thee that gave it, and hee goeth downe to the grave, from which he ſhall not returne againe till this world is at an end: Therefore, deare Lord, I now moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, for thy beloved ſonnes ſake, who hath ſatisfied thy juſt wrath by his infinite and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſufferings, and redeemed me from ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than by his death, Lord forgive and pardon me all my ſinnes and offences paſt, either in ſoule or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that I have committed againſt thee ever ſince I came into this miſerable world, which I confeſſe are innumerable, more then the haires of my head, or the ſand upon the Sea ſhoare, but vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:121289:83"/> O mercifull God, to be reconciled unto mee a wicked ſinner, in thy deare and righteous Son Chriſt Ieſus my only Saviour, who hath paid my ranſome with his owne pretious bloud, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, oh God of mercie, blot my debt to thee by ſinne, out of thy ſight; and alſo he did fulfill all righteouſneſſe for me, who is now my bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator in heaven, to impute all this unto mee: Therefore, deare Lord Holy Ghoſt, by thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and holy Spirit, joyne and unite me unto my Lord and head Chriſt, never to be ſeparated from him while I live here, and when I goe from hence carry me to be where he is, and give mee grace and faith in and through him, to make my peace while I am in the way and paſſage of this life, and while I have breath to call upon thee, before I am laid into the darke dungeon of the earth, when the wormes ſhall eat my corrupt fleſh; yet I truſt and doe believe through him, that hath overcome death, the grave, and hell for me, that at the bleſſed reſurrection of thy children and ſervants, that my corruption ſhall put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and I ſhall ſee my bleſſed Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour with theſe my eyes, who did redeeme me, and ſhall be my mercifull judge to ſave me; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have ſure confidence in his favour, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wings of his mercie ſhall I reſt in ſafety. Now I humbly pray thee, O God the Holy Ghoſt, to ſanctifie, fit, prepare, and aſſiſt my heart and ſoule with thy Spirit, to fill me with all ſaving
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:121289:84"/> graces for my ſalvation; while I live, to enable me to call, pray and ſtrive to pleaſe thee here in all things; but eſpecially Lord at my death ſtand by me and pray for me that my faith faile not: fit and prepare me for thy gracious acceptance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou call and ſeiſe upon me to take me out of this preſent life; and make me alwaies mindefull both in health and ſickneſſe of my owne laſt end, and then of my appearance before thee, to make anſwer before the great God of Heaven &amp; Earth (from whom nothing can bee hid) of all my life and deeds paſt, even to my very words; for thou art only and above all to be feared, who canſt both ſave and kill, and caſt both ſoule and body into utter perdition in hell: Therefore Lord, vouchſafe to aſſiſt me with thy grace to worke in me all things which may make me acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee before the day of my departure, that when it doth approach it may not bee fearfull and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, but happy and comfortable unto me in Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, that through him, my laſt day may be my beſt, and moſt welcome to my ſoule; that I may then call and pray, and ſay with confidence, Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly, for into thy hands I moſt humbly commend my ſpirit, for thou haſt redeemed me, O Lord God of truth; and vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe thou even to my laſt breath, alwaies to ſay unto my ſoule, thou art my God, and my ſalvation for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:121289:84"/>
               <head>4. <hi>A Prayer in ſickneſſe, with expectation of death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH heavenly Father, who haſt been my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God before I had being, and my mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull guide from my youth, be pleaſed eſpecially now at the houre and point of my death which I ſhall ſhortly expect, to be mercifull, O God, unto me a miſerable ſinner, to pardon for Jeſus ſake all my ſinnes and iniquities that I have committed formerly; and vouchſafe to heale and ſave my wretched ſoule that hath infinitly offended thee, and ſtrengthen my weakneſſe with thy power, and ſupply all graces wanting in me by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and defend me from all my ſpirituall adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who will endeavour my deſtruction if they can, but let them not prevaile againſt me; and Lord Jeſus, be not farre from me, neither forſake me in a time when ſo much trouble and danger is about me; but in the multitude of thy mercy, Lord pray for mee that my faith faile not, and ſtretch forth thy hand to ſave me, as thou didſt to <hi>Peter,</hi> leſt I periſh. Now, O God, give me ſuch ſound and unfaigned repentance, as may obtaine from thee remiſſion of all my ſinnes, with true faith to lay hold of all thy gracious promiſes, and a right and a ſtedfaſt hope in all thy mercies; but chiefly indue me with devout and perfect love toward thy Majeſty, which may make me faithfully and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:121289:85"/> conſtantly thine to ſerve and obey thy holy will in all things, with Chriſtian charity towards all my brethren: but Lord, if it be thy will give mee knowledge of my death when it is neare, that I may faithfully pray unto thee, and call on thy moſt bleſſed Name with my laſt breath, and may joyfully and willingly yeeld up and commend my ſpirit backe to thee my Lord, who gave it unto me: And deare Lord, prevent and remove all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hindrances in my way to heavenly happineſſe, that through Chriſt Jeſus my Saviour, I may bee received amongſt thy children and ſervants, and admitted into the preſence of thy Majeſty, O heavenly Father, there to enjoy eternall felicity with thee in heaven when this life is ended by death. But if thou ſhouldeſt pleaſe at this time to continue and prolong my daies upon earth; Lord, ſo long as I live, teach me by thy grace ſo to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my daies that I may apply my heart to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and godlineſſe and holineſſe of life, ſeeking to redeem my loſt time paſt which I have miſpent, by daily repentance and amendment of life, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to make my calling and election ſure, by a holy and good converſation the reſt of my time to come, that by thy mercy, and merits of my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus I may be freed of my treſpaſſes, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy account with thee before I dye, and may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape thy juſt and great wrath which is due for my manifold tranſgreſſions. Now Lord Jeſus, I willingly ſubmit my ſelfe to thy good pleaſure to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:121289:85"/> diſpoſe of me as thou ſeeſt beſt: but I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg of thee, when my laſt and appointed hour is come, that I ſhall enter into my long ſleep of death, and goe to lye downe in the duſt; deare Lord, give me a happy departure out of this life, that I may dye in thee, O Lord, to reſt in peace and ſafety, and may be raiſed up by thee at the laſt day to grace and glory, that thou receiving mee into thy mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and favour, I may live and remain with thee in eternall happineſſe to glorifie thy bleſſed Name, and ſing hallelujah amongſt thy Saints for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <head>5. <hi>A Prayer unto the Lord of mercy in the time of ſickneſſe to be fitted for death, and aſſiſted in that dreadfull houre againſt all temptations, to gaine a bleſſed paſſage out of this world at Gods appointed time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Great and mercifull God, who reigneſt and diſpoſeſt of all things in heaven, and in the whole world as it pleaſeth thee, and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt all the paſſage here below on earth, be it never ſo ſecret, and by thy mercie and power doſt work all things to the beſt for thoſe that love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon thee; for thou art full of goodneſſe, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long-ſuffering towards us poore weak and fraile creatures, and thy abounding mercy, doth exceed all other thy great workes in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſinners; but beyond all other thy favours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:121289:86"/> us, thy infinite love to mankinde did moſt appeare in ſending thine owne dear Son into the world to ſave ſinners by thy grace, that all that beleeve in him might be ſaved; without which thy mercie, what hope, comfort, or helpe were there left unto us miſerable ſinfull creatures; for the juſt man falleth ſeven times a day, but the wicked much more, and if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appear, ſuch as I am? Therefore I come and cry and pray unto thee, who only canſt relieve me, in all humility, contrition and confeſſion of my manifold tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and in the bleſſed Name of thy dear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, my only Saviour, I do beg and beſeech thee, O Father, full of compaſſion, not to enter into judgement with me, nor to remember what I have done amiſſe; but to conſider what thy Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for mee, and looking on mee through him, have mercy and pity upon me a moſt grievous ſinner; I know too well, how juſtly thou maieſt condemne me; but Lord, to ſave a poore ſinner by thy grace is farre greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory unto thee: And gracious God, who of thine owne meer mercy didſt give us thy moſt deare Son to be our reconciliation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were thine enemies, much more being reconciled, and having performed all things for us, thou canſt deny us no good thing that wee aske in his beloved Name: Therefore, O God, for Chriſt innocent ſake, vouchſafe to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:121289:86"/> unto me, thy moſt unworthy ſinfull ſervant, and caſt all my offences into his grave, where my Saviour paid the laſt part of my ranſome; and by his power riſing againe the third day from death, he conquered and overcame all my ſoules ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſin, death, hell and Sathan; and deare Lord, with his pretious bloudſhed upon the croſſe, waſh my ſoule cleane before it appeare in thy preſence, and take away all my iniquities out of thy ſight, never to come in remembrance before thee, ſo that Chriſt may be unto me both in life and death an advantage. And now moſt deare God, my life and time here is only in thy hand and pleaſure, and thou haſt caſt me upon the bed of ſickneſſe, from which I know not whether I ſhall recover, or riſe any more while I live in this world; therefore I moſt humbly pray thee, ſweet Jeſus, never to leave or forſake me, but ſtand thou alwaies in mercy by me, and let thy right hand uphold and ſuſtaine me to preſerve me from all my ſpirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that wait to deſtroy my ſoule: But thou my Lord, art ſufficient for me, O Lord, vouchſafe me thy grace to direct my heart and words to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, and by thy ready helpe to aſſiſt me in all things, and at all times, that in thy mercie at the laſt thou maieſt finiſh all thy favour in mee, which is the accompliſhment of my faith and hope in thee: And Lord grant that I may willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and readily come unto thee when thou calleſt; and vouchſafe, O bleſſed Spirit Holy Ghoſt, to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:121289:87"/> fit and prepare me by unfeigned repentance to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine remiſſion of all my ſinnes that I have done before thee, with true faith to lay hold of all the mercies of my God in Chriſt, and with ſtedfaſt hope to reſt on all thy gracious promiſes, O Lord, who never faileſt thoſe that truſt in thee. Now Lord, give me ſtrength and patience to wait thy good leaſure and pleaſure, untill thou have pity and compaſſion on me, either to recover and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore my health here (if it be thy will) that I may live and glorifie thee longer in this life, or elſe that thou wilt pleaſe to receive and prepare me for thy ſelfe, and give me all ſaving graces for thine own mercifull acceptance, when thou pleaſeſt to call and take me to thee out of this wretched world, that ſo my faith and ſure truſt in thee may never faile unto my laſt breath. Now laſtly, Lord grant, that as the outward man (the body) decayeth and groweth weaker, ſo the inward part (the ſoule) may by thy gracious aſſiſtance grow together in faith and confidence towards thee, with full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy Spirit within me of thy favour to me for my eternall ſalvation: Then come Lord Ieſus when thou pleaſeſt, for into thy hands I humbly commend my ſpirit, that when this life ſhall leave me, thy grace and mercy may receive mee into that endleſſe happineſſe in heaven, which my Lord and only Saviour hath purchaſed for me, that I may praiſe God everlaſtingly. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:121289:87"/>
               <head>6. <hi>My Prayer of thanksgiving after my long and great fit of ſickneſſe, which begun on Twelfth day at night and held me till Whitſontide: This may ſerve upon any other occaſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOſt gracious Lord God, I bleſſe and praiſe thy great and holy Name, for all thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and benefits both ſpirituall and temporall vouchſafed to my ſoule and body; but eſpecially. I magnifie thy glorious Majeſty for all thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces thou haſt beſtowed upon my ſoule before I was borne and hitherto, which I beſeech thee of thy mercie daily to continue and increaſe towards me: Now deare Lord, make me thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervant ever truly thankfull to thee for all thy goodneſſe extended towards me, and grant me grace to make ſuch right uſe of all thy mercies as may be moſt to thy glory, and my ſalvation in Chriſt. But now, O Lord, that art my God, I muſt at this time render thee humble thanks in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and not forget to acknowledge thy benefits, and to praiſe thy holy Name for all thy mercies ſhewed unto me; for in my late and long ſicknes thou haſt heard my groanes, and taken pity on me, and releaſed me from all my paine and griefs, for thou doſt viſit my tranſgreſſions with favour (not in wrath) and haſt alwaies been my ſtay and comfort from my youth, and thou art my delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ready helpe in all my adverſities, thou
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:121289:88"/> didſt bring me downe for my ſinnes almoſt to the grave, and haſt in mercy lifted me up again from the gates of death, and reſtored me to health, who healeſt all my infirmities, pardoneſt all my iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and giveſt me preſent ſupply in all my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, bleſſed be thy glorious Name for ever. Now O God, as thou art pleaſed to prolong my dayes on earth, ſo eſpecially I humbly pray thee daily to increaſe all ſaving graces in mee for thy true and faithfull ſervice, and vouchſafe alwaies to continue all thy goodneſſe and mercies towards me, that I may truly feare, perfectly love, and carefully obey thee in all things; and by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thy holy Spirit, make me to become, and ever to continue to bee more and more thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned ſervant: And now I am aged, and fit to leave the world when thou pleaſeſt, yet while I am in it, Lord make me continually to grow from grace to grace unto the knowledge of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with faith in him rightly to pleaſe and praiſe thee ſo long as I live. And gracious Lord vouchſafe never to withdraw thy grace and favour from me, untill thou haſt finiſhed thy grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt worke of mercy, and the height of my hopes, and happineſſe, which is the ſalvation of my poor ſoule, through thine owne deare Sonne, and my only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; and when it ſhall pleaſe thee to call me away to thy ſelfe out of this vaine world, be pleaſed to give me a happy and bleſſed departure to dye in my Lord Jeſus, and in thy true
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:121289:88"/> faith and favour, that thou having pardoned all my ſins, and paſſing by my unworthineſſe, in Chriſt, thou maieſt after death receive and accept mee poore ſinner into thy grace and favour, though thy dearly beloved Sonne, in whom only thou art pleaſed, who is my righteouſneſſe, Lord, and my Redeemer; and ſo when I have left this life, I ſhall reſt in peace and ſafety, ſleep in Chriſt, and bee raiſed by him hereafter to great glory amongſt his ſervants, and may obtaine favour to be accepted into the ſociety of holy Angels and bleſſed Saints, and admitted into the glorious preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, there to praiſe and magnifie his Name, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>7. <hi>My concluſion. A Prayer to my bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH my deare Lord Jeſus, I moſt humbly begge for thy love and mercies ſake to pardon all my ſinnes paſt, that thou maieſt looke downe in pity and compaſſion on me, to heare the prayer of thy unworthy ſinfull ſervant, who doth ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty intreat thee, to vouchſafe me thy gracious and continuall helpe, protection and direction, in all my weake endeavours, wants and troubles, that ſo all my deſires wayes and actions, being begun, continued, and ended in thee, I may bee able rightly and faithfully to ſerve and pleaſe thee at all times, really to love and honour thee above
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:121289:89"/> all things, truly and carefully to feare and obey thee according to thine owne will; confidently to relye upon thee, and willingly to ſubmit to thy pleaſure in all my croſſes and calamities; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to praiſe and magnifie thy moſt worthy and holy Name, for thy great and manifold bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and benefits beſtowed upon me of thy meer grace and mercy: O my bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who art the author and finiſher of my good, and finally of my eternall ſalvation, to thee be all praiſe, honour and glory, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <head>8. <hi>Another ſhort Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord my God, have pity upon me that am a moſt miſerable ſinner, and full of frailty, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt and unable to doe any good, I earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire rightly to ſerve thee, but without thy grace and help I cannot doe it, a fit ſubject for thy great mercy. Dear Ieſus, pardon all my ſinnes paſt, and give me grace henceforth to become a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in thee, daily to attend thy ſervice conſtantly, and to performe all holy duties which Iowe unto thee faithfully; and to ſhun and reſiſt all ſinfull ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glects towards thee carefully; that ſo while I live, I may duly feare and obey thee rightly and truly to love and praiſe thee, here and for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
